flocks of birds flying together
and creating these elaborate structures,
even though each bird individually is not that intelligent,
isn't making a lot of decisions,
but there are these complex patterns
that come out of swarm behavior,
or the way that water, oceans, waves,
all of the different patterns we observe there.
There are people who say that computation is the key
to unlocking all of these systems,
and that actually they're all effectively
computational systems.
So that's the sort of really ambitious claim
to say the universe is a giant computer.
Hello, and welcome to the 32nd episode of Neo Human Podcast.
I'm Agab Bahari, an agologist on Twitter and Instagram,
and you can follow the show on liveinlimbo.com,
iTunes, and YouTube.
With me today is Ed Finn. Welcome to the show, Ed.
Thank you for having me.
It's my pleasure. Why don't we start by talking a little
about your background, the works that you've done,
and what you're focusing on now these days?
Sure. So my background is in literature
and also in journalism.
I started out my first career working for Time,
Slate, Popular Science, and I did some freelance writing.
And my sort of academic background
started in comparative literature,
and I did some computer science and some creative writing.
And then in graduate school, I went to Stanford,
and I got my PhD in Contemporary American Literature,
but still had a computational focus,
and I got involved in what some people
call digital humanities,
so how we can use computation to explore questions
in literature, questions in culture.
And so all of that was the framing for the job
that I have now. I'm an assistant professor
at Arizona State University,
and I'm also the founding director
of the Center for Science and the Imagination there,
which is its own cool and weird thing.
And that string of interest is also what led me
to write this new book,
What Algorithms Want, Imagination in the Age of Computers.
Excuse me, in the age of computing.
I should know my own title better.
And so, yeah, I've always been interested
in the intersection of computation, technology,
and the ways in which that changes how we read and write,
how we think, how it changes fundamentally
what it means to be human.
What made you interested in the beginning,
in digital humanity, as you explained?
Were you one of those kids who were watching sci-fi shows,
and how much difference do you see from the time
that you were yourself much younger than now?
I was definitely a kid who watched sci-fi shows.
I loved Star Trek. I grew up with the next generation.
I read lots of science fiction when I was a kid.
One of the most amazing things about my job, my career now,
is that I get to work occasionally with some of these writers
that I grew up with, people like Neal Stephenson.
I think one of the things that has changed since my childhood
is how much more intimate most of our lives
have become with technology.
You think about a computer.
In the 1960s, the computer was something
that was cordoned off in a special room,
and nobody was allowed in there
unless you were one of the in-crowd.
And then it was something that went onto our desktop,
and then it was in our laps,
and now the computers are in our pants.
They're getting more and more intimate with us every day.
And you can see that transition culturally, too,
even in a show like Star Trek,
where the computer was something that lived
maybe in the wall or on the ship somewhere,
but it wasn't nearly as personal as the relationships
we all have with our machines now.
Mm-hmm.
How far away from how do you think we are now at this point?
That's a really interesting question.
I think we're still pretty far away
from the kind of general intelligence AI
that Hal imagined so powerfully.
And that story, there is a handful of stories about AI
that stick with us.
Hal is one of them.
Terminator is one of them.
And I think one of the things we're gonna need to grapple
with in the next few years is telling new
and different stories about AI
that match up more to what we're actually gonna get.
So I think we're still a pretty long way away from Hal,
but we're getting very close to
and living with in a lot of ways
these more limited kinds of computational intelligence,
Siri, the kinds of intelligence
that a system like Google has
that might not be so obvious to us as the users,
but are actually very important
to creating the experiences that we now depend on.
Right.
Your book is about algorithms.
What is an algorithm?
That is an excellent question.
One of the reasons I started writing this book
is that it's actually a word that's not that well-defined.
So there's a very clear mathematical grounding.
And if you look at the proofs of computation
that Alan Turing and Alonzo Church
and others have developed over the years,
algorithm is a concept that comes out of those proofs
about what they call effective computability,
the space of mathematical problems that can be resolved,
that can be predictably resolved
within a finite amount of time.
And so an algorithm is basically just the method
by which you solve one of those problems.
But if you look at how an engineer,
a computer scientist uses algorithm today,
they might just define that word
as a method to solve a problem.
Well, that's incredibly open-ended
and it doesn't necessarily involve computers at all.
Baking a cake might be an algorithm.
Rotating your crops and different kinds
of agricultural methods might be algorithms.
And so that got me really interested.
A lot of what the book is about is the gap
between this mathematical, very ideal computational notion
of what algorithms are and what they do
and the ways that they work in the real world,
the complications and the workarounds and the hacks
and the different conflicts and manipulations
that algorithms have to go through
to make them usable for real life.
So one example is you think about UPS delivering
all of those packages every day and the routing,
the algorithms that determine how
to most efficiently solve that problem.
There's a math problem called
the traveling salesman problem.
That's the idealized version of this
where you have a bunch of points in space
and you have to figure out the most efficient way
to get between them.
And you can write a solution to that problem
in, I don't know, maybe half a page or a page
of computer code, but the solution that UPS has to use
for real life is a thousand pages long
because life is complicated.
And there are apartment buildings
that don't have anyone who's gonna answer the door
and people have pets that are gonna bite you
and you can't turn left
because it takes so long to turn left at stoplights.
There are all sorts of interesting adaptations.
And I suspect that that algorithm
is probably changed all the time
to adapt to all kinds of emergent problems
and changing situations.
Is the algorithm changes by itself
or are the operators changing it
based on the data they receive?
I think it's probably both.
I think that one thing that a lot of these companies
are working towards is algorithms that can adapt
and evolve more effectively on their own,
but they're still always humans in the loop.
And especially many of the problems
with the more sophisticated algorithms today
are kind of boundary condition issues
where the design of the program initially
just didn't consider a whole set of problems
or maybe the problems that didn't crop up
in the training data that they use
to create whatever this algorithm was.
And so you can't solve that problem
with the system that you created
because the problem by definition is outside of the system.
And so then you need humans to come in
and sort of figure out how you're gonna compromise
between the world of computation
and the world of human culture.
It's very difficult.
And I think more and more we're getting to a point
that we have to start discussing these things, right?
One of the very obvious examples,
I think the effect of automation on job markets
that a lot of people don't think
that it's because of automation.
They think it's because of, I don't know,
maybe low minimum wage
or China is stealing our jobs or something like that.
The reality is that these algorithms and machines
and automation are taking more and more and more
of our lives, making it easier.
But at the same time, a lot of people argue
that they're also very intrusive and invasive
and threatening their privacy,
whatever the definition of privacy is anymore.
Yeah, that's right.
I think that we're in this sea change.
Everything is changing through computation.
There's this layer of computation
that's popping up more and more interfaces
between us and the world and that's having profound effects.
And we're not telling very good stories about that.
So in terms of labor and the changes to the labor market,
I agree, right now there's this weird nostalgia,
this myth that we can somehow take manufacturing jobs
in North America back to where they were
in the 1950s or the 1960s.
And that's not gonna happen,
that those jobs don't exist in the same way.
Manufacturing is not the same industry that it was
50 years ago.
And the kinds of changes that had incredible effects,
often really destructive effects
in places like the steel belt in the United States,
those kinds of changes are coming
to many other industries now.
We're already hearing about robo cars.
Uber has a bunch of robo cars driving around my offices
in Tempe and Arizona.
And there are many people who drive vehicles
who are gonna be displaced in different ways.
And so we need to start telling new stories
about these very practical
and short-term consequences of automation.
Because those people are gonna be displaced,
but there are gonna be other kinds of work emerging as well.
Algorithms are not only going to solve problems,
they also create lots of problems
that can become new opportunities for employment.
But we need to think about those consequences.
We need to think about how that's all gonna play out.
Do algorithms exist in nature?
And if so, can they be considered as examples of orders
that's been resulted out of chaos
through the process of the revolutions?
So this is really an interesting question
and sort of a profound, almost a religious question.
So there are people who think that computation
and that complexity is a basic model
through which we can understand all the...
Let me start again.
There are people who believe that computation
is a model we can use to understand all forms of complexity.
So patterns, simple rule sets that create complex behaviors.
So if you imagine the flocks of birds flying together
and creating these elaborate structures,
even though each bird individually is not that intelligent,
isn't making a lot of decisions,
but there are these complex patterns
that come out of swarm behavior,
or the way that water, oceans, waves,
all of the different patterns we observe there.
There are people who say that computation is the key
to unlocking all of these systems
and that actually they are all effectively
computational systems.
So that's the sort of really ambitious claim to say
the universe is a giant computer,
that consciousness and cognition,
our brains really are computers.
They're not just like computers,
they actually are computers.
And digital.
And digital, right.
And once we have sufficiently sophisticated
modeling capabilities and we understand more
of how this machine called the brain works,
how this machine called the universe works,
we're going to be able to unlock the keys
of all kinds of different scientific knowledge.
So I'm not sure that I believe that,
but I think it's a really interesting question.
And I think you can see the ambition of that
being played out in much more practical terms right now
in the kinds of things that technology companies,
the ethos of Silicon Valley is bringing forward.
They want to make everything effectively computable.
Driving a car, finding a date, predicting the stock market,
running companies, one of the world's largest hedge funds,
announced its plans to try and automate a major part
of its day-to-day management of the company.
And you're going to see that kind of automation taking place.
So that's not industrial automation,
this is knowledge, knowledge work automation.
And that's going to be a huge transformative thing
over the next decade or two.
So I think algorithms,
if you buy the analogy,
are you familiar with the game of life?
There's this sort of mathematical game
that this guy, John Conway, a mathematician came up with
that basically just says, what if we imagined
a set of cells as little squares in a grid
and cells can interact with one another?
So coming up with this very simple model
of how life evolves or life interacts with other life.
Three or four rules, I think only.
Yeah, exactly, yeah.
And just with that tiny rule set of this very, very simple,
simplified model of how life can work,
you can do these incredible things.
You can make complex systems.
I have a picture in my book of somebody
who actually built a Turing machine,
which is sort of Alan Turing's classic groundbreaking model
of how a computational system would actually work.
Somebody's built a Turing machine in the game of life.
So that might be an example of an algorithm working in mixture.
Your book is titled,
What Algorithms Won Imagination in the Age of Computing?
What do algorithms want and how are we contributing
to what they want as users of those algorithms?
So I offer a couple of different answers
to that question in the book,
but I think that the most compelling one centers
on the roots that algorithms have in our long running quest
for knowledge.
So I tie the notion of computation
to the much older history of the enlightenment
in Western Europe and this transformative moment
when humans said, we're no longer going
to center the universe around God.
We're going to center the universe around knowledge
and understanding that we can build out.
We may not be very good at it.
It may take us a long time.
There may be many false steps,
but we can gradually construct this understanding
of the universe that's built on rationalism,
scientific observation, reproducible work.
And so in one way, and so there's a quest
for knowledge embedded in there,
a quest to understand the universe
that human curiosity is all about.
And I suggest that there's a pairing of that.
So one thing is to understand the world around you
and the other thing is to understand yourself.
So there's this twin quest for knowledge.
These are the things that we as humans always wanna do.
And of course, they overlap a lot
only by understanding the world.
Can you understand yourself and vice versa?
So algorithms want that.
And in a lot of ways,
what they wanna do is to do it for us.
I talk in the book about Google.
Google has this set of ambitions
for helping people on the quest for knowledge.
And Google actually talks about when you type something
into Google, they've used this phrase a lot
in their discussions about what they're trying to do.
They say this, we wanna help the user
on their quest for knowledge.
So you may not have known that's what you were doing
when you were looking at dog food prices on Google,
but that's what you were doing,
engaging on a quest for knowledge.
But Google says they want their systems to reason,
to converse and to anticipate.
And the first two are sort of standard,
near-term science fiction.
We want a computer that understands
what we're talking about.
We want a computer that can talk back to us.
This is like the Star Trek computer.
But the third thing is really interesting
because if Google is anticipating what we want,
then Google is wanting what we want before we do,
figuring out what we want before we do.
If you think about the auto-complete function
in Google, for example,
I don't know if you've ever had this experience.
Sometimes when I'm typing something into Google,
it pops up with its auto-complete suggestion
and it's not quite what I was going to ask,
but it's sort of close enough.
I'm lazy enough to say, okay, I'll search for that instead.
Or, hey, thousands of other people ask this version
of the question, maybe this version
is better than my version.
And so those are small instances
of this kind of anticipation
where the quest for knowledge is now something
that algorithms are doing for us.
So algorithms want to know everything about the universe
and they want to know everything about us.
And how do you see the combination
of internet of things and big data on one hand
and machine learning and artificial intelligence
on the other, which it's kind of the timing
of all of these developments at this time
is very interesting that they're all happening
at the same time in this level.
How do you see they're shaping the future of us as a specie?
So I think that they're all happening
at the same time for a very good reason.
They're all very interdependent.
You can't do this kind of powerful,
massive big machine learning project
without big data to feed it,
without the many, many results,
many, many data points to train your models more effectively.
This is how systems like Siri work.
This is how Google Translate works.
They need huge quantities of user data
in order to train the systems that they're creating.
And so the consequence of that is that
we're quantifying more and more of our lives.
We're putting more and more cameras
and microphones into our lives.
All of these new, the latest trend is sort of the Alexa
and the Google Home systems,
which are designed for convenience,
but they're also designed to get more data into the cloud.
So we have more training sets to understand
how to build these interactive systems.
And so there's some very profound consequences for that,
for humans, for our species as we do more of this.
And one of them is that our lived existence
is now more and more diffuse.
We're more and more of what we think of as our identity,
our presence, our lives lives online.
If you think about already,
if you, for many people,
and I use this example with my students,
if you lose your smartphone or you break your smartphone,
you might feel like a part of you is missing.
You feel somehow diminished as a person, right?
And somehow the smartphone is more than just a tool,
it's actually an extension of ourselves.
Or if you've ever had that experience of the phantom ring
or the phantom vibration
where you thought your phone was ringing,
it's like a phantom limb, you know?
There's a, so there's this interesting
cultural proprioception thing that goes on
where we extend ourselves into our tools in different ways.
And so as the tools we're using
are no longer just physically proximate things
that we have around things that are on our persons,
but now live in the cloud that are connected
to these much bigger and more amorphous webs,
the sense of who we are as individuals
is getting complicated in different ways.
So there's this sort of blurring of the lines
between the individual and the collective,
but the sense of collective is mediated through computation.
We might get into a stranger's car
if you're using a ride sharing service like Uber or Lyft,
and you're trusting that stranger
in a fairly important way.
Maybe you're doing this late at night,
you're getting into some random stranger's car
in a strange city,
but you're not trusting the stranger directly,
you're actually trusting the algorithm
that tells you the stranger is okay.
And that it's only through that mediating step
that the whole transaction is possible.
And I find that really interesting that it's computation,
our species is a fundamentally social species
and how we structure our society,
the tools we're using to interact with one another.
More and more of them are computational,
they're adaptive and they have their own kinds of agency.
They're not just transparent conduits,
they're actually making different kinds of choices
and filtering information in important ways.
And that's gonna really change what it means to be human
as an individual and as a member of broader groups.
One of the factors of, I think, being a human,
I keep hearing it again and again,
is ethics and morality,
that the people who agree with it,
they believe that it's a tool
that we have developed as a species,
that maybe is not objective,
but it's something that is needed
if you're going to, for example,
develop a kind of artificial intelligence
that we can rely on the decisions that it's gonna make,
that it's gonna be in our favor.
Do you think there could be an algorithm
for ethics and morality?
Do you think ethics and morality is objective
and can be made into algorithms?
Well, I think people make,
encode ethical and moral judgments
into algorithms every day.
Every algorithm comes with different forms of bias,
whether that's conscious bias
or unconscious bias, subconscious bias.
We're always making moral choices
in the ways that we build the systems that we build.
So it happens all the time.
And I think the question of objectivity
is very alluring and dangerous,
because we want to believe that these systems are fair.
We want to believe that they're objective.
And precisely because they're not human,
we can trust them in ways
that we wouldn't necessarily trust humans.
But these systems are flawed
because they're always designed by humans
and they're always gonna encode the failings
of the humans who create them.
So I think that what's really interesting
and powerful about computation
is that we can be more transparent
about the moral choices that we are making
and that we're encoding.
We can be more transparent
about the way that we create the rules.
Now, that doesn't happen very often.
Now, most of the really important computational systems,
the big commercial systems that we're all using
are walled off and protected.
They're in black boxes
and nobody wants to say anything
about how they actually work
until something really bad happens.
And then it becomes obvious
what kinds of decisions are being made.
And I think that needs to change.
There needs to be more transparency around,
especially this kind of stuff,
the moral and ethical judgments
that are encoded or the decision structures
that are encoded into these systems.
Yeah, because I'm thinking about
one of the most horrible things
that anybody can do is kill somebody else.
So we consider killing as a bad thing,
but we're killing each other every day, right?
Yes, yeah, absolutely.
And the dilemma that exists now is,
and one side I can understand
that automation, for example, in military
can be good because soldiers don't have to die.
But at the same time,
how are you going to define this robot soldier
to understand who he can kill, who he cannot kill?
What are the differences?
And because I don't think we humans know
about these kinds of things ourselves either.
We're kind of on our autopilot.
Yeah, well, if you think about
military training and the sort of
hierarchical structure of a battlefield,
it takes a lot of work to actually create a soldier
who is prepared to do that, make those decisions.
And certainly the US military thinks quite a lot
about this question of autonomous,
lethal autonomous technologies,
technologies that can actually kill people
without necessarily an active human decision at each stage.
And one argument that gets floated a lot is like,
well, the US might do it, but somebody is going to do it.
Somebody is going to build a killer robot.
And I think that in some ways,
clearly we all can sense the unease
and we all know about the warning signs.
We all know about the Terminator movies.
And you can see how things can go really, really dark
if you pursue this thing, if you pursue this line of argument.
But it's also worth thinking about all of the ways
in which computation as infrastructure
is already making decisions like this.
There's something as mundane as a city's traffic signals
and traffic control system.
There are ways that system might be geared
towards more efficiency or more safety.
And we've all probably, many people have heard now
about the notion of the trolley problem and robocars.
Is your robot car going to decide to save you
as the driver or the owner of the vehicle?
Or is it going to save the pedestrians?
If it could save three lives,
is it going to make that choice instead of saving one life?
And so this notion of computation
making life and death decisions,
I think is already real in different ways.
I don't know, I think there's something again,
existential and sort of deeply troubling
about the notion of autonomous, intelligent systems
that are out there ready to kill human beings.
But the way we'll get there is the way we've gotten
as far as we have already,
which is thinking about these systems
that are not just computation,
but they're computation combined with policy,
combined with human judgment.
And people sort of thinking of that as a big switchboard
with different levers and buttons.
And people will keep pushing the combinations
and pushing the envelope until they get to some result
that they want to.
So that's how people will rationalize
their way into killer robots.
Any technology seems to be working the best
in the societies that adapted it the best.
How are we doing as a society adapting to technology?
Because we may be using smartphones every day,
but we're not really using them to their full capacity.
We might not really understand what's going on
in this phone and the power that it has
and the power that we have in our hands
and we just using it for mundane tasks.
Well, I think that there's an ironic twist
on William Gibson's famous quote,
the future is here, it's just not evenly distributed.
All right.
And the future is here in our pockets,
but it's not evenly accessed.
And so I argue that that's not actually
the biggest problem though.
The biggest problem is that the rates of adaptation
are very different in different markets.
So in consumer culture and consumer products,
we adopt these new products very quickly
and it might take us a while to figure out how to use them,
but we're still using them.
Figuring out how the legal system,
how political systems need to change
to adapt to these new technologies,
how social realities change, that's much harder
and it takes a much longer time.
And that's where we're starting to see real problems
between the pace of technological change
and the social consequences,
the legal, the ethical consequences of that change.
Do you think our systems, political system,
education system, financial system also needs to change
because all these technologies that we are adapting as humans?
Well, financial market seems to be adapting the best
out of all of them,
but political system and judicial system
seems to be being left behind.
Well, I think that these other systems are changing.
I think if you look at the last two
U.S. presidential elections,
technology played a huge role in each of them.
And in many ways...
But none of the candidates talked about
artificial intelligence or automation.
And I've had this conversation
with a couple of guests on the show
that I don't really know if they didn't mention it
because they just didn't know about it
or didn't consider it important,
or they just didn't mention it
because their audience wouldn't care
as much as they would care about other things.
Well, I don't know why they didn't talk about it more.
I think that my guess would be that
because it's such an unknown, it's a dangerous topic.
It's hard to, if you're a politician trying to win votes,
it's probably hard to win votes by talking about AI
because there's nothing you can say
that's gonna make people more sympathetic to you.
Right.
You know, so avoid it.
But in the terms of the mechanics
of how politics actually works,
it's clear that social media, targeted advertising,
big data have all had a huge impact
on how politics works.
They had a huge impact on the result of this past election.
And that's not even talking about the seeming cyber attack,
cyber espionage aspect of this past election.
So, you know, in many ways, the game,
the political game has really been transformed.
People are actually still trying to figure out
how to deal with it.
If you think about more extreme examples,
like say the Arab Spring where,
or many other contemporary revolutionary efforts
around the world where social media was essential
to organizing and motivating people to get out there.
But of course, on the flip side,
it also presents the whole new range of opportunities
for authoritarian states to spy on people
and to identify, you know, those who are against them.
So, you know, things are changing really fast.
Maybe the most interesting example of this is China,
which has somehow succeeded
in creating a largely separate internet
or an internet that maintains fairly powerful state
censorship and control, kind of soft censorship mechanisms.
I'm fascinated by this citizenship score
that China has introduced and is gradually gonna be
implementing over the next few years,
which basically, you know, gives you a numerical ranking
of your value and your status as a citizen in China.
I had no idea about that.
Can you expand on that?
Yeah, and so I'm not an expert on this.
I hope I don't get anything wrong.
But basically, it's a number that tells you, you know,
whether you're being a good citizen or a bad citizen.
And as it was initially laid out,
if you had a good number,
you could also get certain perks.
You know, you might get faster service at the airport
or other kinds of things, or maybe you could.
And of course, it initially sounded
incredibly Orwellian to me.
But then I realized that it's basically 80% of it
is more or less what a credit score is in the United States.
And if you think about it,
a credit score is also a fairly arbitrary number
that has a huge impact on your life.
It determines whether you can buy a house or get a loan.
It may impact what kind of a job you can get.
It has all sorts of consequences.
It's very opaque.
It's very centralized.
It's very difficult to understand how it actually works
or how to change your score or improve it.
So the only difference is that in China,
they take that financial concept.
And so maybe think about the credit score in the US
in a more dystopian way.
But in China, they take that and then they add on things
like, well, if you're ordering too many video games
or playing too many video games,
your citizenship score may suffer
because that's not really civic behavior.
That's amazing.
It's also exactly like a episode of Black Mirror.
Yes, I feel like the overall Black Mirror quotient
of reality is rapidly increasing.
Yeah, it's an interesting time to be alive.
Ed's book is called
What Algorithms Want Imagination in the Age of Computing.
What made you want to write this book now?
Well, I feel that we need to understand
how these systems work better.
So my fundamental call to action in the book
is that we need to learn how to read algorithms
because algorithms are reading us all the time.
And so I don't mean by that that everybody has to go out
and learn how to program.
I mean that we need to understand a little bit more
about computational thinking and systems thinking,
how these different systems shape
our understanding of reality.
And there's some very simple lessons.
When you think about the beautiful interfaces
and just push this one button
to make everything better in your life,
which is what a lot of the rhetoric
around high-tech apps and computation boils down to,
whenever that happens, there's a whole set of things
that are hidden away or pushed off
that are not on the menu.
And so starting to think about what's on the menu
and what's off the menu is one really important lesson
so that we don't just become passive consumers
or unquestioning consumers
of these different technologies
and the social assumptions and social notions
that they embed within them.
But we start to think about what else is possible,
what other options there might be.
And that's really important because if we want to avoid
simply being the products,
when you use a website like Facebook or Google,
for the most part, we are the products
that those companies are selling to advertisers.
So if we want to be more than products,
we need to learn how to become more active
and more engaged with these systems that we're using.
And I would assume the more knowledge that the user has
about the system that they're using,
the systems also will change according to that knowledge
and become better and more adaptable.
Yeah, and this is a really profound change.
I think this is one of the first times that we have,
computation, very broadly speaking,
is the most complicated and interesting thing
that humanity has ever constructed,
at least in the space of technology.
Maybe you want to argue that a great symphony
or great work of art is more sophisticated.
But in terms of technologies,
the sort of broad network of computation
is incredibly complicated, but it's also adaptive.
And this is really new.
We now have tools that are watching us as we use them
and changing based on our behavior.
And so that's a really novel situation for us to be in.
It is a way in which we're now creating systems
that are like the human mind
in that they have a kind of plasticity.
And that's really important to recognize and understand
as we try to work out these literacies
and figure out how we can be more engaged.
Definitely.
You're also the founding director of the center
with the most awesome name ever for science
and the imagination at Arizona State University.
What is the connection between science and imagination
and how good of a job are we doing
educating the next generation
about both science and imagination?
I think that the connection is hugely important.
The mission of the center is to get people thinking
more creatively and ambitiously about the future
because we do need to start thinking about the future
as a set of possibilities, a spectrum of choices.
And the things we do today are gonna determine
which of those worlds we live in.
We all have a responsibility
in making the world that we want to happen happen.
So I've started to think that
and imagination is vital to this
because if you ask a physicist or a poet,
an engineer, an architect, a writer,
they will all tell you that imagination is crucial
to being successful in their field and their work.
And yet we know very little about
what imagination really is.
We don't really try to measure it.
We talk about it, we wave our hands about it
but we don't really try to measure it
or to support it and foster it.
And in a lot of educational fields,
it's really, you know, minimized, denigrated
and more traditional educational modes
often, you know, sort of beaten out of students
so that they become less imaginative
and more conformed to whatever, you know,
curriculum they're being fed.
And so the central argument of my work at the center
is that we need to start thinking about imagination
as a fundamental capacity that every human has.
It's a fundamental resource that's a precursor
to all the other things that make humans great.
It's a precursor to creativity and innovation.
It's a precursor to solving
the huge complex problems that we have
because if you can't think of the impossible,
if you can't make up a new word
that's gonna describe the solution to the problem,
you're never gonna solve the problem.
And so that's the kind of work
that I think we need to advance more.
We need to start thinking about
how we identify this resource, how we support it,
how we build networks so that people are getting mentored
and we're celebrating imagination as a thing on its own
and not just something that's applied.
You know, you don't just recognize it
in particular imaginative works or projects,
but we actually start to think about the capacity
behind those particular outcomes.
Absolutely, it's very important.
Do you think algorithms or computing in general
can ultimately address the subject of purpose?
I think that computation can force us
to address the subject of purpose.
You know, as we build...
So, you know, one of the long-term outcomes of automation
is going to be that we're required to do
less of the road tasks that we do now.
We can outsource more things.
Already, we outsource a lot of our memory.
You know, when I was growing up,
I needed to remember my phone number
and my friend's phone numbers, parents' phone numbers.
Now, nobody remembers any phone numbers anymore.
That's something that we've more or less
completely outsourced to computation.
It's a very simple example,
but we're doing more and more of that.
I'm really, I always use the example
of how birthdays have changed because of Facebook.
You know, once upon a time,
if you remembered a friend's birthday,
that was like a meaningful thing,
and it was significant, and you know,
only your really good friends
would actually remember your birthday.
Now, everybody knows about your birthday,
and it's become this weird...
It's just a notification.
Yeah, it's this kind of weird ritual
where you have like hundreds of people
sort of feel obligated to say happy birthday,
but do they even really mean it?
And, you know, so it's just a totally, it's totally changed.
So, I think that as we outsource more
of our basic knowledge work,
basic thinking tasks,
basic memory tasks to computation,
we're gonna really be forced to ask ourselves,
well, what do we wanna do?
What should we be spending our time on?
And I think that, you know,
computation has this purpose
that I think is fairly clear,
to make everything tractable by computation,
to make everything computable.
And whether that is humanity's purpose or not,
I think remains to be seen.
We need to decide, you know,
how far we wanna invest our culture and ourselves
in a world where everything is computable
and things that are not computable
effectively don't exist.
And to what extent we wanna think about
a world that is symbiotic, you know,
because I don't think there's any unringing this bell.
We're not gonna burn all the computers
and go back to a 19th century way of life.
That's just never gonna happen.
Unless, you know, we really screw things up
and then it's not gonna be a choice.
This is gonna be an apocalypse.
But I don't think that's gonna happen.
I think that we're gonna need to decide
when we wanna celebrate, you know, analog,
direct human to human contact, lived experience,
live experience, live performance,
being present in the moment
in a way that's not mediated by computation.
And I think those moments are gonna become
more and more precious as they become more rare.
I'm an optimist myself.
I think we're living in the best time in human history.
And, you know, it's not perfect, but what is perfect?
You know, we have to define perfect at first.
And I think technology has been equalizing
access to information clearly much better than anything.
And I think we just headed towards better days.
I think there's great reason for optimism.
And this is, I talk a lot about thoughtful optimism.
This is another one of our mantras
at the Center for Science and Imagination.
And thoughtful optimism, the way we talk about it,
means not just that everything is gonna be great,
but that if we are thoughtful and if we work at it,
if we explore the full possibility space
of what might happen,
we can build towards the best possible future.
We can work towards better things and avoid the bad things.
But, you know, it's not gonna happen on its own.
We have to work at it.
We have to invest the energy in imagining different futures.
And that's how we can make the world a better place.
Yeah, we have great tools,
but the source of creativity still comes from us.
So it depends on us how we use those tools.
Yeah, and, you know, we have to learn how to recognize
the limitations of our tools as well as their powers,
because they can be incredibly seductive, you know,
because they can seem so powerful
and they encode a lot of creativity and imagination in them.
But we need to learn
when we have to bring something extra to the table
and when to see the boundaries of the powers
that different computational tools give us.
Very true.
The book is called
What Algorithms Want Imagination in the Age of Computing
by Ed Finn.
Let me ask you a question that I ask all my guests.
If you come across an intelligent alien
from a different civilization,
what would you say as humanity's greatest achievement
and what would you say as the worst thing
humanity has done?
Well, I think our greatest achievement
is in creating a space for imagination
and recognizing this fundamental capacity
and not trying to optimize it out of human culture
in some way.
You know, even though many people have tried
in different ways, I think the very messiness,
the fecund, crazy, overflowing diversity
of human creativity, intellectual thought,
artistic practice, science, technology, business,
you know, that is a great strength for us.
And I think it's remarkable in a lot of ways
that we've been able to maintain that
and not destroy the world somehow.
But I think that, you know,
that imagination, there's a moral imagination too.
And that has been the thing, you know,
you can imagine these crucial moments
like the Cuban Missile Crisis
where a moral imagination intervened
and people, you know, took the step back
from the precipice before something really awful happened
or all of the untold stories, you know, in the Cold War,
there are several times when a flock of birds
or strange clouds or something else
set off the alarm bells in the Soviet Union or the US
and it looked like, you know,
a fleet of bombers was coming to attack
and some human being had to sit there and say,
no, you know, we're not gonna just push the button.
We're not gonna escalate this and counter attack
even though the system was saying, you know,
that's what you have to do.
So I'd say that's our great strength.
And I'd say our great weakness is the opposite of that,
is when we become so enamored of our systems
that we forget who we are, you know,
and we are so seduced by our creations
that we conform ourselves into them.
We wrap ourselves up, we try and squeeze ourselves
into these little black boxes that we've created.
And that's when I think we lose something essential
and that's when, you know,
sometimes those are ideological boxes.
You know, you think about World War II
and that's when we lose our humanity
and we can become terrible, terrible machines.
And that's when we lose our humanity and we can become terrible, terrible machines.