moving beyond the earth, leaving the solar system, moving to other stars, leaving the earth behind,
are our obligations to ourselves, our obligations to the earth itself, our obligations to life,
our obligations to the universe, and, even though Stephen doesn't use explicitly religious words,
our obligation to God. Now, this is the ethos that I recommend, which is basically a reformulation
of the Cosmic ethos in a language that is more understandable to people here and now.
Julia Prisco, welcome back to New Human Podcast, this time the 98th episode, sir.
Thank you very much for having me again. I enjoyed our last conversation last year.
Yes, indeed. It was right after the first launch of astronauts with SpaceX reusable rocket,
which I know you're very adamant in following what's going on with respect to space exploration
and SpaceX and all that, and that was my second launch that I saw, and I recently just saw my
fifth launch, which every single time it really is a spiritual experience, which again is good to
talk to you because you're talking about science technology, but also about spirituality and
religious aspect of what is going on in our civilization. So, congratulations for your new
book, which is the main reason we're having this discussion. Future is Spaceflight Meditations,
which came out recently, I believe, and it's available on Amazon and everywhere else. The
digital and printed books are available. And audiobook, is it also available?
Uh, no, no, not audio book yet. Um, so we're gonna, also because, uh, you know, I understand
that many people like audio book, the things here. I like, I like, I love reading so very much
that, you know, for me, uh, depriving myself of the pleasure of reading, uh, written words
is unthinkable. And, uh, well, but I do know that many people like, uh, like audio books.
Yeah. By the way, let me just get a copy. Great. I also show it, um, as we talk about it. Yeah,
wonderful. And this is a follow-up. Would it be fair to say that this is a follow-up to your first
book, Tales of the Touring Church? It's much less general. Uh, I would, uh, I prefer to say that it
is a zoom on one, uh, chapter in Tales of the Touring Church, the chapter where I discuss
space exploration. And since I believe, uh, that chapter is one of the most important in
Tales of the Touring Church, I thought to expand it, uh, in a standalone book. We're definitely
going to talk about it, but as I mentioned before we start recording, we'll go in public.
I want to talk to you about a blog post that you had that, uh, the title is, I have resigned from
the IEET board of directors. Would you mind if I read just the beginning of your post just so our
audience can have some kind of a opinion? Um, uh, um, I was kind of hoping to avoid that, but anyway,
let's go. Please do. I have resigned from the board of directors of the Institute for Ethics and
Emerging Technologies, IEET. I have resigned in protest against a recent decision which hasn't
been publicly announced yet. Like much of today's liberal left, the IEET has embraced certain
currently fashionable by dangerously toxic trends, identity politics, Me Too, cancel culture. These
trends start with good sentiments, but become toxic and dangerous when pushed to unreasonable
and often ridiculous extremes. And the reason I wanted to start with this is because I believe
that what's going on with respect to an underlaying of technological debate and developments that we
are dealing with, there is a war of ethos. There is a war of philosophical aspect of what it is that
we are doing, what is the purpose of it, where we are headed and why we are doing what we are
doing. And so I think this is related because in many fields, especially AI ethics, this is
almost entirely occupied by people who are coming from that political perspective, that
philosophical perspective that you can call it far left, extreme left, whatever you want to call it,
so liberal left as you're calling it. So I just want you to very generally talk a little about it
before we get into your book, just so we know what was the problem with this organization, not exactly
but just let's hear it from you.
Okay, and as a matter of fact, I do discuss these things in the book as well. And my last book,
Future is the Space Flight Meditation, is one of the very few writings in which I have gone
into any kind of detail about what I think of what's happening in the world of politics
and especially culture. I don't really like to discuss these things and in fact I almost never
write about this for essentially two reasons. The first is that it's a complete waste of time
because as things are today, you will not persuade anyone when discussing the politics and
culture. Nobody will persuade you. What will happen instead is that you will start calling
each other names and I just don't have the time for that. It's a complete waste of time. I prefer
to dedicate my time to other things. But there is also another reason why I'm kind of reluctant
to discuss these things and it is that, you know, the world in which we live today is so
toxically polarized. For example, in the United States
we have a situation where 40 percent of the people hate and are hated by the other 40 percent.
It's a very heated situation. It's not good. It's not healthy. It's not something that can lead us
anywhere good. So I kind of feel that my responsibility as a citizen is to stay in the
is to stay away from this debate. I don't want to contribute to blowing on a fire
that could become a very dangerous one so that I normally stay out of these things. In my writings
I focus on other things. In my social media posts on Facebook and Twitter I also focus on other
things. I almost entirely ignore politics just like every now and then because, you know, I think
this is the responsible thing to do. Let's just talk of something else and let's just discuss
something else. Now concerning this IEET episode, let's just say that there was a decision
taken by a very narrow majority vote by the rest of the vote
and I did not agree at all with this decision. My disagreement was so strong that I resigned
from the board and I was kind of sad of doing that because, you know, I had been one of the
co-founders of the Institute of Ethics and Emerging Technologies back in 2004
and I was full of enthusiasm at that time because I thought the Institute would
really amount to something one day but now that it has fallen to cancel culture I don't think
it's likely to go anywhere and here again I have better things to do with my time and so I preferred
to part ways as friendly as possible of course but I was just not interested in continuing to be part
of that organization. Now coming to what exactly was the episode that
prompted me to resign from the IEET. I'm not at liberty to say it and I'm not at liberty to say it
because it was a discussion among the board of an organization and the discussion led to a decision
that has never been communicated to the public as far as I am aware so that, you know, since
it's not a public decision I'm not at liberty to comment on it. Now of course many people have
guessed correctly exactly what decision I was talking about and let's just say that it's not
that difficult to guess. Yeah I think a lot of us want to leave politicization alone just so we can
do the stuff that we like but the problem is that the politicization by totalitarians is not leaving
us alone, you know, to do whatever we want to do so everything is being politicized and I think it
goes back to again a discussion that we had the first time that we talked about I think we
disagreed with respect to for example Mormon Transhumanist Association that you said that
it's actually a beneficial thing for religions to adopt into or religions to yeah adopt a modern
technological kind of a framework within themselves and this seems to be to be the same thing that
certain kind of people from certain political perspectives they are basically monopolizing
on their ethos on their perspective and then using technology in order to empower that and this is
affecting every single one of us ultimately that's that's one of the reasons that I wanted to start
with this. I can agree with that and there's also another reason why one unfortunately cannot keep
so far from politics as one would wish it is when you know the things that really interest you depend
on political decisions that may or may not be made and this is exactly the case of space flight
and this is the reason why I do discuss political and cultural issues in my book because you know
it's very good that private space flight operators like Elon Musk or Jeff Bezos are doing all the
wonderful things that they are doing but I'm not too optimistic when it comes to
to their ability to do these things
not only without government support but even in presence of some kind of opposition from the
political world and this is a very likely a risk that we will be facing you are reading of course
of this declaration that of influences that you know this space program of billionaires are not
something good and this and that and blah blah and I think there is a very real danger that
uh in countries like the United States the administration may become more and more hostile
to private commercial space flight ventures and at the same time of course we cannot
rely on the government alone to take us back to the moon and then beyond because you know
we have been waiting for that for 50 years and that hasn't happened which means that this will
not happen without some being uh changing factor like the advent of private space flight so I do
not think that our expansion into space can proceed at this moment without at least some
moderate support from the government and that means that unfortunately politics is still very
much related to space flight and of course culture overall is also very much related to space flight
and these are things that I could not ignore in a book dedicated to space flight as simple as that
yeah absolutely do you see this competition and conflict that is going on between US and China
help development of further and further technology that I would imagine that you're considering
space exploration to be the objective and goal of all of these technological advancements that
we're experiencing correct not only space exploration space expansion is not exploration
for the sake of science it's much deeper than that it is that we need to expand our habitat
our human habitat beyond uh this uh planet and uh you know is not exploring a mass to see what mass
is like is like it's more uh settling mass to enable large numbers of people to eventually live
there and then move beyond so yes space expansion is uh what I'm really interested in do you see the
conflict between US and China helps this space expansion as a matter of um survival if not
if not anything else yes it's uh it is really a matter of survival and uh you know helps uh uh it
can help in uh two different ways one is that you know uh China will just go to the moon and
will just colonize mass and uh this is the possibility that over the rest of this century
it will be China that uh leads human expansion in the solar system if this happens I think this is
good I mean what it's important for me is that humanity expands beyond the earth now whether
that humanity is American humanity or Chinese humanity or African or whatever is a very secondary
consideration to me the important thing is that we do it as human beings who does it first it's
less important and this is one of the reasons why I'm a while uh I mean I'm not a fan of today's China
on the contrary I am very critical of today's China because you know I keep reading about this
how do they call it social control system something like that
that they basically want social credit score what they basically want to achieve is a society
where everyone is monitored from the cradle to the grave 24 seven every day by the government
and of course they will be monitoring the compliance of the citizens to all that the
Chinese communist party thinks is good and well I think this is no good I'm not a fan of that kind
of social organization not at all but while I'm not a fan of the social organization system of
today's China you know I am a fan of humanity moving to settle space so if it is inevitable
that China takes the lead then I say okay why not welcome to China now of course for me
uh this is a easier to say than for an American because I'm not an American so I have
had and still have a great admiration for America I'm not a citizen I do not live in America so that
you know if it's America or China if you ask me that okay well I would like to see a continued
leadership of America but if it has to be China so be it but going back to America what I think
is that at this moment the only thing that can revitalize the US space program and make sure
that it stays vital is competition with China uh this example competition is good if there is
an immediate and credible threat that China could be about to achieve space supremacy in the
cislunar space and of course convert that space supremacy into geopolitical and even military
advantage here on the earth that I think would be something that no American administration regardless
of its political color could ever afford to ignore and I think that is happening now
and I think it is good I mean without uh China I'm not very optimistic about the US administration
to give any damn about space with China they have to yeah that's a very good point space maximalism
basically now whatever is going to happen is going to happen for as long as we get to where we are
supposed to be getting which is popularizing the solar system first and then beyond with humanity
yes I think this is a good time to read the beginning of your book and then get some
ideas from you that why this was right now was the right time to write and publish this book
you're saying in the introduction we must strenuously push toward our cosmic destiny among
the stars beginning to expand beyond the earth before it's too late is our most important task
at this moment in history many actors have important roles to play and there's room for
everyone space flight will also help find viable solutions for current developmental environmental
and social problems but the road to the stars is full of impediments and roadblocks we will not
advance as fast as we wish therefore we must keep our moods strenuous and our drive strong we need
an optimistic space flight culture oriented to the future with energizing visions of interplanetary
interstellar and cosmic futures we also need a futurist space philosophy which I totally agree
and that's exactly why I said that this war over the ethos that is now being politicized is essential
with respect to our technological advancement and space expansion
well you have read the first two paragraphs of the book and after that perhaps there is no need
that you read the rest of the book because what I wanted is to say in these very short paragraphs
exactly what the book was about but no I'm joking I think that's the thesis that is the thesis of
your very other right right right yes I'm saying the most important things here at first
that you know moving beyond the earth leaving all over the solar system one day
leaving even the solar system beyond and moving to other stars is you know it is the most important
thing because it's what we have to do it's built in our genes that's what humans do
and it's also kind of an obligation to the earth to life and to the very universe an obligation that
we have to bring life out there of course there is other life out there but we have something to add
but we have something to add and adding this something that we can add is an existential
imperative for humanity so this is my consideration number one now it's a philosophical position
and I cannot expect everyone else to automatically agree with my philosophical position if I don't
persuade them first and persuading them has to be based on arguments that they can accept
that they can accept that's why I dedicate a big part of the book to describe some
practical benefits in terms of economy in terms of national security in terms of environmental
protection social justice that space flight will bring I tried to persuade those who do not
immediately relate to my overall philosophical position that we must
expand into space because we must expand into space because it's our cosmic destiny
so this was the second important thing the third important thing is a reflection on the history
of the last few decades you know where you are younger than me a little bit and yeah you are not
on July 20 1969 you are not even alive I was I was 11 years old and I was watching this extreme
extremely bad quality video image on a black and white tv and it was like oh this is our future
and this is my future I was a kid I thought that when I turned 25 or 30 there would be a city on
the moon where I could move to this is where we landed on I'm just saying for people who don't know
yes yeah yeah we had so many great expectations all the hits of my generation and we have been
frustrated because after 1972 we have never been back to the moon now we might be back to the moon
before the end of this decade perhaps I'm not even 100% sure of that so maybe things are moving
again but one thing is true is that it has taken a lot more than we thought and things will continue
to be that way I mean is inevitable then in a complex world with technology finance politics
and culture and all that we will not advance as fast as we would like to advance on the road to
the stars but we need to keep our enthusiasm alive and here is where I come to the paramount
importance of cultural factors we need to uh engineer cultural factors that uh permit
a sustainable space program over the next few decades regardless of the roadblocks and
difficulties and lack of money and political opposition that we will inevitably encounter
this is the importance of
popularizing space this is the importance of good science fiction this is the importance of new
spiritual movements related to the space expansion of humanity these things are extremely important
and uh this is uh what my own work is mostly related to
you had mentioned in the book that you start writing it right after the first launch of
astronauts by space x reusable rocket right what made you think that this is the right time
to write this book and who exactly are you talking to is the general public or is this
a specific group of um people with influence and power what was the what was the objective
and what inspired it when it did uh you know if the those in the general public want to read my
book i can only be happy of that at the same time i understand that those who do not already agree
with me on most things may find it difficult to relate personally to my book because i say
very clearly that to me space flight is important in itself i say that space flight is the most
important thing and that is my philosophical position uh many people won't like that
from many comments that i've received many people actually don't like that
uh so that uh the book is mostly directed at space enthusiasts like me who do share
my philosophical convictions and i give them a lot of
practical arguments and consideration in support of space flight the support of human expansion
into space because i hope that they can use these arguments and considerations when talking to others
uh so i'm not credible too many because i am too much of a space enthusiast but perhaps some of my
readers are for example uh you know there is some kind of uh tension between uh enthusiasm for space
enthusiasm for space and enthusiasm for things like protecting the environment from
climate change these are seen entirely entirely erroneously in my opinion as too conflicting
the goals on the contrary i offer some arguments to understand that these are not conflicting
goals but on the contrary they are complementary goals that reinforce each other and in particular
no space expanding into space is really the only way to protect the environment of the earth
in the long term and here i'm talking of things like for example uh offshoring
some heavily polluting the heavy industry to space i'm talking of things like uh extracting the
energy from space and using it on the earth throughout uh the last few days there have been
for example uh papers about space-based solar power and this is another consideration if
is another consideration if we can extract energy up there and use it and use it down here that
means we don't have to extract the energy down here in the first place there is the possibility
and that is specifically related to the moon that mining the moon for helium-3 could provide
inexhaustible reserves of fuels for future nuclear fusion reactors and in the last few days
interesting synchronicity we are also hearing a lot of the fact that nuclear fusion is becoming a
viable operational technology at the end you know these are so many things that are conspiring
to put it like that to make people understand that if we want to protect the environment
of the earth then we need to expand into space beyond the earth that will only be beneficial
for the planet so that this is an entire chapter of my book and it's something that you know if you
have some environmentalist friends of the people who are fans of uh Greta Thunberg for example
you can use these arguments to persuade them that space is good for the environment of the earth
and then they can use these arguments to persuade other people and so on
I think one of the problems that these um a lot of people do have to even begin to comprehend
the value and viability of the idea of space expansion goes back to inequality and class
issues here on earth because for a lot of people it's a matter of how they're going to survive the
next day and so even talking about this the space is kind of they take it as offensive because
they're like we don't even care you know we just want to survive and raise our family and so when
you're focusing on space it means that you're ignoring all the problems that we are dealing
with here on earth and so you know i'm being called the leftist for talking about inequality
and like for example i'm absolutely in favor of ubi uh in you know as at so i mean they're
inevitably you know we are dealing with explosion of technological tools because they're
advancing exponentially and our experience is linear but at the same time i understand if i
talk to somebody about space expansion that person look at me in a very strange way and like i just
want my kid to survive a school and i be able to pay my rent
and this is a point that i completely understand and here again
um i made that many considerations in the book to show that it is not so
uh expanding into space does not in the long term
take uh important resources away from important things that we should
do here on the earth on the contrary uh space expansion is an enabler for all these things
and you know uh an analogy
that could be done is uh what happened in the united states in the 19th century where uh
people started to move west no uh it's not like everyone was happy in new york it's not like
everyone had enough to eat in new york uh but and it was a very wise move the government decided to
encourage and they had to spend money on this of course they decided to spend money on the
encourage and they had to spend money on this of course they decided to encourage a mass
uh movement toward the west they did that with financial incentives and things like that
and you know that didn't directly change the condition of uh the poor people in new york
not uh directly and not immediately but eventually it did what happened eventually is that the
expansion of the united states toward the pacific ocean uh was one of the factors that made the
united states the most advanced economy in the world and you know there are still some uh
people who go hungry in new york today but i think we can agree that there are not as many
as the people who went hungry uh 150 years ago so that ultimately the expansion of the habitat of the
of the u.s population that was only living on the east coast it has uh eventually resulted in
economic prosperity for everyone this is one example another example is much closer to us in time
in time and uh it is uh the development of internet technology that started in the 60s
with the financial support of the government then went kind of invisible for a couple of decades
and then started to explode in the early 80s a few years after that we started to see the
first mobile phones now uh perhaps you don't remember the first uh mobile phones oh i should have
taken one of my first mobile phones that i still have to show it on camera it was uh it was break
size yeah it was heavy as a brick i had to buy a special carrying case for it because of course
it didn't fit in my pocket and of course it costed a hell of a lot this was one year
this must have been a 90 this must have been like 94 95 something like that
and uh something that many people say is that well okay these things that you have to pay
two thousand dollars for a mobile phone is an insult to the poor and i can i can understand
if some people felt insulted seeing the others on the road with an expensive mobile phone
but what we used to say is that okay look we are at a very early stage of a new technology
what will happen because that's the evolution of important technologies that the price of these
things will go down and down and down and at the same time the performance of these things will go
up and this even if we cannot see exactly how right now will entirely change the world
in a couple of decades and that is exactly what happened because now a mobile phone doesn't cost
money i mean if you don't want to spend money the phone company will give you the mobile phone for
free if you have a contract with them and the performance of the phones you know is uh
is uh phenomenally better and it was uh 20 years ago and now i don't think i know anyone
doesn't have a mobile phone and at least if we stay in the western world this is also true in the
uh most under-privileged inner cities in the u.s and europe essentially everyone has a mobile phone
and uh the impact of everyone having a mobile phone is overall good
i'm persuaded of that and the same will happen with space now space flight cost a lot of money
and at times is difficult to see to see exactly uh why we are going to space and what we are
going to space for but just give time to time just wait for a few decades and it seems evident
from so many early warning signs that we can see right now that in a few decades you know it will be
it will be very evident inside why we decided to expand into outer space and it will be evident
that the overall impact on humanity will have been good i'm sure of that yeah um another example of
people being offended by expensive new technology was uh google glass that when it came out we
talked a lot about that in this podcast that when it came out people were being attacked who were
wearing them there were also an aspect of like an elitist aspect to it that you couldn't just go out
and buy it you had to be chosen and be given those devices and this is almost 10 years ago that people
were being attacked around silicon valley in san francisco all these big tech buses were being
attacked and now politically this is coming from the right there is a backlash against technology
altogether and there is a revival of traditionalism they're saying we have to go back to traditional
roots and they all seem to be connected in a sense that technology is evolving exponentially
and we we can't even comprehend it if we are not seeing the big picture and a lot of people not
only they get offended they get really scared and this being scared has real world political social
and cultural consequences that can affect what you're saying the advancement of technology is
not as fast as maybe we want it to be or as it needs to be in order for us to survive as a species
as a civilization i prefer to be optimist and the thing that even if things will be difficult
i prefer to hope that we will make it and even more important than that i prefer to do all the
little things that i can do to get closer to that objective but you know uh back to the tension
between uh technology and our cultural traditions i don't think that there has to be an opposition
i think we can uh advance technology even advance technology uh very fast
uh within our uh cultural traditions i mean it would be a long discussion but uh i'm not
i'm not immediately persuaded that it is not the case do you feel the same way about democracy as a
system of governance because you mentioned china advancing really quickly it in a way is as a
consequence of a central structure of authority that they have and here in the u.s. all the places
basically that are developing and doing research about these technological advancements they are
being run as centralized uh points of authority centralized structures of authority like whether
it's darpa or a spacex or google i'm not um i'm not really fundamentalist in this i think there
is room for many different organizational models you know i do tend to have a slight preference
myself for decentralized models but if it happens that you know the weakest solution
to an important problem can only come from a centralized structure then i would say why not
this is the same kind of reasoning that i was making before saying that you know
uh government support is still necessary for spaceflight and space expansion we cannot i mean
there is uh nothing bad in the idea of government itself does nothing bad about the idea of
government itself i guess it's just a form of government no yes it's the focus is a
is a management thing some organizational structure can be better than other
organizational structures for some specific purposes and that's it not really fundamentalist
here i welcome uh many different possibilities it just seems like the long-term big picture kind
of view is maybe incompatible with the system that people run on the basis of being elected
and then re-elected rather than being focused on some kind of an objective and determine policy
on that basis rather than you know determining policy based on the next century rather than the
next four years this is this is the reason i'm saying but right but yeah i understand this point
but um you know here again it comes down to whether we are intelligent and pragmatic enough
to work together with the people who do not think in exactly the same way as we do
and as a matter of fact you know uh reading the news now and especially through the social media
you can develop the impression that you know people on the left will never accept
or to work together with people on the right and the other way but you know it hasn't always been
like that as a matter of fact this is quite a new development that has accelerated in the last few
years in the past it was a perfectly normal thing for example in the united states for uh
for uh democrats and republicans to push a bill that uh was good for both
um that were i mean this is really an important thing in fact uh you know um
um space flight the advancement of space flight needs bipartisan support
otherwise the rocket just doesn't take off
uh from the inception of a space uh program to its completion it does
take a long time it may be 10 it may be 15 years it may be decades and you know this can only be
compatible with uh a system like in the united states or many western democracies where the color
of the government changes every few years it can only be compatible with this if there is bipartisan
support and in fact i think this is uh if uh we keep talking of uh government space there has to be
bipartisan support but since the government can also impact the space uh commercial space
could also impact the space uh commercial sector you know uh the government could kill
elon musk with over regulation anytime so that uh you know it's not only that we need bipartisan
support for government space program we need bipartisan support for space flight it's safe
even in the private sector especially in the united states in western europe and uh you know the
exhortation that um uh i give many time in this book is that you know uh politicians uh i'm not
going to read but i'm trying to quote from memory or something like that i say somewhere that
politicians of the left and politicians of the right should just uh uh let go of the
toxic aspects of their respective ideologies should just let go of their hatred for each other
and just sit the fuck down to define programs that uh everyone is willing to live with
for a while this is exactly what needs to happen in space in the west now in china they don't have
this problem or at least this problem is not apparent so that yes as you were saying uh china
can think long term but this doesn't mean that we cannot think long term and you know uh the
chinese can think long term in their own way uh their way is not our way so we must learn to think
long term in our way and not ready to let democracy go you know uh when you first started talking
about democracy came to my mind my two favorite descriptions of democracy so the first i don't
know who said that first is that democracy are uh two uh wolves and the lamb deciding
democratically by majority vote what to have one of the founding fathers i don't exactly remember
who but one of the founding fathers said it uh perhaps somebody important say that and uh the
uh the other and i think it was uh sir winston churchill who said it first is that democracy is
the worst system of uh government with the exception of all the other systems so that you
know even uh in view of the structural weakness of uh democracy that is quite evident in the story of
the two wolves and the lamb i still think democracy is better than the alternatives
that we have been trying so far so i just found that it was said by benjamin franklin democracy
is two wolves and lambs voting on what to have for lunch liberty is well armed lamb contesting the
vote i'm a big fan of the second amendment i think it's it's makes a very different uh
apparent different and very obvious different when um the populace are i didn't know i
i didn't know the second half of the citation yeah but what you're saying is totally sensible
because space flight and the space expansion is about humanity it's not about left and right
democrat and republican these are all blocks that we are passing through to get to the point of
of first surviving as one humanity and then expanding into you know we might be human plus
or whatever that comes next after humanity just that it seems like there is a battle right now
about what is the definition of humanity and therefore what is the goal of humanity that's
where we are it seems like it and i think you're a very um valuable kind of a perspective because
you're bringing spirituality and quote unquote god into it because that is the ultimate uh purpose
and ultimate ethos of what humanity as a collective regardless of whatever kind of ideology we have
can strive towards and can um can build towards that kind of an objective that is god-given for
lack of a better term right um we don't even have to use explicitly the term god i mean uh
you finished the book with some people won't yes yes yes i do
i finished the book with a quite um unconventional concept of god
unconventional in the sense that my god is not a supernatural god and uh i think the concept of
supernatural doesn't make any sense to me because if you define nature as all that exists then
supernatural doesn't exist by definition so everything is uh uh natural now of course
that we may have to expand your definition of uh nature to make room for things that do exist in
nature so uh there is an overall organizational principle in the universe that kind of uh pulls
the universe above toward the increasing levels of complexity and uh you know generates uh
intelligent life well first it generates non-intelligent life then it generates
intelligent life then it may generate one day super intelligent life and one aspect of this
uh principle of uh increasing complexity and penetration of consciousness and intelligence
in the whole universe one aspect of this is that we must go to space we must leave the earth we must
bring our dna our uh calcification of the universe we must go to space we must leave the earth
our dna our culture everywhere in the universe among the stars this is a
a universal principle that you don't have to call god but you can call god if you want
and uh i think this is what uh uh traditional religions refer
to in the most abstract parts of their theology then besides that you have the evolution of
evolution of super intelligent itself you know we will go to the stars we'll expand among the stars
and uh humanity itself uh uh will be changed we will uh edit our genome we will perhaps uh
upload our minds to uh computational systems much more powerful than a biological uh brain
we will do all these things and we will ascend toward god-like uh levels and conditions that uh
uh we probably are not even are not even able to imagine now and so many countless other alien
civilizations in the universe must have done exactly the same things and this is another reason
why you must go to the stars to find uh teachers among the stars civilization much more advanced
than ours and uh one of the things that i have in the last chapter of my book that you were
referring to is a wonderful quote by Stanley Kubrick the director of 2001 space odyssey
where uh you know i don't remember to quote by heart but uh if you read the book just read it
is uh you know he's saying in very few words that out there in the universe there exist uh beings
uh so inconceivably advanced from our point of view that we can only call them gods
whatever else would uh whatever other name will be a lack of honesty so there are uh gods out there
and this is another religious concept what um stanley cubrick did not say but his uh
collaborator Arthur C. Clarke uh did say that is that we ourselves if we are lucky and if we do
things well we ourselves may become a god-like civilization in the future
and that again is among the ultimate objectives of our quest to go to the stars we have to go to the
stars out there to do all that yeah and now there are philosophical and there i say religious
attempts are being made in order to create some kind of an ethos on the on this exact basis that
you're saying whether it's simulation hypothesis or theory or jason georgiani's prometheism
yeah these are all coming from traditional religions breaking the mold and moving towards
whatever that is coming next which i think they're very valuable yes in fact i've been
listening to your interviews with uh jason georgiani and your two separate interviews
with the recent work yes basically when ritz says that his version of the simulation hypothesis
is a necessary adaptation of the metaphors that the religion use to communicate to people
i think he's uh totally right one moment i think i need to put the power cable
here we go
amazing i had jason georgiani twice i don't know if you listen to both of them
uh no yeah i had them i'll look for them yeah the first one was when his prometheism book came out
maybe a few months ago and the second one was after that yeah after that he wrote a book uh called
closer encounters about ufos and this came out basically as a response to the government the
us government report on ufos oh i need to read i really like him i mean he's a very controversial
kind of a figure because of you know some of his views but uh i think he's extremely unique and he
dares going to places that you know not that many people i don't think you know can't even begin
you know can't even begin comprehending the possibility of them i like his book maybe i didn't
100 percent of it but i certainly did like a good 80 percent of it yeah excellent well this is a
pleasure that you've been listening to the interviews that i've done with them two of my
favorite guests definitely what are some of the characteristics of the ethos that you would
recommend for humanity to have in order to move uh to the point that we can decide as humanity
rather than left and right black and white you know democrat and republican and all that
is uh
uh i don't have a name for it the name that comes closer to my mind is cosmism is uh from
the russian cosmist philosophical movements that was uh that started in russia between the end of
19th century and the beginning of the 20th century but uh you know they they used a language that
we find very much outdated now and if you read the writings of a russian cosmist philosopher
you wouldn't understand much and perhaps you wouldn't like what you read thinking of
more contemporary examples
because
talk of an excellent book written uh to me one moment i just need to tell my wife to
turn the water off yeah it was background noise
uh there was there is an author called steven wolf who wrote a great book called the obligation
by the way if you never had steve on the podcast you should definitely on on the show you should
definitely have him it's a very short book and uh he says much better perhaps the same things
that i say that you know all the things that we have been discussing uh moving beyond the earth
leaving the solar system moving to other stars leaving the earth behind are our obligation
to ourselves our obligation to the earth itself our obligation to life our obligation to the
universe and even so steven doesn't uh use explicitly religious words our obligation to god
now this is the ethos that i recommend which is basically a reformulation of the cosmist ethos
in a language that is more understandable to people here and now let's fill this obligation
that we have to ourselves into the universe around us to contribute to awaken the universe
to life consciousness super intelligence and perhaps god-like nature this is our obligation
this is what we are here for when uh earlier you said of course there are excuse me of course
there are other lives beyond earth on what basis do you say that on what kind of life
on what kind of life are you talking about conscious life or just like bacterial life or bacteria
bacteria i guess it could be conscious too but you know what i mean bacterial life and animal life
and the human life life and conscious life and super conscious life there is room for all possible
uh source of life as a matter of fact i'm persuaded that no life is not an accident it's not uh the
result of uh excuse me one moment i have to pay my life again that uh she wants to cook dinner so
things just happened just yeah just a five uh just five more minutes after that
okay but this uh but this thing about life is important you know uh life is not a random
accidents that happened as a result of a random fluctuation that uh happened but could not
have happened i have a completely different view i think that the very loss of fundamental physics
are wired to eventually reduce complexity life consciousness intelligence
super intelligence and godliness it could not have been another way it has to be this way
one consequence is that there is life everywhere it's not ruled out that we will find some
elementary examples of life here in the solar system for example there is a mission
planned to one of the ice moons in the outer solar system that may have an ocean
which may have more life we will find something in the solar system and when we eventually move out
to the stars we will find all sorts of life from simple life to societies like
our human civilization to inconceivably more advanced alien societies we will find all that
great i'm not gonna keep you much further from the delicious dinner that i'm sure your wife is
preparing it my best to your wife as well julio prisco's book thank you very much book is called
future with space flight meditations uh check him out all over uh internet wonderful i'm also
showing uh showing the cover and the amazon page and all that um just please share your message
to the humanity as the final saying of this episode of podcast
uh let's just go to space
so