One problem that we saw with the social bot
is that if we allow it to teach itself,
it becomes a disaster.
It could be a disaster.
It'll end up like the rest of us bastards, right?
Hello, and welcome to the eighth episode
of Neo Human Podcast.
I'm Aga Bahari at Agologist on Twitter and Instagram,
and you can follow the show on iTunes or liveinlimbo.com.
With me today is Professor Michael Lynch.
Thank you so much for being with us, Michael.
Well, thanks for having me.
My pleasure.
I think it would be much better than me introducing you
if you introduce yourself,
and tell us a little bit about your background
and what you're doing now.
So I'm a philosopher by training and by profession.
I teach at the University of Connecticut,
where I also direct the Humanities Institute,
and I'm also the PI on a large research project
on public discourse and the barriers to public discourse
and concepts like intellectual humility.
And I'm also the author of this recent book,
The Internet of Us,
which is the book that I just put out from Norton.
Yeah, and that's the reason that I got to know you.
Right, right.
So yeah, and that book is what we might,
say it's a bit of philosophy on a topic
that I think philosophers haven't,
well, they haven't ignored,
they haven't really focused on as much as I think they might,
which is the philosophical implications
of information technology, you might say.
That's what this book is about.
And philosophical implications,
particularly with regard to how we understand knowledge,
because not only do we live in the so-called information age,
we also live, as many people say, in the knowledge age.
We talk about the knowledge economy
and knowledge workers, right?
And we think about the fact that people's ability
to get knowledge and become trained as knowledge seekers,
that is, have a higher education,
impacts their life in the economy economy.
So knowledge is sort of a central topic for us in our lives.
And it's partly a central topic,
just because we do have these incredible devices
that we all use for accessing information.
So it seemed to me that,
as somebody who works on epistemology,
which is the study of knowledge,
that it was high time that we started thinking
as philosophers and as intellectuals
about what these changes and how we distribute,
access and produce knowledge,
because of information technology, these changes,
how these would actually affect our understanding
of knowledge itself and its value.
Would you say that our philosophy in general
is in need of updates because of our technology?
Yeah, I think it is.
I mean, the book is divided into two parts.
In one part, I talk about how certain old,
classic philosophical problems,
problems that have been around for thousands of years,
or as my students say,
that I've been discussed for thousands of years,
sort of old philosophical problems,
have been reached, sort of given new life
by our digital form of life.
I talk about our life in the infosphere
as a sort of what Wittgenstein would call form of life.
That is, we have a sort of ways of acting now
due to how we interact with information technology
that we don't even sort of notice.
These are sort of behaviors and habits
that we engage in on a daily basis,
having to do with access and information
that we almost never notice anymore.
And that fact, the fact that these things
have become so much part of our life
that is these devices and so forth,
and our analytic techniques
that allow us to use these devices,
the fact that they've become so much part of our life
has made these old problems new again.
And so let me give you an example of that.
An old classic philosophical problem is
how do we rationally resolve disagreements
between each other over competing values and facts?
That's something that's been around for a long time.
How do we rationally resolve our differences
of opinion over values, for example?
Can we do that?
Some people might say yes,
some people might say cynically no, we can't.
Politics at the end of the day
has to become war by other means and so forth.
Well, the way in which information technology
is impacting this is really sort of funny and curious.
We have all, we have, you and I,
by virtue of just accessing our phone,
have tremendous amounts of information at our disposal,
more than most humans have ever had combined.
Right? Absolutely.
Is that absolutely the case?
You're doubling the knowledge of humanity every year.
Indeed, indeed, and maybe even,
that might even be underestimating it.
Just simply because the,
I mean, partly this is a sort of inside,
but the use of data analytics,
our sophistication in those methods
is really just shot up in the last couple of years,
I think, and that is,
it may be increasing even more than that,
but let's say it's doubling it.
Now, what you might think that that sort of from a sort of,
if you just sort of heard that,
you heard somebody like living
just even 50 years ago heard that, right?
And they could believe it.
They might think, wow,
then we should be closer to solving certain problems, right?
We should be closer to solving
not just certain technological problems,
but also maybe policy problems.
I mean, if we have all this information,
then surely if we put our best minds at it,
we'll come to greater agreement on matters
like climate change or the environment,
as they might've said years ago, right?
But what we're finding actually is that
the disagreements in policy
and disagreements over matters of fact even
are becoming more and more entrenched,
even though we have access to greater amounts of information.
And why is that?
Well, partly it's due to a fact
that a lot of people have commented on in the digital age,
which is that when we access information online,
it's not just all the information.
Because there's so much information, we have to sort it.
We have to make decisions, who we're gonna check,
what sources we're gonna rely on,
what friends we're gonna accept, so to speak.
And that puts us in,
and this is the point that a lot of people comment on,
is that puts us in sort of information bubbles.
But the point that I think is new,
and this relates to this sort of perennial
philosophical problem, is that these information bubbles
have gotten to the point where our disagreements
are no longer just over values.
They're no longer just over the facts.
They're actually over whose sources
are the most reliable for deciding what the facts are,
and what even a fact is, is I think an issue right now.
So that's essentially an old philosophical problem,
is being given new life by the very technology
that we might have thought would have solved it.
It's the concept of the more we know,
the more we know we don't know.
Well, in a sense, in one sense, that's a good,
yeah, I mean, in one way, that's right.
Another way of thinking about it, though,
is that, and this is something, the subtitle of my book
is Knowing More and Understanding Less
in the Age of Big Data.
And I think we actually do know more.
We don't just have more information,
we do actually know more.
I often feel without my phone, I'm just 100% dumber.
But the sense in which we know more
is a very minimal sense.
When we know from, most of the times,
by using apps, for example, not just Google searching,
but actually using an app, let's say,
to perhaps an interactive app,
the sense in which I know is the minimal sense
in which, if I'm lucky enough to get accurate information,
form an accurate belief from using that app
about some subject matter, let's say the weather.
Then that belief will turn out to be knowledge.
If it's accurate, it's based on a sort of reliable source.
And that's the minimal sense of knowledge
in which we gain knowledge
from interacting with digital sources.
And in that sense, we know more.
But the problem is that, because we do know more in that way,
we have more reliable sources checked,
that actually makes us overconfident
that we actually know more than we do.
I think sometimes we don't actually think,
and we should think, that we know less than we think we do.
But I don't think that often happens.
I think we do know a little bit more,
but a little bit of knowledge is a dangerous thing.
And what happens is that we don't know
what happens is that people think
that they know even more than they do,
just because they have this information right at hand
and they've been able to use it so far
to find out, let's say, what the weather is,
or even what the level on a particular,
I have an app on my phone that allows me
to detect the level of a piece of wood,
let's say, it's a carpentry app.
That's an amazing little app, by the way.
What is it called?
Carpentry level.
There's about 10 of them, but there's,
so I can know things, like this one piece of wood is level,
by using that app.
But I shouldn't think that that fact
makes me an expert carpenter either.
What do you think it takes for a knowledge
based on evidence to become a policy?
I'm living in Canada, and what we're witnessing
in the United States is that there are senators
and congressmen who are arguing that
there is no global warming because there's a snow outside.
Yes.
So those are the people who are basically
are affecting the progress of technology
and knowledge and everything because of public policy.
What do you think it will take for the people
like yourself who are creating the new ways
of understanding knowledge to convince the politicians
who are mostly conservative and business oriented
to accept the facts so we can all move forward?
Well, that's a really, really good question.
I guess it's a sort of great follow up
to the point that I had raised is that right now
we are disagreeing over our sources of evidence
and even over whether evidence is important.
So how do we move forward from there?
I mean, on the surface, at first glance,
it seems impossible because once we disagree
over whether evidence is important,
what sort of evidence could I possibly give you
to think that it is?
Yes, exactly.
All right.
So I think what we need to do is shift
slightly different tactic.
I think what we need to do is to convince people
that share at least some sense of democratic commitment
to a sense of sovereignty of the public.
And not all the folks that I'm gonna,
what you might have in mind might be committed to this.
But some of them, let's say are,
they do think that democracy is all things in equal,
better form of government than alternative forms.
If they do think that, then I think what I can do
is make an argument that appealing to evidence
is actually an essential decision-making procedure
for democracy.
Because it's only by paying attention to your evidence,
as opposed to your moral,
you know, your spiritual character, for example.
It's only by paying attention to the evidence
you give me for your beliefs
that I truly respect you as an independent thinker,
somebody who's capable of making up their own mind
about how to vote.
And the same goes for me on the other side, right?
I mean, I've got to be willing to take the evidence
of the conservatives insofar as, you know,
if somebody has some evidence,
and take it seriously.
Because only by then I can respect them
as full participants in the democratic process.
And without that respect,
without the sense that we can mutually respect one another,
then there is no point of talking about a democratic process.
Because democracy is founded on the idea of equal respect,
that we treat each other as fellow participants
in the project of democracy.
So would you suggest that we perhaps,
in need of upgrading our democracy and political system
along with our philosophical system
because of the growth and advancement of our technology?
I think, yeah, I mean, I think our growth
and advancement in technology has been tremendous aid
in some ways to democratic practices.
It's given us, because it has given us the ability
to acquire more information and data
about things like climate change.
I agree.
Without the techniques that mathematicians
have been able to give us,
applied mathematicians for data analytics,
some of the data that we've been able to collect
on climate change wouldn't have never been collected.
So it's only because of technology and our advances
that we're able to do that.
I think what we do need to do is to make sure
that our personal citizens' uses of technology,
the uses of, let's say, social media,
that we understand the ways in which we're using social media
both can reflect our biases and our prejudices.
It's, you know, when we talk about social media,
the social part is really important.
Absolutely, yes.
And that could be really great. It could connect us.
It's awesome to be able to connect
with your old friends on Facebook.
But it's really important to realize
that the biases and prejudices
that infect our social relationships offline,
also affect our life online.
And in a sense, that's trivially obvious.
We think, oh, we all know that.
And yet, we often ignore that fact
when we draw conclusions from, let's say,
about what to believe from something
that somebody posted on Facebook
because they're in our circle of friends, right?
I mean, we tend to, you know, there's a lot of evidence
to show that the sorts of interactions
that we engage in, social media in particular,
tend to lead our perfect situation
in which for us to reflect our quick, implicit biases,
partly because the interactions are so quick
and not often reflective.
They're not Twitter, for example.
I use Twitter. I love it.
But it's not a medium that is really,
it's not the best medium to use
if you're interested in another truism,
reflective, critical engagement.
It doesn't lead to these sorts of conversations.
It's true. It's true.
Well, I mean, with 140 characters, how far you can go?
Yeah. I mean, some people have been incredibly creative
at that, right? There are people that can,
but most of the time, you can't go very far.
But it's interesting, when you mention your life online
and your life offline, Twitter is a very good example
how the 140 limit characters
has affected the news programs.
Indeed.
And our ability to absorb information,
we need something fast and to the point.
And that can be manipulated very easy in that way.
How difficult do you think it's becoming
to differentiate the life online and life offline?
Because on one side is the software advancement
like machine learning, big data and hardware advancement,
like a virtual reality and augmented reality.
How difficult it will become in the coming years
to tell the difference between the two?
Well, I think it's gonna become even more difficult.
And I think it already is.
You're right that there is for many people,
for many of us, I mean, many people listening,
not just some people over there, for all of us,
there are ways in which the two lives
have become very blurred.
And that's particularly, that blurriness happens
right out of the area that I'm interested in,
in knowledge acquisition.
You think about how you know
most of the things you know now, right?
And what's the first thing that you're gonna do
if you have a question?
First thing you're gonna do is Google it,
at least if you're me.
Yeah, you use a term called Google knowing.
Yes, exactly.
So would you expand on that?
Sure, so Google knowing is not just knowledge by web search,
although it's certainly that.
It's the sort of knowledge that we acquire,
what I earlier called this sort of minimal knowledge,
that by digital interface.
So it's the sort of knowledge we might acquire
from my little level app,
but it also might acquire from,
we might acquire from a smartwatch and from a web search.
And I think it's right there at that,
that the concept of knowledge is where right now already
our online life and our offline life is fuzzy,
because what we do in our offline life
is often dictated by what we know or think we know, right?
So what we do in our ordinary everyday life,
I mean, from mundane examples,
like we don't have to talk about something important
like climate change.
We just talk about like, you know,
which restaurant we go to is dictated by what we know.
And how do we figure out what we believe we go online?
So much of our offline life is already heavily impacted
by what we do online.
I mean, and the reason that Google knowing,
and well, the return to your earlier question,
I mean, is that gonna increase?
Well, sure, I mean, you know,
Larry Page, the CEO, or Google,
one of the founders of Google, certainly thinks that,
I mean, he's in the book, I quote him in saying that,
no, one day we'll have, he says, he hopes,
that we'll have an implant that will allow us,
a neural implant that will allow us to
just think of a question, he says,
and then get the answer, right?
And if he's right that that was to come around someday,
or even something closer, like an actual Google Contact,
which they have been working on, right?
They have a project, it's not very far along,
but they have a project in which they'd like
to take Google Glass and put it farther closer to the eye.
Right.
So even if that neural implant never comes to be,
I mean, once you get the Google Contact
as a possibility, and I think that could come along,
then I think things will be even blurrier.
I mean, one way to think about it, so,
Sergey Brin once said, when they introduced Google Glass,
he said, the greatness of this technology is that
it's going to get technology out of the way,
and what he meant by that, I know what he meant,
he meant we won't have to fumble with our phones, right,
to get it up on the internet,
so I understood what he meant.
But it's sort of ironic, isn't it,
because Google Glass or Google Contact
get technology out of the way
by literally putting it in the way of innovation.
Right.
And if that isn't a metaphor for this blurriness
that you're talking about online and off,
I don't know what is.
Isn't it the kind of a natural evolution, though,
becoming a biological and technological hybrid,
or in other words, human 2.0?
Right.
Yeah, so, I mean, the cyborgian of the human
is certainly something that a lot of folks
are interested in, and I think have been writing about,
and I'm interested in, too,
and I think we are moving towards that, human 2.0.
And there could be a lot of benefits from that.
I think there's a lot of benefits
from information technology,
including certain implants of various sorts
that are wired to the internet in healthcare, right?
I mean, there's lots of benefits that are,
I think, could come from that.
So I'm not saying that I'm just blatantly
antagonistic to this.
What I'm interested in, at all,
what I'm interested in is thinking through
the consequences of some of this technology,
both ethically and epistemologically,
and it would be great if once in our life,
and once in human history,
we actually thought through some of these consequences
before we actually went and made the technology,
but I don't really know about that.
Yes, me neither.
That would be, that's never happened before, so.
What do you make of the court case between Apple and FBI?
They dropped it, and then they came back and said,
no, we need Apple, because-
They dropped it, they said, oh, no, just kidding.
They actually didn't.
What do you make of that?
But first of all, do you think the concept of privacy
does even exist anymore?
And if so, how we can protect it, and if not,
what is the option going forward?
Yeah.
Okay, that's a bunch of really difficult questions
and good ones.
So, yeah, let's put off the Apple case for a second.
I think that raises a bunch of interesting questions,
but let's talk about, maybe I'll talk about your more,
the general questions about privacy first.
So does the concept of privacy,
is it even relevant anymore?
That's one way of understanding what you were asking me.
I think yes, it is.
So I don't think it's an outdated value.
I think Jeremy Rifkin and others have argued
that it's a bourgeois value, it was an architect
of the Victorian age and so forth and so on.
I think that's just a mistake.
Yeah, Jeremy Rifkin is the author of the book,
Zero Margin Society, a very interesting concept.
Yeah, please continue.
Yeah, indeed, and I think it is a very interesting book,
but I disagree with him on this point.
I think that one reason to think that it's not an outmoded
notion is to realize what the roots of the notion are.
If we think about why privacy matters
and its philosophical roots,
you'll see that it actually is based, I think,
in our very psychology as human beings.
So part of what we think makes a difference
between you and I and minds in general
is that our thoughts are, in a sense, our own.
We can have this conversation
and we can sort of infer what we're thinking
and so forth as you do.
But of course, what makes you different than I
is that your thoughts are your thoughts,
my thoughts are my thoughts,
and you can share those thoughts with me,
but if you don't, then I'm not necessarily
gonna be able to feel or experience
what you've felt or experienced.
They're private in that sense,
and that's the fact that very term
that philosophers have used for a long time,
that a mark of a human being's psychology
is that we have a special relationship to our psychology
that we don't have to us, to other people's psychology.
And we value that.
We value our sort of subjectivity, our individuality.
And as a result, we value the sort of privacy,
the control and protection
that we can give to our own thoughts.
And that's really, I think,
the philosophical root of privacy.
And I don't think that the notion of,
I don't think individuality or subjectivity
is something that was just recently invented.
I think it's a human being's been around
for longer than that.
But why does it matter?
That's a different question.
Why does privacy matter?
I think privacy matters both for, still today,
for certain obvious reasons and less obvious reasons.
The obvious reasons are that,
the reason I don't want the NSA poking around in my emails
is partly because they might do,
they might, I don't know what they're gonna do
with that information, right?
And we, in general, we don't want people
breaking into our phone,
whether it's the FBI or otherwise,
because that gives them some measure of control.
If they know certain information about me,
they could control me in some way.
And so, that's a sort of obvious point, right?
But even that obvious point
is sometimes missed by certain politicians.
So, Mike Rogers, for example,
a Republican, conservative Republican
from Pennsylvania in the United States,
at one point in a congressional hearing said,
look, I don't know what this problem with the NSA is.
If people don't know about the fact that they're being,
their privacy is being, then what's the harm?
If you don't know, there's no harm.
Which was really only consoling
to peeping Toms everywhere, right?
Do you think he, for example, really believes in that,
or he's using that as an excuse to push his agenda,
which is a party agenda?
Well, that's a perennial, I mean,
let me put it this way.
I think almost the more charitable reading
is that he actually believed it when he said it,
and he just hadn't thought it through.
That's the more charitable reason.
That's a great quality for a politician.
Because if he's using that sort of reasoning
to push his party's agenda, then good luck to him.
Yeah.
So, I think it might've been he just,
he hadn't thought through the logic of what he was saying.
Of course, we think in some ways that if we don't,
if you break it in my house and into my computer
and steal all my financial information,
then even if I don't know about it until later,
like when you drain my bank account,
it's still bad when you did it, right?
So, partly because of consequences.
But there are even less obvious,
but more fundamental reasons to be concerned about privacy
and information privacy.
And that has to do with our autonomy.
It gets back to my first point
about the origin of the notion.
Look, if you, suppose you, again, break into my phone
or whatever, you hack my phone,
and you get the content of my phone,
various contents, the emails and the like.
But suppose you do that only as a scientific experiment,
but you don't do anything with it.
You just, you don't use it to blackmail me or anything,
right, or whatever.
Is it still wrong?
Well, it is.
And a side to that is still wrong
is that we find things like that,
or people, an older example would be somebody reading
your diary or something, right?
But not doing anything with it.
Would you, if you found that out later, right?
Even though that later, like, you know,
you realize that person never did anything,
you would still be creeped out by that.
Of course.
You shouldn't do that.
Well, why not?
Well, because, because you can imagine the other person saying,
well, I never did anything, right?
Well, that wouldn't matter.
Because you violated my autonomy.
I didn't choose to share that information, right?
In this case, or you didn't choose to share it.
So what I did is I sort of made the decision
to share or not to share moot.
It would be, it's similar to if a doctor gives you
a drug without your permission,
even though the drug helps you out, there's a problem there.
Why do we think it's a problem?
Because I didn't get, I wasn't in on the decision.
The decision was made for me.
Now, the doctor case shows us that, in fact,
there are times where we think that privacy invasion
are justified, just as we think that there are times
in which the doctor giving you a shot
or doing a medical procedure is justified
even if you're not conscious, right?
Because in an emergency, right?
We don't, the emergency physicians don't, you know,
look, if you're dying of some problem
or you're in grave medical condition,
they have, they're justified in acting
even if they don't have your consent.
But, and that's the case.
And sometimes we think of privacy cases, right?
We think that other matters, other values
might supersede it, right?
And so that's understandable.
But it's still the case that there is this fundamental
reason to be worried about privacy
that has nothing to do with consequences, right?
Even in the case where the invasion of my privacy
has no bad effects on me,
there's still something wrong about it.
And that is a point that's often missed,
I think, in these debates.
Absolutely.
The book is called The Internet of Us,
Knowing More and Understanding Less in the Age of Big Data.
It came out in March 21st, I think.
That's right. This year, yeah.
In Canada, I think next week.
Oh, it's not available in Canada yet?
I don't know.
I think it comes out in Canada next week
or maybe, right, maybe this week.
Oh, excellent.
Mark Goodman, in his book, The Future Crimes,
make an argument that we have two kinds of computers,
the computers that have been hacked already
or haven't been hacked yet.
So speaking of privacy, what...
That's almost, yeah.
Yeah, what kinds of measures do you think we can take
as members of general public to secure ourself
from intrusion of, well, police is one side of the story,
but the other side are hackers.
The other side is what's going on in deep web and darknet.
Yeah, darknet and deep web.
Well, as a philosopher, first, let me say,
because that's a practical question.
I am not, you know, if you want to know
how to protect yourself in a practical way,
don't ask a philosopher because that's a practical question
and practical questions are not our forte.
What I do think, I mean,
but I don't want to punt completely on the question.
I think actually, as Snowden pointed out,
probably the easiest thing to do to protect yourself
is to try to use sort of reasonable,
sensible policies on passwords,
the sort of passwords, policies that people have.
I mean, that's not gonna protect you completely, obviously.
I mean, nothing can protect you completely.
There is no such thing as complete protection.
That's right.
Not anymore, I guess, yes.
Not anymore, and probably even with any technology, right?
Any technology can be broken.
The Enigma code was broken by Alan Turing and others,
and that was a pretty damn good technology for encryption.
So there's just more or less difficult,
there's techniques.
Now, I mean, there might be logical limits to,
but I mean, quantum, I mean, yeah.
Let's just leave it at that.
Practically speaking, there's no safeguard
that can't be gotten around.
However, you can protect yourself by engaging in more,
and pretty much just following the things
that the IT people will tell you to do on day one.
I referenced Snowden because he was on,
at one point interviewed, I think on 60 Minutes,
so don't quote me on that.
You can Google it and find out, I suppose.
But just telling people the very basic things
about encryption and password protection,
and those things, I think,
are probably the best things you can do.
Now, I think for those of you,
for those of your listeners
that actually know something about encryption,
there's a whole bunch of much more sophisticated things
to do, but they don't need a philosopher to tell them that.
But for folks who don't know anything,
not giving your middle name as your password
and using different passwords for different sites,
those sort of basic things,
it's sort of like locking your door on your apartment.
That's right, exactly.
Can the person who wants to get in your apartment
through that lock and who is a professional do it?
Yep.
Is it gonna be dissuaded, however, some folks,
if there's just a lock or two on your apartment?
Yep.
Both things are true.
You can't stop everybody,
but you can slow people down
and make it more of a pain in the butt
for them to evade your privacy.
Yes, very true.
Speaking of your book,
another concept that you talk about
is extended knowledge hypothesis,
and I'll be very interested for you to expand a little bit
on that concept as well.
Sure, that I think relates in some ways in my own mind
to the privacy debate as well.
Extended knowledge hypothesis is a variation
or an implementation of another hypothesis,
which is called the extended mind hypothesis
due to the philosophers Andy Clark and Ann Burrow
and David Chalmers, who's in New York.
Those philosophers 20 years ago suggested
that it's possible that our mental states,
like the state of memory, might already be extended
to things like books or notepads.
Their example, this was pre-smartphone days,
was that if you just took a shopping list,
you were extending your memory to the list.
What they meant by that is
there's sort of an innocent way to read that,
and one innocent way to read that is that they're just saying
that, oh, shopping lists are good aids to memory,
or the iPhone is a good aid to your memory.
No, no, no, no, no.
They mean something much more radical than that.
What they mean is your memory state itself,
the actual state of your memory, your memory,
actually part of it is that piece of paper.
In other words, your mental states,
your psychological states are partly composed of paper.
That's the extended mind thesis.
Your mind extends beyond the bounds of your skull.
The biological, the structure.
Yeah, exactly, beyond the biological structure.
Now, the extended knowledge hypothesis
is something similar to that, but could be held independently.
I'm sort of agnostic about the extended mind thesis.
I think it might be true,
but there's some good objections against it,
which might not be relevant to mention here.
But I'm like, oh, well, let's see how it goes.
Let's see how things sort of unfold,
and maybe it will turn out to be true,
or maybe it's true about some states,
but not others, and so forth.
I think that's probably the case.
But you could still, independently of that,
hold that our knowledge processing is extended.
That is, you might think that,
even if my mind isn't completely extended,
the ways in which the processes that I use
to form beliefs are belief-forming processes.
That is, the processes that I use
to form an opinion about a piece of information,
to process information, might themselves be extended,
and I think are extended to our digital devices.
And I think extended to each, actually, other people.
I think that when I ask somebody
and the philosopher Sandy Goldberg
has said this sort of thing, he says,
look, even in testimony, if I stop somebody on the street
and ask them how to get to the restaurant,
then the process by which I'm forming that belief
is extended, both what's going on in my head,
as I'm listening to them,
there's also what they're doing and their expertise.
So if I end up knowing where the restaurant is
on the basis of that testimony that they gave me,
it's because their testimony was accurate.
But their testimony was accurate
based on what's happened to them, right?
That depends on them,
whether they've been to the restaurant before
and they know where they are
and they know how to get there, stuff like that.
So I think that's persuasive,
and I think that it also means that much of what we know
today, Google knowing, is extended in just this way.
I think that's what makes Google knowing really interesting,
is that when we Google know,
we're radically dependent on what's going on elsewhere
in space, that is, what's going on with these devices,
whether the, what's going on with the software,
the hardware, and the people that of course
program those devices.
All those facts are part of the process
of our information processing.
So that in a sense, when we know what we know,
when we Google know,
if you asked where is the knowledge,
the knowledge is distributed.
And in that sense, knowledge is networked,
which is something people a lot of times say,
but they often don't, I think, really know what they mean.
But that's what I mean when I say,
in the truest sense of the word,
knowledge is networked now,
because it's actually to know in the Google sense
requires a network, and in fact,
that network is part of your information processing system.
So that's the thesis of extended knowledge.
Speaking of distributed knowledge and learning,
as we create more information,
it's becoming harder to analyze that information,
and that's where machine learning
and artificial intelligence becoming
more and more important, I think,
to process that information.
One good example in, I think, about a month ago,
that Microsoft artificial intelligence was put on Twitter,
and almost overnight, it turned into
a Hitler-loving sex addict.
Right.
So what do you make of that,
and how do you see the progress of artificial intelligence?
And then I wanna speak to you as a philosopher
about the concept of ethics in artificial intelligence.
Sure.
So, yeah, so that was something that actually
I've been sort of noodling about,
that example of the bot,
that overnight sort of became this racist, sexist monster
and had to be shut down.
Now, there was a reason for that, of course,
which is that the way it was constructed
and how it was trained to train itself
was to listen, in a sense, to what other people said to it
and the sorts of questions that they asked it,
and it would abstract from those questions
and make certain inferences from those questions,
and of course, I mean, I think there was,
in this particular case, there were some people
that cottoned on to the fact that this was going on, right,
and sort of deliberately did this.
I'm not sure that everybody was sort of aware
of what was going on, and that's not surprising
because as you may know, social bots,
bots in general all over the web,
I mean, Twitter tried to ban them for a while,
I mean, they're not hard,
you make a bazillion of them there,
and if you're, we all probably have our own techniques
for trying to spot when one pops up
and asks for a Facebook to be our Facebook friend,
but what does that tell us, this fact that this bot became so
biased so quickly, so hateful?
Well, it says, it tells us exactly
what we started out talking about.
The internet is the greatest fact checker
and also the greatest bias-confirmer
in the history of history.
What I remember when I said earlier about social media,
you've got to concentrate on the social,
the biases that in fact are offline life,
in fact are online life, and actually our online life
makes those biases, tendency to make those biases
more entrenched and more visible in certain ways.
Some of that has to do with the fact that much of web life
is or can be more anonymous than offline life,
but that's not the only reason.
But I think that that is really what's going on,
that's what that illustrates, that's a perfect illustration
of the way in which social media,
far from connecting us in certain ways,
has made us exemplify those traits that don't connect us,
and that's worrying,
and we need to figure out ways to fix that.
Because social media is not going away.
I'm not going to stop using it.
It's expanding.
So we better start paying attention to this right now.
And if that example of the social bot isn't going to,
if that, it just crystallizes the point.
Right.
So, yeah.
I just wanted to talk about artificial intelligence.
There is a great discussion around the potential dangers
of artificial intelligence and how unpredictable
it's going to be.
And one of the ways that it's been suggested-
When we reach the singularity.
Yes, yeah.
One of the ways that maybe we can control
or try to understand artificial intelligence
is to put our own ethics into the machine
so the machine will operate based on those ethics.
Yeah.
Do you think ethics is objective to begin with
and how it will translate from humanity into machine?
Those are two really great,
another great couple of questions.
So the first question is very complicated to answer,
but I have a lot of opinions about,
but I'll try to crystallize them.
Yeah, short order is I think it's objective.
I think, so a lot of my work in the past
has been on the nature of truth and objectivity.
That's what I sort of, as a philosopher, have worked on.
And so I have views about that.
To summarize them, I think that ethics is objective.
Its objectivity, though, isn't in the same,
doesn't consist in the same set of features,
or it's not the same in its character
as the objectivity of, let's say, physics.
And in other words, what I mean by that
is when I say something like grass is green
or that grass is green pointing to some grass,
that truth sort of depends on whether,
if that is true, it depends on whether there's grass
that actually is green that I'm pointing at.
So the truth sort of depends on whether it corresponds
to some objective facts in the world.
Well, ethics, it's much harder to point to anything.
You can't point to a human right.
You can point to what you think is an example
of a human right or violations of it,
but a human right is an abstract notion, right?
So, but of course there are other abstract things
like numbers that we think that are objective truths about.
I don't think you can point to a number.
You can point to a numeral.
I can write one down on the whiteboard behind me.
But of course, if I erase that number off a whiteboard,
it's not like I killed the number seven.
Oh my God, the number seven's gone away!
Oh my God, the number seven's gone away, right?
I just killed, I just erased a sign for the number seven.
And so there are abstract entities that we can talk about
that are objective or our thoughts about them
can be objective.
And so I think that the nature of objectivity changes
in those domains, but there's still objectivity.
So yeah, the short answer is that I think there are truths
and objective ones about what's about right or wrong.
But the hard question is not that one.
The hard question is how do we know which ones those are?
In mathematics, it's easier because we have a series,
we have techniques, proofs, and the like,
that we can, we generally speaking,
unless we're talking about really advanced mathematics,
we're generally going to agree on whether
certain mathematical propositions are true or not.
Not so much with morality.
And that of course convinces a lot of people to think
that there is no objectivity at all.
I think that's a mistake.
I think in morality, what we have to do is realize
that we've got to be tolerant of a certain reasonable amount
of pluralism, that there might be more than one true story
of the world when it comes to morality,
even if it's the case that not every story is true.
There could be ties for first place,
morally speaking, for moral systems.
But some, like the Nazis, are right out.
And the hard question philosophically
is to try to explain how that could be the case.
I think most of us probably think that's the case.
And the hard philosophical work is, how can that be?
But that all suggests to me that the hard question is going to be,
well, which ethical principles do we put in the robot?
What do we teach it?
One problem that we saw with the social bot
is that if we allow it to teach itself, it becomes a disaster.
It could be a disaster.
It'll end up like the rest of us bastards, right?
Right?
It turns out that some humans might turn out to be ethical,
and a lot, not so much.
Right.
So if we adopt the Asimov method, that we,
from the foundation novels and the robot novels,
if we think that we need to provide
our artificial intelligence with some firm moral guidance,
then the real question will be, well,
then the real question will be, what
is that moral guidance going to consist in?
And there, of course, people will have different views,
especially when we get past the abstract principles
to how we apply them.
I mean, a lot of us can agree on abstract principles
like don't kill innocents for fun.
That's not too hard.
Most moral systems will agree on that.
Question is, who are the innocents?
That's a very good point.
That's the hard part.
Yeah.
And I don't know how you're going to program anything
to deal with the messiness of human experience,
or any experience, human or otherwise.
So I think that at some point, it's going to be unavoidable.
I think the hope to somehow imbue
our artificial intelligence with good moral character
is going to be as successful as our attempts to do
that with our own children.
Sometimes, that works out.
Sometimes, not so much.
Right?
Yeah, you do your best by you.
Morality is not an easy thing to do.
You do your best, but you have no absolute control
over the outcome.
Right.
And why is that?
Because they're going to find a different path through life.
Different things are going to happen to them.
Right.
And they're going to run across questions
that you might not have run across, like,
is this person innocent or not?
So that which seems easy in the armchair of the philosopher
is rarely easy when it meets the cold, hard facts of daily life.
And that's going to be the case for artificial intelligence
researchers as well.
Excellent.
We've been speaking to Professor Michael Lynch,
his latest book, The Internet of Us,
Knowing More and Understanding Less in the Age of Big Data,
available now in the US and will be available in Canada
this week or next week.
It's been a pleasure speaking with you.
I'm just going to ask you the last question that I'm
asking all my guests, that if you come across
an intelligent alien from a different civilization, what
would you say is humanity's worst thing, the worst thing
that humanity has done, and what would you say
as humanity's greatest achievement?
The worst thing that humanity has done
is allow itself to act on its deepest hates of each other.
The worst thing is the aspect of humanity itself,
acting on hate.
And of course, there's lots of examples of that.
But the mere fact of acting on hate
is probably the worst thing that we can do.
Having hate is bad enough, but acting on it is even worse.
What's the best thing?
The best thing is learning how to act out of love for others.
That's the best thing humanity has learned how to do.
It's unfortunate that we still need to keep learning,
but that's humanity.
That's what I would say to the aliens.
I learned how to enjoy our life.
I learned how to enjoy the life that Earth lives.
I learned about the life that humans live.
you