I believe that we are machines and in the full formal definition of a machine, obviously
we're not gears and oil.
And so of course machines can have spiritual experiences because we are machines and we
have them.
Hello and welcome to the 79th episode of Neohuman Podcasts, I'm Agabahari Adygologist on Twitter
and Instagram.
You can follow this show on LiveInLimbo.com, iTunes, YouTube, BitChute, and at some point
on Spotify.
And today with me, I have Brad Templeton.
Welcome to Neohuman Podcasts, Brad.
Yes, hi, good to be here.
Pleasure to have you.
And just to give our audience some kind of a context where your thoughts and opinions
are coming from, let's start with your background, the work you've done, the lives you've lived
and what are you mainly focused on now these days?
Oh, I mean, I have to do that.
It's always much more self-aggrandizing when you have to do that.
You get the host to do that.
Well, I've done a lot of different things, all pretty much related to computers and high
tech, but I started out in the software field, wrote a dozen software packages back in the
80s, games and tools and things like that.
Got probably, well, the other two things that made people know me were one was in the 80s,
the internet was growing and I hosted what would be considered the first or one of the
first blog type things, a publication of comedy that was the most widely read thing on the
internet for many years.
But then I also started the first dot com, the first business on the internet, an electronic
newspaper back then, which I built during the 90s.
That was started in Waterloo, Ontario, a town you may know, but I moved it to Silicon Valley.
Since then, after selling that, I've been involved in a lot of different ventures and
the nonprofit work.
I was 20 years at the Electronic Frontier Foundation, which is a civil rights group.
It does free speech, privacy, these things in the computer world.
Forsythe Institute, an organization devoted to nanotechnology and futurist technologies,
went to work on self-driving cars, got very interested in them, got invited to work on
Google's self-driving car during its first few years.
It's now known as Waymo.
And let's see, also helped build a fake university called Singularity University, which tries
to help people understand the effects of rapidly changing technology and that during the previous
decade.
And all along, I've been writing and talking and inventing in those fields.
How has the internet world has changed and changed the world since its early days where
you were there, present, right there?
Not much.
Really?
No, of course not.
I mean, I don't know how you can ask that's a very broad question.
How has the internet changed the world?
I mean, it's probably the, I mean, you could say the computer is the most significant invention
of recent days because it sits underneath all those, but of the things the computer
did, the internet probably changed people's lives more than any of them.
And one obvious reaction that we're all experiencing right now is that if we had wanted to do a
lockdown to stop a disease from spreading 20 years ago, what we're doing today, everyone
working from home, everybody meeting all the time by video calls and so on, that would
just not even be possible.
So the lockdown wouldn't be possible.
It might not be possible to fight that kind of disease.
So that's just one example.
I am one of several who, back in 2005, I wrote an essay saying, you know, a pandemic is going
to come and at least this time, and I outlined all the things we're doing, we'll all be
doing classes at home, we'll all be working at home and getting deliveries of everything
we order online.
And that has happened.
Unfortunately, the other things that I predicted or advised didn't happen.
So not everything changes, but you'll have to get a little more specific with a question
like that.
One of the reasons I ask is because this democratization of information seems to have brought a lot
of liberty for people, but at the same time have brought a lot of confusion that some
people are making the argument that we've never been this divided.
But my argument is that we probably have always been this divided, but it just hasn't been
heard.
Now we have channels and access to those channels to be heard and, you know, contribute with
our ideas and everybody seems to be, you know, basically ringing their own bells.
Well I think what you say is true to an extent, but and I used to say it wholeheartedly.
I don't say it so wholeheartedly now.
I think that one thing that none of us, I would say none, I'm sure there were a few,
but very few people accounted for, was the extent that propaganda could be a digital
weapon.
And so that, I think that has changed and is going to get worse.
We're seeing that people, you know, countries, nations, and are attempting to use propaganda
in an entirely new and different way.
Targeting people individually, targeting people with just exactly the messages to push their
buttons and get them to fight each other more than they would have fought each other in
the past.
Yes, we've always had differing opinions.
We didn't tend to have our own facts so much and what's become clear is that populations
are now isolating where they get the information from and each source is slanted in particular
ways.
It's, you know, mostly people in my community say, oh God, it's the right to have this
worse and they're watching Fox News or whatever they're doing.
But the truth is every side is getting its own particular collection of information.
It's very hard to try and remove the biases from the media that you consume and, you know,
we didn't anticipate that we anticipated, at least I anticipated that you would socialize
with your friends online because I was doing that in the 1980s.
In fact, it was one of the, what I'll call the great realizations of my life was back
in a long time ago now, back in about 1981.
I first got, oh, I've gotten on the ARPANET in 79 but I got on it for a day to day basis
a year or two later and at that time everyone thought computer networks were for computers
to talk to computers and, you know, exchange data, share files, that sort of stuff.
And the epiphany was, wow, no, no, this is for people to talk to people.
This is for our communication and not just for business but for socialization and a lot
of the things in my career have been based on that epiphany and everyone else pretty
much agrees with it today.
But what was, should have seen more of the dark side of that, I guess.
Yeah, I guess they come together, right?
The light and darkness?
They always do and in fact, you are, even the funny thing is you make this mistake even
though you know the truth but it is a very common and foolish mistake to not look at
any new technology and say, okay, what will bad people do with this?
And I mean, we always think that, we always ask that question, we're always seeing bad
people do things but I don't know why but we missed the idea that someone like Vladimir
Putin would attempt to, you know, manipulate a country from the outside at a very deep
detail and inside, you know, countries have done propaganda, they've done these sort of
things but it was dropping leaflets from airplanes or having radio free, you know, radio stations.
It was not the way it's become.
It's also that the arbitration of good and bad has been democratized in a way that now
a mob of people on Twitter can decide who is a bad person based on maybe one comment
that that person has made 10 years ago, 15 years ago which brings a really big concern
that how this whole thing is going to evolve considering how you mentioned we don't agree
on facts anymore, how this world with all this arbitration of good and bad plus technologies
like deep fake that are being easier and easier for people to just make up stuff from ground
up is going to affect this sociopolitical, very fragile sociopolitical dynamic that we're
dealing with right now.
Well, you had two things in there.
I'll briefly touch on deep fakes.
While they're scary, if you think about it, of course, there's nothing in text which is
inherently true.
If someone sends you a written article saying something, you know that well, you know, anyone
could write that and you have something in your brain that says I should see whether
that's believable, I should see whether that's true.
With video, you don't have that.
You sort of think if I see it, it must be true and what I'm hoping is that we'll lose
that sense that we'll see a video and we'll say okay, that's a video but, you know, videos
are no more real than text and at least I hope because if not, if we start believing
everything we see in video is true, we are going to get more riled up.
But you touched on I think the deeper issue, one that we have not figured our way out of
at all which is, you know, becoming mobs and this very tempting but dangerous vigilante
justice which on the one hand, you think well, hey, that's just people expressing themselves.
It's certainly allowed and it is but, you know, we actually have centuries of experience
where we sort of laid down the principles of justice and how they should work.
The idea of people having been presumed innocent until they're proven guilty and not being
punished until that happens of metering out punishment to fit the crime and to perform
not a retribution role but, you know, a deterrent and a rehabilitation role.
Principles of evidence, principles of rights of the accused, rights of everyone involved
and we built those systems of justice over hundreds of years because we saw what goes
wrong when you don't apply those principles.
Unfortunately, we have now discovered this new way to get not justice but retribution
and we're clearly not being very good about it and we all feel very satisfied, haha, there's
that person and I saw a video what looks like they were racist so I'm going to make them
lose their job and I'm not saying people should be racist or we shouldn't be disapproving
of people who are racist but sometimes the penalty is, you know, total annihilation from
society for an offhand remark which is not appropriate meeting out of justice and I don't
know actually what's going to be the solution to that.
Now here's an example with respect to autonomous vehicle.
There is the ethical dilemma with respect to autonomous cars that if you come across
a crossroad, there is no ethical dilemma now just in this example that I'm trying to make
a point out of, that you come across a crossroad and one is blocked, you can kill yourself
for example and the other has a baby in it or an old man in it, which one would you choose?
Now if this kind of mob mentality get into a justice system and say that, hey, if you
for example kill a black person that is not okay but if you kill a white person that would
be okay with an autonomous vehicle, would that be a possibility?
I don't know about that one but getting back to your question of who the car would run
over, that I do have an answer for which is they're keeping track of who asks that question
and they're going to run over the people who ask that question.
That is the plan.
The reality is, does this happen to you a lot?
Have you often been driving and had to decide whether to kill yourself or a baby?
No, not at all.
Have you ever heard of it happening to someone else?
No, I've read a lot of arguments about it though.
It is not a real thing.
What it is, is it's a morbid fascination that we have with the idea of a machine deciding
who lives and who dies.
So for us, that used to be for gods, not even for people to decide and so as soon as you
start saying, what if a machine is deciding who lives and who dies, everyone goes, oh
wow, that's like deep, oh, got to figure that out.
In fact, no, it's an extremely rare situation.
I've been looking around and I can't say I've never found an instance where something like
that happened but it's just not the kind of thing that's anywhere on anyone's priority
list about what to program a car to do.
And secondly, there's almost always already an answer in the law about where a car should
go because the law is actually full of a thousand rules about where the car can go and who has
right away and who's supposed to yield and so the car will first and foremost obey the
law and so it's long time before anyone will have to imagine a car having to make that
decision and so the fact that worrying about it is actually the ethical problem because
if you spend a lot of time worrying about that, you're not worrying about the things
that actually matter and might actually save people's lives.
What are some of the more important factors and elements that matter with respect to autonomous
vehicles?
Well, I mean everyone is set on a goal of making the car so that it's safe enough on
the roads to be accepted by the public and to not create great liability for the people
who put it out there.
There's actually nothing, I mean there are moral concerns going on but in fact there's
just very practical concerns which is the first you've got to build a car that you can
prove to yourself is safe enough to put out there.
Actually, that's the first people you have to convince is that you yourselves have done
it, you have to convince your lawyers, your company's board of directors that it's time
to put this vehicle out on the road.
So that's the challenge everyone's working for is how can they make it safe enough that
we feel comfortable doing it.
Obviously you want the public to feel comfortable with it as well.
Right now you don't actually have to make the government feel comfortable with it.
Someday you might have to but here's a little dark secret no one seems to know, it's already
illegal to hit people.
We don't actually need another law that say that, we've got that law down there, it's
probably the most tested law in the world.
There's no tort that's more common in courts than a car accident.
Actually it's not in the courts that much because it's in insurance companies but effectively
in that sense.
So that's what you got to do and so now of course that breaks down into a lot of different
problems.
Right now if you were to ask people what's your hardest problem that you're working on,
I think a lot of them would say we want to get the computer better at predicting what
humans will do.
So you're driving down the road, is that car going to suddenly change lanes?
Is that guy going to step into the crosswalk?
This is something that humans are better than computers at predicting what other humans
are thinking.
So that would be the one thing that people are sort of pushing on and people are working
on all the other problems as well, making sure that you see and understand everything
in the road, that you know you can handle lots and lots of unusual situations.
These are key problems everyone is always trying to improve on and eventually people
argue about what level of safety they want to achieve.
Most people sort of dance around the idea of let's make it better than the average person
and I don't think that's unreasonable.
Some people want to be much better than the average person, I don't actually think that's
the right path.
I think perfection is certainly not attainable and therefore not the right goal to go for.
I even think there are arguments that you could make it just as good as a teenager with
a freshly admitted driver's license.
Now people would say that's not very safe but we certainly allow that on the road and
we do it because that's how we turn those teenagers into more mature, better drivers.
But the one trick is that when we make a teenager better with a driving course or some experience,
we only make one teenager better.
If we let robots go out there and get their experience and improve, we make all the robots
better at the same time, at least all the ones from the same company.
Yeah on the social level it just seems to me that people's immediate problem with machines
is that they're going to replace humans, whether it's labor or decision making or anything
like that and then a lot of arguments are being made using or maybe taking advantage
of that concern coming from the side that they're fundamentally against automation,
against autonomous vehicles, they make the ethical or moral kind of an argument, right?
Yeah, it's reasonable to worry about that.
I think some of that worry is not justified, I think some of it is.
So far the history of machines replacing humans is actually not nearly as scary as people
imagine back in the Industrial Revolution.
In fact a famous statistic which astounds people is that there are more bank tellers
today than in 1970 and if you were to say name me a job where the machine replaced a
human everyone say well bank teller I don't go in and you know get cash from the human
being anymore.
Those bank tellers aren't handing you cash anymore of course, they're doing other things.
But in fact we actually haven't done that much.
Now will that change?
But we've predicted that machines will take all the jobs for 150 years, every 10 years
a big nasty book will come out warning how oh my god the machines are going to take all
the jobs and guess what?
It's wrong every time.
Now is it someday going to be right?
Maybe, maybe and should we think about it?
Sure we should think about it but we should also understand why we're always wrong when
we make the prediction and try and figure out how we can tell that oh this is the time
where we're no longer always wrong, this is the time where it really happens.
Now when it comes to driving well we got two kinds of people making their learning or making
their living from driving.
We do have you know all the uber cab drivers that sort of thing in the world and I don't
want to deprecate these people but the truth is they don't think of that as a career.
They didn't when they were little kids say I want to grow up and be a cab driver all
right.
They do that because it's kind of handy gig work they can set the hours, it doesn't take
a lot of skill, you basically can go out there and work when you want and you've got a car
and you make some money and I think that those people will go and do something else like
that if driving isn't that great a way to make money with it.
Sure uber and lift and those companies discovered a way that people could make money that way
and they enabled a lot of people to make money that way but that didn't even exist 11 years
ago.
So cab driving existed but it was a much smaller profession.
Then there's professional truck drivers those are real there's about three million of those
in the United States.
Now in the professional truck driving industry and long-haul driving in particular the turnover
every year is often more than 100 percent.
Basically that people leave more people leave the job than there are jobs so that they only
last less than a year in the job that's what it means you can you think how could it be
more than 100 percent.
They just don't want to do it right?
It's grueling work.
If you do it long haul you basically have to go out and for a week of sleeping in motels
in the back of your truck you don't see your family.
It's both boring and scary at the same time and yeah it pays it pays okay than most other
jobs of that skill level because it only takes a month or so to get the training but no.
So when they start driving the trucks which they will they're not going to put anybody
out of work at first they're going to just replace the truck driving jobs that are sitting
open which is a lot of them.
Eventually they might sit and go after some of those career truck drivers and I do feel
yeah it would be good to have some alternatives for them find some outs and maybe the government
can do that maybe the companies can even do it.
But among all the jobs that people will find replaced by machines these ones this is not
a great answer if you're in them but these ones are not the top of the list of ones that
people will worry about.
Yeah people also are very worried about the manufacturing jobs and that is being misused
or used or whatever you want to call it for political purposes all across board.
You know manufacturing jobs weren't taken by robots manufacturing jobs were taken by
cheaper workers China oh not just yeah China other countries Philippines Southeast Asia
is the place right now used to people who used to think Japan was the place with the
cheap workers of course Japan very quickly didn't have cheap workers and you know people
in India Pakistan you know they're anywhere that especially that is there they speak English
so help them do jobs for the Western world.
Anyway yes that's going to continue there's going to be labor disruption I don't think
anyone can alter that but let me give you two ways of thinking about machines doing
human tasks which is that many people have published studies and they say we calculate
that machines are right they don't do it yet but they're right to do like a third of the
tasks that human beings do and some people get that and they respond by saying oh my
god the computer is going to take my job what am I going to do I must admit that I respond
to a different way saying when can I get that fantastic I don't want to do all those stupid
boring things I have to do the computer could do that for me and sign me up and it's really
a mix of both for most people and what's actually happened in the past in all the jobs is that
the computer has done some of the boring or dangerous parts of it and the human beings
have done the rest and employment has not counting coronavirus panics employment has
grown and was until recently higher than it ever been in history and it wasn't the credit
of Donald Trump he likes to pretend it was it was the march of progress that's actually
made more and more jobs a hundred years ago half of the population worked in agriculture
farming and now about two or three percent of the population work in agriculture farming
so all those jobs disappeared half the jobs in the world went away and now more people
are working than ever right new jobs were created because of the technological revolution
some brand new jobs are created but actually most of those people are working in jobs that
existed in some form or another but they're doing them in different ways like bank teller
bank tellers are not handing you cash anymore right they're doing other parts of the banking
job so let me read you a question that one of our readers and previous guest fritz harrell
from ontario you're from canada originally right i am from ontario indeed yeah yeah amazing
i live there 11 years in toronto he's wondering about your take on the long-term consequences
of separating humans from the actual activity they're doing given we are the outcome of
a long evolutionary process and this technological concentric distancing from an activity we
are actually responsible for might have unexpected unexpected outcomes and then he's using the
airbuses fly by wire computer controlled flight that left pilots unable to fly boeing's computer
assisted aircraft safely which he thinks were part of the mcas mishaps in addition to a
poor design decisions he has another part to his question but maybe you answer this
one first well yeah i don't want to be too critical but that question seemed to dance
around a lot of different things so i'm not sure what specific thing he wants to get at
but i'll talk about a little bit about the boeing aircraft i mean so um i mean it was
airbus of course that pioneered the idea of making aircraft be fly by wire at the time
that they were founded everyone said you're crazy we can't make an aircraft that way and
they did and they were very successful and boeing was of course the company not that
did not pioneer that and their decision with the 737 max was actually uh i i thought it
very different from that they wanted to make another vehicle that they could say was the
same the 737 one most popular aircraft in the world every airline has a lot of them
every pilot in the world is trained to fly the 737 and what they hoped is they could
make a 737 with bigger engines and more and newer more efficient engines and make it so
that any pilot could fly who knew how to fly the 737 that was what they hoped to do and
that's what they got wrong uh they they figured the way to do that since they built actually
a different aircraft which wouldn't fly the same as 737 and they tried to make it fly
as a 737 by using the software system which is not entirely a wrong thing to try to do
but they just didn't do it very well and they there were some areas where they didn't test
it properly and it it um you know it goofed up and then the pilots were not trained on
how to deal with it because that was the whole point of the 737 max no not no new training
but very little new training needed for a 737 pilot take the wings it turns out there
should have been more training and so some pilots uh didn't understand what was going
on by the way there were pilots who had that happen to them and they uh dealt with it because
they were more experienced pilots and uh so anyway and of course catastrophic for bowing
uh but uh i'm the rest of the question rambled a little bit so i wasn't entirely i think
the soul of this question goes back to what you said how human drivers are still better
than machines and he's talking about the unseen consequences of replacing let's say human
drivers who have we have evolved decades learning how to drive a car and watching our parents
drive a car and seeing other drivers and this whole thing being replaced by the machines
basically well so um that is actually an answer we'll give in the other direction by some
of the for example waymo the company that i worked for in its early days google um yeah
it was google at the time uh they have now been out there driving and testing their software
well i don't know what the most recent number they published but i think it was around 20
million miles of real road driving um so that's about 40 human lifetimes of experience in
the sense that when anything unusual happens so these cars are out there driving themselves
but they have people in them the people are making note if anything weird goes on they
take over if they think there's a chance the software is going to not do the right thing
and so their safety record is excellent they've had only one very slow crash that took place
where it was the fault of the computer uh and by the way so you never you know there's
never been a case of human being driving for 40 lifetimes well no one drives for 40 lifetimes
but um human beings are not nearly that good they could drive for 40 lifetimes and never
and only once have fault for a crash um now that's with the supervision there it's more
like student drivers with a driving instructor sitting next to them ready to grab the wheel
and so that's one reason they don't have the accidents but anyway they've been doing that
and so they think they have seen more than any person could ever see in addition by the
way they uh then have the car drive around in simulator you know a little video game
basically uh and they've driven billions and billions and billions of miles and either
way and most of the miles none of the miles they drive in simulator are boring they don't
have it simulate driving on the freeway for an hour which is what humans have for most
of our experience it spends that hour going through a hundred different crash situations
and 200 strange other situations testing and it's going to do the right thing so actually
there's a fair claim that these systems are far more experienced at driving than we are
what they don't have they have experience what they don't have is uh you know the high
level human thought and intuition uh which can solve problems never seen before so the
answer to that is they feel now people can argue whether this is true or not but if you
just pound at it long enough and you drive for 20 million miles or some other amount
like that and do all these tests you reduce the probability of something you've never
seen before happening you get it down to the point where you're you are seeing new things
but you're handling them correctly and if we don't handle one correctly then you get
very upset and you try and fix it and you find yourself getting to a level where that
bad incident where something new happens and you don't handle it correctly and there's
a crash is so rare that you're better than people and if you get to that level um which
Waymo claims they are already in at least in the simple driving environment near Phoenix
where they have an operating passenger service where vehicles are running around not right
now with the virus but generally we're out running around with nobody in them picking
up passengers taking them across town so uh you can do that once you've got to that level
and then you get even better and you release it out to the world.
Waymo is the same company that they partnered with Walmart for driverless trucks?
They do they do have a they do have I believe a small partnership with Walmart doing deliveries
I think Walmart's done one or two partnerships um but the other yes they are also making
trucks as well that's correct.
Do you think laws and regulations are in a way obstacles in a way of technological progress
I think I read somewhere that the first car when it came out in late 19th century it was
15 years later that they placed a first stop sign.
Well that would make sense I mean there were no roads for cars back when those first cars
arose and there were no gas stations and there's the famous story actually of Berta Benz the
wife of Carl Benz who of course built the first commercial motorwagen and Berta uh it's
maybe exaggerated but the story is she kind of snuck off with it and drove for about 60
miles to another German town and she had to stop at a drugstore which actually had a supply
of benzene there were no stations of course for this and it was all back dirt roads and
so on so she did the first road trip including having to fix the vehicle on the way so a
pioneer in her own way and it's certainly was a long time it yeah it took a while for
I don't know if it was the law I mean there were a few rare cases it's not as common as
people imagine but there were a few cases of very strange laws from people scared of
the car.
The funny story is that when the car did arrive actually the first cars were electric but
pretty quickly they switched to running on benzene gasoline that the first cars to or
when cars start arriving in New York City everyone praised them as oh my god we're
going to end pollution with these and the reason they said that was the roads were full
of a different kind of pollution from the thing that we used before cars yeah no they
were the roads were deep and harsh it was an actual big problem and yes these things
made a few bad smells in the air but nothing compared to the horses and so people were
very happy about that.
This dynamic between regulations and technology today though because the way that you talk
about it and I totally agree with it that automating driving maybe it is an ethical
choice that it can be made an argument because of it that it will cause less accidents it's
better eventually than human drivers but there will be lawmakers who are paid special in
United States lobbied by car companies let's say or a variety of special interests and
lobbyists who are placing obstacles on the way of this progress.
To an extent actually though because the car companies at least until recently and still
to a large extent they want to win this technology fight they they're trying to build these vehicles
they're scared of the startups being more nimble than they are smarter than them but
they won't admit that so they're mostly for it although it doesn't mean that they wouldn't
mind if it went a little bit slower and if it was a little bit harder for new companies
to get in the game and for big companies to continue to win but other than that what we
you know the people we've got try to do this though are Google and Apple you know and Ford
and General Motors frankly when those companies want something I think it'll happen I think
that they have the lobbying much more lobbying power than anyone else.
Now nonetheless there's certainly legal efforts to slow things down and as I've said I think
it's already illegal to not drive safely on the roads and so that those laws and the truth
is all the companies are very afraid not just of the legal consequences of them hitting
something but we saw that Uber of course did completely screw up what they were doing they
did run someone over and that shut down their project which a project they had named was
central to the success of their company and it shut down and it's they have like a couple
of test cars out now and this is years later now it's just two years later now everyone
stopped because of the pandemic but you know everyone realizes that they're investing billions
in this thing and if they make a mistake like that it could just wipe it all out and so
they're very strongly motivated to not make such a mistake obviously in the case of Uber
not strongly enough and that is a long story we can get into if you want but because I
probably studied that more than anybody outside of Uber or the NTSB and you know and it was
in the end it was it was a it was human error but human error caused by management decisions
poor management decisions.
This is Uber.
Yeah the Uber fatality now I mean obviously the software in the Uber car was not good
enough to drive the roads that's pretty clear but that's not a mistake in the sense that
all of the cars when they're prototypes go out there unable to drive and I have been
in the Google car when it you know started acting erratically and I had to take the wheel
every single vehicle no matter what the quality of the team making it goes through periods
where it's necessary for the human being inside of it to take the wheel and stop it from hitting
something fortunately very rarely a person but in some cases there have been many incidents
where you someone had to take the wheel to stop what might have been an accident that
hurt somebody so that's normal that's that's part of the game and as I said they've gone
for this 40 human lifetimes without hitting anybody so it works if you do it well but
it doesn't guarantee that people will do it well who were hired obviously a very poor
choice of person to supervise the vehicle to make it worse everybody uses two people
to supervise the vehicle and they decided to go to just one for reasons that are still
debated and the person they hired paid no attention to her job and started watching
a streaming show on her phone and so yeah yeah if your job is to watch the road and
you're watching a streaming show on your phone people can get hurt and that is that is tragic
but it is sadly not too remarkable in terms of of telling us that though the robots are
dangerous I mean I won't say there's no lessons to be learned for how to operate robots there
are lessons to be learned that uber and other people did learn them but everyone also learned
the lesson a lesson that they all knew which is you cannot play it fast and loose the way
that uber did because it can mean the end of everything you're trying to do what you
said what you said about google also reminded me of google glass that when it came out it
was it was so cutting edge and we were all like this is what we want to get you know
it's it's like a very obvious step towards becoming a cyborg but people started attacking
a lot of people who were wearing google glasses around san francisco area that they filmed
it whether it was because they were threatened because of privacy reasons or because they
were threatened because hey you you think you're better than me or something like that
and that kind of shut it down for I don't know I know that they're still around but
not my doctor is always wearing one when I go to the doctor and he says he says I have
to ask if it's okay to use this and I say well I helped build it so I'm probably okay
with it now I helped in a very very tiny way I was working at google x on the car and glass
was the second project of google x where I sat with those people and you know contributed
very tiny amounts to what they did but so no I mean glass was just a product that was
I mean both too early and aimed a little bit wrong as happens when you're too early and
I don't think there's any giant lesson from that I mean there are lessons to be sure the
lesson as I make in a humorous way is that glass was designed to be super lightweight
they wanted it to be really light and small and especially for that day I mean I think
there's people who've done even better years since but at the time it was a remarkable
engineering achievement to make it so light and small and the goal in fact was to make
it so light that you would forget you had it on which you could I mean I wore it from
time to time and I would forget it was on there I let you know I'd even go to the bathroom
with it on I'd realize now probably that's not a cool thing to do but the joke was that
it nobody else forgot you had it on anyone who looked at you said oh he's got that super
geeky thing on his head one of the design factors was it was asymmetrical it was only
on one side of your head the human eye is very noticing of that so nobody knows and
so people just weren't very accepting of it it couldn't do very much because it was limited
by how much power it would take to do things it had to run on a very small battery that
fit in the arm of an eyeglass or a little box behind your ear and I don't think we've
actually figured out the exact answer for how we would want to wear a computer well
I don't have it on right now but I guess so I have smart watch that I wear some of the
time I actually think the watch is a better form factor for these sort of things the watch
doesn't take video because it's not up in a place to do so you know I see you're wearing
a kind of amulet I actually think that wouldn't be a bad form factor what have you got there
it's a yeah these two have been brought for me by my girlfriend from Hawaii and the first
you're wearing it is art yes but I'm all in favor of you know if there will be a contact
lens or Elon Musk Neuralink by the time it's a third fourth generation that you can somehow
rely on it that it's not gonna you know it's not the first generation I'm all in favor
of it because I think this is actually not a new process that we are merging with the
machines is just becoming seamless well so the goal with glass was not to merge with
machines by any stretch what they wanted to see happened with glass and you know unfortunately
wasn't as exciting as they wanted it to be but they wanted to see what happened with
what if you know what if a computer or a computer or the network was just really super available
with very little effort very little time I mean obviously everyone's already got a phone
in their pocket so you'd think boy isn't computing very available to you and it is but reaching
into your pocket pulling out a phone unlocking it finding the app you want to run running
the app getting an answer that is comparatively a lot to just having something in front of
your eyes that you can just look at and see so anyway so the answer was yeah it wasn't
as exciting for people who need to work hands-free like the doctor there's people like that using
devices like Google Glass today and it's reasonably successful with them but will it be in a watch
will it be an appendent will it be in a well contact lens sure but we don't know how to
make we don't have the technology yet to make a contact lens to do what we need to do there
other than to also have glasses with it to send the power to it because there's no way
to store power in a contact lens you got to transmit the power safely to it and and will
it be an implant in the brain well again lots of experimentation going on there but very
very primitive right now maybe someday will be less primitive including Neuralink you
know Neuralink doesn't say a lot about what they're doing so I can't really you know comment
on it only in a very speculative way but actually I'll tell you the one thing about about things
like Neuralink which makes it such a hard problem is we've already got this massive
channel into the brain right here and to beat the ability of this thing to get information
into the brain I mean that that's not happening for a long time I mean the eye the eye and
the ear of you know obviously evolved to be this but they're extremely high bandwidth
information channels which we're very tuned to work with so you toss a chip in your brain
with a thousand electrodes and yeah you might be able to do some cool stuff but you're nothing
compared to the eye what are your thoughts on merging with machines in general you're
involved in Singularity University Ray Kurzweil has the date 2045 for Singularity yeah I don't
know I think you should never name dates that's a that's a bad thing and it well whatever
of course people have many different definitions of what a Singularity is actually Verna Vinci
who was the person who coined the term and who I've known for many years I published
one of his books in e-book form back good lord almost 30 years ago he eventually said
that the idea of a singularity was actually like a mathematical singularity a metaphor
for it as a point that you can't it's undefined that you cannot predict beyond that it's you
don't have the equipment to predict what it means so which means it's not kind of pointless
to talk about what it means because you are not equipped to do it maybe future you will
be equipped to do it and and then more specifically of course of computer intelligence becoming
so smart that it surpasses humans and that among the things that surpasses humans that
is programming new intelligence so that it is also better at making its own descendants
and that this could then happen so quickly that you quickly leave the abilities of humans
behind it's very hard to predict when that would happen or if that would happen but yes
we're we are going to get closer and closer machines and I do believe it is obviously
possible to have intelligence in a machine because if you can have it in a sort of a
wet tank of proteins inside bone I'm pretty sure you could have it in other things I'm
nothing magical about our brains some people trying to imagine all the brain has some mystical
ability to hold intelligence well obviously religions believe that religions believe that
there's something outside the brain a soul bestowed from God or whoever is the origin
of those things but if you're not taking that approach then there's nothing magical about
the brain and so clearly that's not the only way that intelligence could exist and so eventually
we will make one I mean we make intelligences all the time any man and woman can do it with
the things around they have around the house but we are not aware of how we do it it just
evolved but it's obviously possible to do it when we will understand how to do it is
a less answered question but we keep seeing glimpses that we're getting closer to that
but I'm not going to go so far as to agree with Ray's prediction very interesting perspective
I haven't I've never heard the bone and the like if we can create intelligence in with
our structure we certainly can it can be done within machines that's that's a very interesting
comparison but we do it right I mean yeah unless you believe in the mystical soul coming
into the body it is entirely the act of humans which makes more humans and more intelligences
well mystical soul is just an attempt to answer the unanswerable basically right our attempt
that we know what's going on it's a lot of things it is for many people though a strong
desire to feel that we are more than yeah some people some people feel that and then
they sense that they look at the world and they say it has to be more than flesh and
bone other people you know feel they've had a religious experience to tell them that and
so there are many people who think that and there are other people and I'm one of them
who look at it and say actually I think it's freaking amazing that you can have intelligence
from just that's it's not you know God is wondrous and amazing I'm saying it's wondrous
and amazing that evolution could produce something like us and Einstein who though he was a religious
man said a great thing he said the most incomprehensible thing about the universe is that it is comprehensible
that that the remarkable thing is that something as amazing as the universe and of course it's
amazing and many people say that's proof of God is that the universe is so amazing but
the fact that the workings of the universe can at some level be understood inside the
brain of a piece of the universe that's what Einstein was marveling at and I marvel at
it with him yeah I totally agree the God term I've talked about a number of people mathematicians
philosopher technologists it means nothing when people are saying it they don't even
know what it means they just throw it out there to basically fill a gap of the unknown
I'm not gonna go that hard I mean there are people who devote their lives to it my father
before I was born devoted his life to it he became an agnostic but the Christian version
of a God the Christian version he was he was of Christian but there are people from all
kinds of faiths who all and many people who devoted themselves now there is a cynical
but very rational explanation for it that the brain does seem to be a little bit primed
to feel a spiritual connection and they've found for example there's areas in the brain
that you can stimulate that cause people to have a religious experience so that they actually
feel they've got direct contact with something spiritual and having directly experienced
that then they it is not surprising that they believe it you think machines could have a
similar kind of an experience yes I mean I don't think they'd have a part of the machine
that you can stick electrodes in and it starts seeing God humans seem to have that some would
argue ah God put that there well there should be a need for it right well I believe that
we are machines and in the full formal definition of a machine obviously we're not gears in
oil and so of course machines can have spiritual experiences because we are machines and we
have them and machines that think as we do or think better than we do of course should
be able to understand what spiritual means and now would they actually have the spiritual
experience that comes to us because of what some might call a flaw in our brains they
could be designed to I'm not sure I would design one that way but someone else might
fair enough but would they be able to understand the things that we talk about when we talk
about spirituality I would have to believe so if they are as smart as we are yeah let
me just mention this when I said about God and people I don't mean to offend anybody
I you know I I guess can be considered a spiritual person in my own way but my argument was that
objectively speaking it's impossible to come up with kind of a definition that you would
have everybody agreed upon because a Muslim God is a very different than a Christian God
than a you know whatever higher being that Hindus believe in for example and majority
of people in the world they don't believe in any specific version of a God well let
me go more specific than this though I will tell you that I'm one of the people who believes
that it is not out of the question that the first machine intelligences would be copied
from human brains and this has become something the public's a little more aware of because
Amazon recently released a TV series called upload where that's essential plot element
this concept has been around in fiction and in speculation for many decades and the idea
is that while we do not understand how intelligence works or how the brain works it's not impossible
that first we'll understand how it works at the low level and simply copy the pattern
that we don't understand but we can copy some people argue whether we can copy it or
not but let's people here are positing that you could copy it into a non-bag of protein
form into a wouldn't necessarily it wouldn't be a digital computer but it would be some
kind of electronic form for example and that you would have then that human mind inside
the silicon and that would be both an artificial brain and a natural intelligence in the and
of course as a copy of you or I or anyone else it could certainly believe in God and
talk to you about God all day exactly the same way the human that this he or she was
copied from could let me read you the second part of the question that I read that how
will the insurance business appropriate fault in a computer controlled car would it be the
driver the car market and carmaker the software engineer who would it be funny because I just
literally a few minutes ago came from a planning session for a debate that we'll be having
online tomorrow on insurance and self-driving cars and I've actually spoken about that a
lot where would that debate be it'll be of course virtual like what what website or it'll
be this website called zoom-tank.com I'm not actually in this particular bait I'm usually
in it but I'm in the planning committee and so the the answer is bad for the insurance
companies which is that I don't think they actually have a role here now he's your friend
is asking a question which a lot of people ask they just want to know who's at fault
and the answer that's always been very obvious which is to say that first of all the computer
makes a complete recording of anything that happened in three dimensions a recording far
beyond any recording you've ever seen so in terms of who broke the law and who was at
fault under the vehicle codes and so on that will be known within seconds you know look
at the recording you'll say okay this guy did that that guy did that so in terms of
legal fault that will be super simple and trivial and so if the software made a mistake
the people who made or run the software will obviously be liable for it and no one's ever
doubted that in fact so much of people never doubted that that most of the major companies
including Google Volvo Mercedes all the big the big car companies not all of them but
most of them have declared in advance of course we will be responsible if our car crashes
and it's the fault of the car software we're not responsible if you run into it but you
know if if it runs into something they're faulting how could it be any other way would
you get into an uber if you had to sign a thing saying if this uber driver crashes I
have to pay of course not you're not going to get into that car so of course they have
to accept the responsibility for it so that a lot of people think like I hear that question
a lot and it surprises me because to me and I think too many of the people the answer
has been very straightforward are you familiar with defense distributed oh you mean Cody
Wilson yes I met him interesting character how do you see this law lawsuit and the whole
being able to print guns from the perspective of free speech and civil rights especially
since you basically were at the top of electronic what is that the electronic frontier foundation
yes we did a lawsuit over many years to get the courts to declare as they did that software
is a form of expression and therefore protected by laws of free speech and so yeah the same
applies to his files I would have to say even though they're even scarier I guess to people
because he can make parts for guns or you can make parts for guns or the 3d printer
so I'm not surprised it scares people I'm not surprised people are going after him but
if you wanted to imagine a world where there are illegal files with things that must not
be known that's a pretty scary world yeah it is speech though right
it is it is yeah I mean and then I think we got the court so I shouldn't say yeah obviously
because not yeah obviously because we did have to fight get a court to rule on that
and have an eight-year fight but to us of course the case was pretty clear yeah I thought
the genius of him was just blurring the line between the second amendment and the first
amendment in such a meaningful way I read his book too it's not like he's right or
left and I think this is beyond any kind of a political affiliation well you know as a
Canadian you're probably not as much of a fan of the second amendment as most Americans
are I'm a huge fan of second amendment because I'm coming from revolutionary Iran and I know
that they distributed guns among the revolutionaries to take over the government and the first
thing they did after the revolution succeeded it's like okay we're recalling all the guns
the state has a monopoly on violence yeah no no I mean if you're in a obviously a dire
situation as was the case in Iran but either during the Shah or later during the revolutionary
government it's there's a reason why you want the public to defend themselves and in Canada
actually of course there's a huge ownership of rifles among the population people think
Canadians don't have guns no no we have lots of rifles what we don't have is handguns and
it is clear that handguns are responsible for a significant increase in gun deaths in
the United States I mean the numbers are just staggering so anyway but whether you're a
fan of the second amendment or not people come to the defense of Cody Wilson because
strictly for the first amendment question yeah all right let me this was a pleasure
thank you so much for your time let me ask you the last question I ask all my guests
that if you come across an intelligent alien from a different civilization what would you
say is the worst thing humanity has done and what would you say is our greatest achievement
well of course the intelligent alien already knows this in any real situation because any
intelligent alien we're going to come across has got significantly greater capabilities
than we have what is the worst and best thing that humans have done I mean I guess my answer
on the worst thing is kind of boring right it's it's atrocity it's the long history
of atrocity that we have it's the long history of you know like what happened you know we
we study forever what happened in Germany in various other cases but to many ways you
look at Rwanda where which happened in the modern world where we know the example of
Germany and where you look at the Khmer Rouge in Cambodia where again we knew that example
and it was modern times and it didn't take very much to pull away the veil and people
would come out with their machetes right in Rwanda so the fact that and the fact that
by the way Germans aren't really worse than us right we imagine okay oh yeah well they
know the Germans were just they were all internal Nazis and so they did these horrible things
no they were people not too different from the people today yeah people think it can
be replicated here and repeated here in the US so yeah that's that that is still true
as I would say is one of the things I think is the worst of us the best of us is what
Einstein said that we have managed to actually get closer and closer to an understanding
of the way the universe works that we're a piece of the universe and we keep doing that
and we came up with science we came up with a way to actually make reliable information
that we could test and repeat and test and repeat until it actually seemed like we had
confidence it was true and that all of us know is true because we bet our lives on the
truth of scientific principles every day everywhere we go and except when we're staying at home
all day that's now we don't bet our lives on science every day well we still bet on
the the food we eat is assured through these principles that we've devised so that grand
achievement is the best bet.