Why aren't they talking about AI?
It just doesn't matter enough to the constituents, right?
Why are they talking about, name your topic, sir.
Name your topic.
I mean, the most arbitrary things
become giant friction points
and then they get in all the speeches.
Is it because of their inherent meaning
and some platonic reality?
No, no, no.
It's simply because they resonate with the constituency.
So we can expect AI to land
on the sort of political speech table
when it matters to the people who are being spoken to.
Hello and welcome to the 80th episode of New Human Podcast.
I'm a Gabbahari etiologist on Instagram and Twitter
and you can follow the show on liveinlumbo.com,
iTunes, YouTube, BitChute, and at some point on Spotify.
And today with me, I have Daniel Affigiello.
Welcome to New Human Podcast, Daniel.
Hey, glad to be here, brother.
Yeah, let's start with your background,
the work you've done, the lives you've lived
and what are you mainly focused on now these days?
Yeah, so I began sort of not in the computer science space.
So right now I'm the founder and head of research
at a company called Emerge Artificial Intelligence Research
that I founded some three years ago
when I sold my last business.
So at Emerge, our work is really
mapping the return on investment of AI in the private sector.
So we look at banking and financial services,
we look at pharmaceutical,
we look at the range of AI use cases
and which of them are actually delivering value
and we provide research products and data and advisory,
kind of like a Forrester or a Gardner,
to big companies who want to actually see a return
from artificial intelligence.
We do a good deal of work in the public sector as well,
mostly in defense and security,
financial crime, surveillance, things along those lines,
but primarily in the private sector,
it's going to be financial services, life sciences.
So market research is the name of the game,
but you want me to get into the old school stuff.
Yeah, it's interesting to have context
where the perspective of each individual comes from.
I mean, I want to talk about Emerge,
I want to talk about AI,
but it's also interesting to know who is representing
and expressing these ideas about AI.
For sure.
Well, I'll give you, I guess, a little bit of backdrop.
So I'm not exactly from a tech background at all,
I'm from a 4,000 person town in Rhode Island
called Wakefield, Rhode Island.
You've never heard of it before,
and you will from this point until you're deaf,
never hear of it again.
It's a very small place.
It's a quaint place, a beautiful place,
but it's not a place I could stay,
given my objectives in life.
So that's where I'm from,
and the way that I paid for college,
and ultimately for Ivy League graduate school
at the University of Pennsylvania,
where I studied cognitive science,
and my focus was on skill development
and skill acquisition.
So the cognitive science of acquiring skills quickly.
The reason I went in for that
is because I was in combat sports.
So the way I was paying the bills
was running a martial arts gym.
So I was training fighters.
We had some fitness classes,
but it was mostly mixed martial arts and Brazilian jiu-jitsu.
So I have a black belt in Brazilian jiu-jitsu.
I've trained extensively, given seminars
around the United States and even in Brazil,
and won a national tournament,
and did a lot of competing in my day.
And so that's how I was kind of paying the bills.
And so I was really interested in what does it look like
to improve faster from an athlete perspective,
training my own fighters, training myself.
And so that's what I went to graduate school for.
And when I was there, this is back in 2011,
I was getting capped on the shoulder that,
hey, Dan, all this human learning stuff,
all this neural stuff,
they're kind of doing that with computers.
And this is the really early days of ImageNet,
when ImageNet started becoming exciting.
This is also the very early days
of when they were applying natural language processing
to Twitter data.
There was something called Google Zeitgeist
that UPenn was involved with at the time,
deriving sentiment from different factors
in the social media ether,
and kind of determining how that correlated
to different cities,
and how weather affected different cities,
and the moods of people, and the sicknesses of people,
and things along those lines.
So when I got out of grad school with the psych degree,
I kind of became convinced this AI stuff,
looking at the near term,
and then also reading people like Nick Bostrom
and Ben Goertzel, and learning about the long term.
I was lucky enough to interview Ben Goertzel
and Bostrom pretty much right out of grad school.
I talked to all the major players in the AGI space.
I became very convinced
that in both the near and the long term,
this was an exceedingly important technology,
and that my understanding from a conceptual level
in the cognitive sciences,
I should just be able to transfer that over.
So I got right into really studying this stuff,
and then talking to the leading figures there,
and eventually started a company.
Very cool.
I mean, you must have started with interest in the mind,
getting into martial art,
the kind of martial art that you got into.
It's not that, hey, let's just go out and kick some ass.
It's more about finding yourself, right?
Through that art of battle.
Yeah, there's something to be said of that.
I don't personally overly spiritualize martial arts.
I think some people will play it up.
They'll be like, oh yes, I'm a martial artist,
and so you should presume that I am wise.
I actually don't do that.
I think if I am wise,
it's because I've read Montaigne and Plutarch,
more than because I've choked men unconscious.
But I've done both,
and I can say that certainly part of the fascination
of the mind is from beginning with martial arts,
and being able to see how different people learn,
and also see how I learned, right?
To go from, you know, in Rhode Island,
there's not that many good training partners,
so to win national tournaments is actually pretty difficult.
And I had to figure out how to go about drilling,
figure out what kind of training regimens
to build for myself.
And it wasn't just what kind of weights to lift.
In fact, I wasn't doing much of that.
It was what kind of skills do I want to acquire?
And so that forced me to think about,
well, how does this thing upstairs actually work?
And how can I learn as quickly as possible
to really perform and also have my competitors
do very well in tournaments too?
So yeah, it was less spiritual,
but it certainly was psychological in martial arts,
and that's what got me to UPenn and ultimately into AI.
Yeah, in addition to spirituality,
it's also that you had choked people unconscious,
but I assume that you were also choked unconscious yourself.
You were placed on the other side of the equation.
Sure, sure did.
I mean, everybody weighs more than me.
I'm a pretty small fella,
so I did a lot of competitions
against very, very big opponents.
In fact, if you go on Google,
you type in Dan Fijella versus the Giant,
you'll see me in a jujitsu match
against a guy that weighs 80 pounds, 100 pounds more than me
who's actually a UFC fighter.
His name is Pat Walsh.
So this guy fought in the cage with other 220 pound men.
I walk around at about a buck 25.
So definitely, I didn't beat all those guys.
That was a good match.
I'll fortunately beat that guy.
But yeah, I certainly had my ears boxed pretty good.
You can see my cauliflower ear is pretty rough.
And I've certainly, you know,
I'm gonna have knee problems when I'm older.
That's just a fact.
I'm gonna have shoulder problems when I'm older.
But right now, it doesn't keep me from doing market research
and what I love, so, you know.
Yeah, it just seems that that experience of humility
and empathy that you create
when you're on the other side of something like that
is also helpful when you're working on,
let's say, artificial intelligence,
which is a big difference from what is being written down
on paper and in academia
than what it's being implemented within the society,
especially the society right now today
that a lot of people are freaked out
by just the name artificial intelligence
and in a lot of aspect for right reasons, right?
So I'm trying to get into,
and we've talked about this a lot in this podcast,
that what you put on the paper,
it might seem awesome and sounds great,
but there's a big difference between what sounds good
and sounds sensible on the paper
than when it's being implemented within the society
when a lot of people have a problem
even accepting the existence of such a thing
that is going to compete with human intelligence
and human, basically the concept of humanity.
Yeah, I think, you know, in the near term,
there's the job and economic considerations
that are real.
I don't think we're gonna see the wave of automation
across the country in the very, very near term,
but I do foresee in the next 10 years,
we did a very substantial poll in 2015 of AI researchers
and by a wide margin,
the most significant and consistent AI risk
in the next 20 years, this is five years ago,
was the economic and job impact.
So I think that seems like a reasonable fear,
but I think to your point,
there is the actual species dominant stuff
if we look 50 years out, 100 years out
that I think is considerable as well.
So yeah, you're right.
I mean, AI in theory and AI in practice,
it's a lot less predictable when it's off the paper.
Social adoption is a big part of any kind of technology
that would progress, right?
So you can recommend certain things to a business
and it might seem all good, a certain kind of a technology,
but when the society is rejecting that kind of technology,
I bring up Google Glass, for example, as an example,
that it was a very practical thing,
well-designed and great, but people didn't like it.
Some because they couldn't get it,
some because they thought, oh, you're taking this,
it jeopardizes my privacy
and you think you're better than me
and all those things, you know?
Yeah, we did a very early interview in 2012
with the head of Engadget at the time.
Engadget is a big consumer tech blog
who talked about his experience
of wearing Google Glass in the subway
and walking his dog and things like that
and just how it wasn't really gonna fit
into the normal mesh of society and the public.
There was in San Francisco?
I forget where Tim is based, Tim Stevens.
This is a great many years ago,
but I suspect it was the Bay Area.
Yeah, because people were getting attacked.
You know, there were videos taken by those,
you know, people who were wearing it
in bars and restaurants
and people were getting attacked
just because of wearing the glass.
Part of it was the argument for privacy,
but the other part was that, hey,
this is not even something we can't buy from the store.
This has to be given to you.
Yeah, so it was like lording over people,
kind of like, ah, I've been granted
this recording intelligence layer
and you don't have it.
There's a certain kind of elitism
that it seems like we can't get away with that.
You know, genetic engineering is another field
that will create this kind of elitism
that, hey, if you can't afford it,
not only financially, but also,
you know, there's a big difference between China,
let's say, and the United States,
and I wanna talk to you about that too,
because you mentioned you're talking to
and you're advising private companies,
but I also see on your website that you've spoken to,
for example, United Nations, Harvard University.
What was, oh, you talked to United Nations,
as I see, about deepfakes, is that right?
Yeah, so we actually, United Nations,
World Bank, Interpol, the OECD,
I mean, we work with-
So beyond the private sector also.
Yeah, these are the most substantial
intergovernmental organizations in the world
who are, luckily, at this point,
at least allocating a certain amount of attention
to artificial intelligence,
and there are certainly initiatives
that I really believe in there.
And not all of those organizations
are our clients, formally, some are.
We've done substantial projects with the World Bank,
for example, but some are just speaking engagements,
because I happen to think it's a very valuable topic
that should be at UN headquarters,
and we were called upon to talk about it.
So deepfakes is a good example of that,
where I'm pretty close with the folks
that run the artificial intelligence and robotics wing
of what is called Unicrit,
which is the crime and justice wing of the United Nations.
I really respect those guys, I think they do a great job,
and they have a thorough understanding of the space.
Not everybody in the intergovernmental domain does.
And they had called us in to essentially create a deepfake
of the head of Unicrit, so a woman by the name of Bettina,
who was the director of that wing of the United Nations.
So we took a video of her,
and then we made her say a bunch of things she never said,
and then also extrapolated that into
how almost anything can be programmatically generated,
and how much better and better
that programmatic generation is becoming,
and what some of the considerations might be.
My personal focus is on the long-term of that.
Yes, political influence, I think, is something.
Media and truth is something.
I think the actual leap in the human experience,
when we can push a button
and have what we wish before our eyes,
the conjuring of what we wish before our eyes,
I think is a much grander transition
than is spoken about in the purely political space.
So I tried to create that stretch for UN leadership there.
So democratization of information is the big picture,
is what you're talking about,
because it's not only deepfakes,
but also, let's say, 3D printing,
that now we have to deal with the very reality
that within a couple of years,
some parts of a gun can be very viably printed
inside of someone's bedroom,
and there's nothing anybody can do about it.
Yeah, my personal expertise
is not in 3D printing.
We've done a couple bits of coverage
on the intersection of what is called
additive manufacturing,
sort of the broad umbrella of 3D printing, and AI,
so where those two mesh.
But making projections around that tech,
I have much less confidence than I do
in, let's say, artificial intelligence
in almost any industry.
But yeah, to your point,
that's part of the transition.
I think what I'm articulating explicitly here
is a broader dynamic of a kind of going in,
so the majority, the bulk of our experience
transitions into virtual spaces.
So you and I are kind of doing that right now.
I do that on my phone a good deal.
We're all on a screen a really good percentage of the time,
and if you look at human life
and human life on screen time as a graph here,
I mean, you don't have to be a rocket scientist.
And I think that when we can call forth
the kinds of experiences we want,
whether it's a relaxing background to do our work,
whether it's a movie that's created just for us, right?
I wanna learn about the French Revolution,
but I wanna learn about it through the eyes of St. Just,
and I don't really care that much
about the post-revolutionary Bonaparte stuff.
I just wanna go right up until St. Just death, that's it,
and I wanna look through his eyes.
When a movie can be played
per my preferences in creation
and based on my past learning
based on my current responsiveness, right?
Am I attentive or is it boring me
being able to have that generated in real time?
I think that might be 15 years off,
but I think that we get to a point
where the compellingness of virtual ecosystems
will be so amazing in terms of fulfilling drives
for curiosity, creativity, for love,
eventually with haptics that might involve sex.
Lord knows how that's gonna evolve.
That's not exactly my focus area,
but I do think there's gonna be transitions there too,
and I think that as the body becomes a husk
and as most of what we wish in its highest form,
right now, if you ask me, Dan,
what is the most refreshing, rewarding,
lovely thing that you could do,
I would tell you it is walking in nature,
reading actual papyrus in a really, really good book,
like not Kindle, I mean like paper,
I don't have ancient texts in my house,
but I'm not, even if I was-
I was gonna ask, you can't read papyrus?
Even if I was exorbitantly wealthy,
I would not become such a profligate
in my collecting of texts like that,
but I like me a good old book,
and I like to breathe in the pine,
and I like to see the sunset and those sorts of things,
but I am not above the idea that within 15 years,
a programmatically generated permutation of that,
even the wind through my hair
in a programmatically generated sense
might be astronomically more refreshing,
because it would be hyper-calibrated
to all the very best experiences of that in the past,
and that is in fact the transition I'm talking about.
I wrote an article called Lotus Eaters and World Eaters,
so Lotus Eaters and World Eaters.
If Googled, that article would come up,
and this is about the bigger transition.
So for me, I think democratization of information
is a very big part of it.
I think that going in is the dynamic
that I consider to be astronomically disruptive,
and I think essentially a borderline
no one is talking about.
That's very interesting,
because recently we've been talking about
when people are talking about AI, artificial intelligence,
and I like personally to think of that A
as augmented intelligence as well,
that you don't really have to reverse engineer
and rebuild the entire brain or an intelligence.
You can use it as a mesh net, basically,
or exoskeleton, right?
But the argument that I'm hearing is that AI
is focused on the thinking mind, on the analytical mind,
on the left brain, basically.
The right brain and instincts
and things we cannot really describe by words,
that is something that we can't even begin
to understand ourselves, let alone trying to replicate
that with any kind of a machine intelligence.
But that is a huge part of what you're talking about,
to merging, basically, within blurring this line
of what is real and what is not real
further and further in the coming years.
Yeah, and I would say, so I may not describe it similarly.
I think it's an interesting distinction,
the left and right brain.
I would say that certainly at an emotive level,
I don't think we're able to replicate,
to the best of our knowledge,
we're not able to replicate sentience in AI,
although we did do a pretty extensive poll
of artificial intelligence researchers
around when sentience might be possible,
something like 2060.
Who knows if they're right, right?
Nobody knows if anybody's right.
But I'm curious about the topic.
Consciousness, I think, is a morally worthy thing.
It might be the morally worthy thing,
but that's its own conversational threat.
But right and left brain, I think,
it's tough to say where AI actually sits,
because, for example, if we look at
the programmatically generated stuff,
in the future, let's say 10 years from now,
if you are a designer of logos, like company logos,
you will not just take 15 hours
to craft one really good logo
and then take another 15 hours
to craft another really good logo.
You may begin with simply a verbalized
or set of checkboxes, set of configurable features,
like what are the values we want to convey,
what are the values we stand for as a company,
what kind of color palettes are we thinking
might be good, whatever,
and have a programmatically generated plethora of logos
that are already stacked and ranked
based on what we would presume
humans would respond to most favorably
based on the values that we had set before.
Now, we would need a really big data set
of people looking at different logos
and correlating them with values,
and we're not there yet.
But if nothing else, we could start with a plethora,
and we could take individual permutations,
determine some tweaks, determine some adjustments,
and create another plethora off of that one permutation,
and in so doing, generate just generally
better and more ideas, better and more ideas.
Same with architecture, same with fashion,
same with textiles, same with name your damn
creative domain, creating beats.
You want to create music for the elevator,
you want to create rap music.
I mean, being able to just have
programmatically generated beats
that we know are going to hit,
that we know are going to respond,
that people are going to respond well to.
We might train it off of Spotify data
in terms of what's most popular right now.
We might train it off of whatever we want to do.
This sort of extension of what you might refer to
as the left brain will eventually become the norm
in a great many creative fields.
Now, is that going to be 10 years?
Is that going to be 15 years?
I can't exactly tell you, but I will say
there was a time where as a graphic designer,
you didn't need to know how to use a computer.
And let me tell you, my good man, times have changed.
And let me tell you, my good man,
in 15 years, times will change again.
And this kind of technology will be part of that change.
I think a good point of distinction,
you mentioned with music, for example.
What constitutes better
is the context that already exists, right?
That is determined based on us, humans,
who are, we are very limited in our experience.
It's linear.
And the argument can be made that for AI
to reaches its true potential,
it should not rely on humanity whatsoever.
So after that point, the argument would become,
would the AI, artificial intelligence,
be able to create a beat or a piece of music
that has absolutely no root within the context
that is created by human civilization
and is something that is introducing
a new context altogether?
Does it make sense?
Yes, it does.
And I don't know if you wanted to go
this far down the rabbit hole,
but there isn't a depth that you could go
that I will not follow you.
Oh, amazing.
I'm mostly interested in rabbit holes
because academic sides, I'm like,
everything is written on Google.
There are so many people who can nail those things better,
but I think it's very important to be imaginative
and consider many different options
that we have to deal with in the coming years.
I think these are interesting topics.
Again, they aren't things that I'd be called upon
to speak about at Interpol or at Citibank,
but they are the long ball consequences
that I think, as you pointed out,
it's important to kind of splay those open
and see what does this mean?
Where does this go?
To your point about music,
I think the question here would be
what would be the purpose of music?
If the purpose is enjoyment
and we are the only sentient things that enjoys,
then I suspect you're right.
We may be able to start from scratch
and create beats and permutations of sound
that really don't resemble any known musical genre
that might be extremely appealing to some people.
Very rare that music would be appealing to everybody,
but that might be doable.
Now, if AI itself could become sentient in some sense,
maybe it would create,
if artificial general intelligence
were to create art for itself, two things.
A, it's extremely unlikely we would be able to understand it,
and B, it's extremely unlikely it would have a form
that we now recognize.
It's not gonna be carving marble.
It's not gonna be fricking oil paints.
It's gonna be something astronomically more complicated,
and from the viewpoint
of something astronomically more intelligent,
it'll be astronomically more beautiful.
The language of such an entity,
we might think about it,
like you and I have an alphabet.
We're speaking English right now.
You may speak other languages, I don't.
I pretend to have a fistful of French words,
but I go no farther.
I'm an uncultured American.
History, I'm pretty strong, but languages.
Let's presume we're talking about the English alphabet.
We've got a couple dozen letters to work with here,
and we can only talk at this current bandwidth.
An AGI might have a number of symbols
that it might communicate with,
either itself or other AGI's.
We might imagine a cube of a million pixels this way,
and a million pixels this way,
and each of those pixels can have
one of two trillion different permutations
of what we want to call it,
like color number, what have you,
and that any combination of all of that
pushed through is like a letter.
And so we couldn't possibly imagine
the full extent of what expression would be
for something beyond us,
no better than a caterpillar could imagine our expression,
could imagine Shakespeare's sonnets,
could imagine great architecture,
Corinthian columns.
Caterpillars ain't gonna cut that mustard,
and we ain't gonna cut the mustard
of what's beyond us either.
Yeah, we are creating a new and different kind of a species
than humanity, and I think this is very important
for people to understand that this is not a phase
or a trend that's just gonna go away,
and in 10 years, people will be in charge
of everything again.
Like, it's just not gonna happen.
Yeah, I think a lot of people do operate
under that assumption, though.
I think it is really seen as a very short-term transition.
Is it also shared within governments and UN
and those places that you talk at?
Yeah, I mean, in the broad sweep,
so my unabashed long-term objective here
is to bring what I refer to as
the trajectory of intelligence conversation
into these organizations which I have a relationship with.
However, I'm not here to impose that
when it's not a time that they're interested about it, right?
I have certain people within these orgs
that I can talk about all manner of topics,
but for many, the reason I'm called on
is because we study what's possible and what's working,
so they're gonna have an academic,
they might have an expert in computer vision,
but they need somebody who's gonna say,
well, here's where it's impacting this industry,
here's where it's impacting the industry,
here's what makes it hard to adopt,
here's what makes it easy to adopt in defense,
here's what, they need a reality check
on where it's impacting the world,
and that's why I step into the World Bank
to enter poll, et cetera.
So I'm not gonna force feed them that stuff,
but it is my unabashed goal
to eventually be able to introduce these themes,
and we have a new series,
we have a podcast called the AI in Business podcast,
and we have a Saturday series called AI Futures,
where we're kind of stretching this,
we're taking people from reputable organizations,
like let's say Berkeley,
Stuart Russell was our first guest on this podcast,
the OECD, folks from the Future of Humanity Institute
at Oxford, and we're having them kind of stretch
the credible viewpoints
into where is this ultimately taking us?
Because for me, I think we do need to consider those things,
to your point, right now in government and in business,
it is absolutely not on the radar.
It's not even fiction,
it's literally not on the table in any way.
It's not even digestible, it's almost invisible,
even if it were to be articulated,
it would not even land on the table, it doesn't exist.
And it's shared in politics.
I mean, you see how important AI is,
and nobody's really talking about it.
Nobody's talking about the long-term, no.
Even short-term, you see like neither Trump or Biden
are really talking about AI,
but AI is going to have huge impacts
on every single human being's lives on this planet.
And I think, so what is it to be a politician?
Just winning a popularity contest.
In Emerson's words,
to eat dust before the men
who actually stand behind the throne,
something akin to this.
Now, I don't know, I'm not disparaging politicians,
not even in the slightest.
In fact, I do respect the profession
despite the gritty realities they're in.
But to be a politician, like you said,
yes, popularity contest.
So why aren't they talking about AI?
It just doesn't matter enough to the constituents, right?
Why are they talking about name your topic, sir?
Name your topic.
I mean, the most arbitrary things
become giant friction points,
and then they get in all the speeches.
Is it because of their inherent meaning
and some platonic reality?
No, no, no.
It's simply because they resonate with the constituency.
So we can expect AI to land
on the sort of political speech table
when it matters to the people who are being spoken to.
Yeah, the disruption of AI and technology
basically are not in any shape or form
determined by the political will
or social will to accept them though.
That's the thing, like you're talking about deep fakes.
Deep fakes will come and disrupt future political campaigns
from the perspective of constituents and the politicians
and all of them altogether
without anybody agreeing or disagreeing with them.
It does not require agreement of people
to go in that certain kind of a speed
that technology is evolving, right?
So it's important to at least acknowledge
the huge disruption that we haven't seen anything of it yet.
Because what we are experiencing right now,
is this seemingly division that exists globally, really.
A lot of people can say that this is because people
finally have channels of expressions
in the form of social media that now they can be heard.
When you say division, by the way,
I just want to follow you, what do you mean?
So division, for example,
what is being portrayed by the media
and what is being portrayed by certain news media?
Division right and left, division upper and lower class.
I mean, what is the core division?
Political, political division.
Yeah, because the class division,
nobody really wants to talk about.
I don't know enough about the class division
to have a firm opinion on that, but okay.
So you're talking about the more or less
the left and right to some degree.
Right, right.
Like this recent example of the video
of George Floyd getting killed by the police,
which is horrible, and it started a lot of consequences
as a result of it.
But in a couple of years, a fake video can come up
of a very same kind of a thing
that half of the audience and half of the viewers
will believe it right off the bat.
Well, this is going to have very real consequences
socially and politically.
Yeah, you know, this really is on my mind a lot.
So, I mean, again, UN, I've been on,
I was in television in Singapore on this same topic.
What does this mean for the future?
And also with reference to this political division,
I've thought a lot about it.
And on some level, I didn't see it coming as fast as it was.
So I was at Facebook headquarters in 2016.
You're talking about Deepfakes.
No, I wasn't talking about Deepfakes,
but I was at Facebook headquarters in 2016
talking to the head of core machine learning at the time,
fellow by the name of Hussein Mahena,
very sharp fellow, I think he's with Google now.
They always swap around over there.
There's only so many places to go in SF,
but a really sharp fellow.
And I recall only very lightly talking about
what was beginning to rattle.
This is before Trump was elected.
What was beginning to rattle is this idea of echo chambers
for political perspectives.
And I thought to myself, you know,
I'm not seeing that much of it just yet right now
in my own experience.
I don't really see that as like the real workhorse
of, you know, friction in society.
But by golly, four years later,
you know, I can tell you that the echo chamber thing,
it's not just, well, more people have a voice
and that's why they're fighting each other.
I would actually push back on that idea very firmly.
I would push back on that idea.
I suspect that there are mounted incentives
and money to be made and influence to be wielded
that sort of make incessant division just work, right?
I mean, who has a Twitter following
more than 100,000 people who isn't primarily
basing it on a for or against or an affinity, right?
Oh, you know, I run a puppy kennel or something,
or I like take pictures on the beach
and I'm an attractive woman.
Like, sort them out.
Intellectuals, you're gonna pop off
if you can have a strong enemy, right?
Because you've already got a huge resonance.
If you're kind of middle of the road,
it's like you're the enemy of both, man.
And I think that what I like about Boston
is it's actually okay to be middle of the road.
I am, I'm tied to neither political party.
You can do that and not be a bad guy.
In San Francisco, I mean, you're essentially a Bible thumper.
Now, I've never read the Bible, but oddly enough,
I'm close to being one in the Bay Area.
And you with that American flag, I would not recommend.
So you doing that within 20 miles of San Francisco,
I would not recommend it.
And you know, I was a refugee in Canada
and I'm an ex-Muslim immigrant in the US.
And I'm glad we have you.
I'm glad it's helping out.
All it takes is one, quote unquote,
wrong interpretation of the US flag, for example,
which I had in my room in Tehran.
You know, United States is a beacon of light still.
For people all around the world,
you see protesters in Hong Kong
under that kind of a situation,
they're waving the American flags.
It has a meaning beyond politics and geography.
Yeah, I hope it retains that meaning, that's my hope.
I agree.
I'm not here calling America good ubiquitously, right?
I'm obviously not doing that.
But I am saying that it's a shame
when it's ubiquitously seen as evil,
because I think we actually have a lot more in common
that hopefully we can get along with,
but technology is certainly veering us away
from having concord here.
Yeah, it also shows deeper parts of human nature, right?
Like what you were saying that people depend on division
in order to capitalize on it.
This is something that is very deeply woven
within who we are.
Oh yes, oh yes, the tribe, sir, the tribe.
Yeah.
I mean, you know, we are a tribal species
and us versus them is the automatic frame.
It takes vigilant volitional effort
to do anything other than think us versus them
in almost all circumstances.
I mean, maybe that's a bit of a stretch,
but to be frank, it's quite clearly the norm.
You know, anyone who considers themselves
free entirely of that dynamic,
I think is generally fooling themselves to a spooky degree.
I think we should be aware of just how consistent
and vigilant we have to be
and that we're never gonna be perfect in that category.
But I hope we can work at it.
I don't think we're doing a great job right now
as a country.
As a country, yeah, especially with China
on the other side of the equation.
Yeah, all right, you want to?
Yeah, let's get in there.
Yeah.
I remember talking to someone in Toronto
a couple of years ago at a Toronto transhumanist meetup
and we talked for like three hours.
It's awesome.
And at the end, it was like, you know,
the really only three things matter in this world,
China, United States and what they do
with artificial intelligence.
And this was a couple of years ago
and it seems to be the case.
My friends in Paris would be angry if I agreed with you.
So I'm gonna pretend to disagree with you.
Please expand on that.
Yeah, yeah.
I would take a lot of flack.
No, I mean, what for you is interesting
about the US China AI race?
I mean, I think about this incessantly
and I think about this from a defense perspective.
I think about this from a media perspective.
I spoke in Shanghai for the United Nations.
I've interviewed a tremendous number of companies
with co-founders in China that are in the AI space
as well as investors in the Asian AI ecosystem.
And so I have vantage points
that have fleshed this out pretty reasonably thoroughly.
I mean, I'm not an expert in its entirety,
but what makes it interesting for you?
What's important about that dynamic?
What's interesting to me is within the context
of human nature, the tribalism that we talked about
and how we have always used technology as a tool
in order to pursue our human intentions.
And the biggest tribes right now I see in the world
is the Chinese Communist Party and the United States
government that they're clearly in conflict with each other,
which creates, competition is always good
to develop new things.
It creates like space race and a lot of our technology
is contribution of the wars that we have fought, right?
But at the end of the day, it's very important
to understand that AI is perhaps the ultimate tool
and ultimate depending on the intention
can be used as a weapon, can be used as like,
it's like any other tool, you know,
with fire you can warm yourself up
or burn down your entire building.
And it's very interesting to me because I know China
has access to more data than United States
and US is kind of, now please correct me if I'm wrong,
but it seems like US is lagging behind China
specifically because of the decentralized system
that the US has versus a centrally driven group
of engineers in China that were like,
this is our objective, we're gonna get it no matter how.
And in the United States, you have to, you know,
argue about the definition of the word, for example,
is for many months, costing millions and millions of dollars.
Yeah, and I mean, the communist system,
never having worked within it or understanding it
to a great extent, I'm sure has its own hiccups
and what we might refer to as inefficiencies
with corruption and, you know, however that operates.
But to your point, so I wrote a rather in-depth article
called The Seven Weaknesses of the West.
So someone typed eMERGE, E-M-E-R-J,
Seven Weaknesses of the West, they'd find it on Google.
And this really summarizes a lot of what I consider
to be where we're behind the eight ball with China.
Now the United States, I did another very lengthy piece
on the AI and China ecosystem, how it's developing,
how it's evolving, the kinds of startups, et cetera.
That's its own bit of research I believe is free as well.
But we have more academic muscle.
We have more actual scientists
and actual scientists who have experience deploying it,
which is a really, really good distinction
because coming out of Carnegie Mellon is kinda neat,
you know, like you're not dumb.
That's awesome, that's great.
But actually having experience,
turning that into a user experience
or reducing money laundering in a bank
or improving retention for a subscription service,
that's a much more robust, practical, applicable experience.
And that's frankly not something
you can get in purely academia.
So we have certainly some edges here.
And I think some people are optimistic
that the free market system
will also just be more creative writ large.
That said, there are a lot of disadvantages.
And a lot of them I think have to do with,
you mentioned centralization.
I think a lot of this ties to the ability
for the Chinese Communist Party
to marshal a united front of effort.
And that involves many factors here.
That involves the private sector and academia
essentially just being wings of the great and ruling power.
So being nothing more but wings, nothing more.
That's a very powerful and lovely place to be.
And in fact, Confucius, there's no better setup.
So Xi Jinping, if your objective
was to rule without question,
Xi Jinping would be, I mean, I think he's in a great spot.
I mean, if that was your goal, Ryan, I'm just saying
if it was your goal, he's in the best spot.
Objectively speaking.
There is no, pericles is not revered in China, right?
The Socrates and Christ of China
would be Confucius almost unquestionably.
And man, I mean, Confucius is real congenial
to everything lining up to the great emperor.
Now I'm not saying Confucius advocates for tyranny.
In fact, I think it's pretty clear he doesn't.
But it can be bent and molded so sweetly, so snuggly
in a nice, obedient alignment.
And I think so culturally, he sits in just
an absolutely beautiful, almost impeccable cultural soil
for what he is to do.
And they have the wings of the party dynamic going on.
I think they also have the ruler for life thing, right?
Now, now, ruler for life.
I mean, they don't fall from their position
until the mandate of heaven takes them off of it, right?
This is like BC, we're talking BC here, these precedencies.
This is a culture that is, I mean, rich, in my opinion,
rich and amazing to no end, to no end.
I mean, the Tang dynasty.
I mean, I'm so fascinated with the history of China.
I'm not a big CCP fan, but China,
I'm just like ravenously interested across the board.
But many of these precedents are very early.
And now they're wielding them and they're leveraging them
in a way that really makes a lot of sense.
And so Xi can think about a 20-year goal.
Trump has gotta get elected, you know?
He's gotta get elected.
And whoever's after him has gotta get elected.
For Xi, it's kind of like, he can set a 20-40 goal
and he can genuinely take a hard swing at that, right?
Deng Jinping was up there for Lord knows how long.
What was he, 90 or something when he stepped down?
It's a, so these guys can take a really good run at it.
And that ability to think long-term, I think,
puts us at a sincere disadvantage.
So do you see, this is actually a very interesting point.
Do you see the representative democracy as a system
is a system worthy of being disrupted
considering that your competitor is being driven
on a centrally driven kind of a system?
Which I also wanna add,
this was something brought up in Joe Rogan podcast,
as Salma mentioned, I keep bringing this up,
that China is run by engineers,
United States is run by lawyers.
So there's a very big difference,
not only implementing solutions,
but also recognizing problems and solutions
to be the most practical kind of solutions.
And we seem to be stuck in this representative democracy
and all the consequences of it.
That question, I think it's,
I would say this is an apt time to ask that question.
I would also say it is beyond my pale
to have firm and square opinions
about the how of the reconstruction.
Again, it's not my domain.
I'll speak to things that I feel confident about
and not so much ones I don't.
But I do believe,
I have reason to believe from my vantage point
and my own experience of where I feel like
I have expertise that's worthwhile to talk about
that it's warranted to question it.
Because some of these points,
so the whole point of that seven weaknesses
of the West article,
and I have some other pieces coming out about China
in the coming three or four months,
particularly around media.
That is to say,
our media is essentially built to divide us
and China gets free reign to come in however they want.
Buy up the movie theaters,
buy up the movie studios,
we're all using TikTok, right?
And what are they using?
Google and Facebook?
Nay, my comrade, nay, my comrade.
So they get to mold this,
what they would refer to as harmony,
we might refer to as something more akin to obedience.
Something more akin to like break your legs
if you do the wrong kind of yoga in the park,
Falun Gong.
But they would call it harmony.
So they were able to consciously mold that
through the entirety of their digital ecosystems
that were not a part of it.
They can buy the movie theaters out, brother.
They can buy the people who make the films out, brother.
They can buy up the big gaming companies.
You see Blizzard,
you're not allowed to talk about Uyghurs on Blizzard, right?
So media is its own ball of wax.
But yeah, I would say given those present dynamics,
there's someone I follow on Twitter
whose name now completely evades me,
who framed it very well, better than I had previously,
is that there's a default momentum
where we would then just follow and keep up with China
in terms of control and media
in order to make sure that we're not weaker than them.
That that might be a natural momentum,
which is dangerous, right?
To be a follower and to also follow of anybody, Mao.
I mean, if you're gonna give me one person to follow,
I will give you a million human beings
before I give you Mao.
I will give you literally a million men,
a million men or women.
I'll give you Thatcher, I'll give you, name him.
I'll give you Joan of Arc.
I mean, I don't care, anybody but Mao.
So I think that the default momentum is in that direction.
We do have to think about what does it look like
to maintain our strengths and our values
while also dealing with the reality
of the digital ecosystem that we exist in.
And one of my big contentions with defense
is that I think a tremendous amount of money
goes into things that rust,
that is to say tanks, et cetera, et cetera.
While China, I think intelligently,
is playing the economic and playing the digital
and media game, which is much more plausibly deniable.
And I think in the future
will be a much bigger lever of influence.
And so I think that they're playing smarter
than we are in that domain.
Very well said.
Do you think it's corruption that takes more money
towards the rustable things that you're talking about?
Like they have lobbyists and contractors
and connections with certain manufacturers.
You know, I don't know enough
about what is called the military industrial complex.
I don't know it.
In fact, I don't know enough
to even have a firm opinion on that phrase.
So I've spoken with folks in defense, writ large,
I consider them to be good folks,
but it wouldn't surprise me if there was all manner
of dealings and whatnot that might be less than ideal
and it might be kind of tainted incentives
in many different regards.
But I can't speak to it enough.
I don't have enough experience.
Is DARPA still the leading,
I guess you can call them agency or department or whatever
with respect to artificial intelligence?
Yeah, you know, they still,
they have so many different branches now.
And I think what I am heartened by
is that there are more of these efforts
to improve public private sector partnership,
really, really direct efforts.
We did a very robust report
about the all of the published AI strategy docs
from the US public sector.
So the AI.gov and all the permutations
that are publicly available.
What do they have in common?
What are the common initiatives?
A critical thrust across absolutely all of them
is improving public private sector partnerships.
And we see new organizations
like it used to be called the DIUX.
Now it's called the DIU.
It's sort of another sort of investment venture wing.
We have things like Incutel and DARPA
that have been around forever.
DARPA is obviously still a huge deal.
But we also have similar little,
we could call sort of like accelerator incubators
slash venture arms of even the Air Force
has their own shtick.
They have a little camp that they run in Boston
and a place that they rent out.
And I think they make investments
and work with tech talent and whatnot.
So there's a spidering proliferation of these groups.
I don't know enough about their coordination
to say if I feel good about that.
My inkling is it's not amazing
because defense is very complicated.
But yeah, DARPA still, I would say the best known
to the best of my knowledge.
But luckily it's proliferating.
Excellent.
Based on the data and understanding
that you have gathered within these years,
you must have some kind of end game kind of a picture
for US AI supremacy and Chinese AI supremacy.
Do you have something like that?
I do, I've written an article on it.
So what are some of the drastic contrast
between those kind of words?
The word where AI is driven by a US supremacy
or the world that AI is driven by Chinese supremacy?
Yeah, you know, I try my hardest
to not think about that as my default frame.
It's very hard not to
because of the whole Thucydides trap
and because of the level of tension
that we're dealing with right now.
But in my heart of hearts as a first swing,
I have an article called We Unite or We Fight,
so E-M-E-R-J, We Unite or We Fight,
which is really around getting on the same page.
It's a horrible word, but same-pagedness,
we could call it solidarity,
around what kind of 10-year, 20-year,
even maybe longer, visions we want for a global society
and being able to somewhere agree on that,
to align and have transparency and steering,
shared transparency and steering
around where the big trajectory actually goes.
That said, I'm not necessarily an optimist
to that same-pagedness between China as it stands today
and the US is really all that possible.
If China had the government of Japan, for example,
I probably really wouldn't be all that democratic nation.
I mean, I just don't really think
there's gonna be that many problems with that.
I mean, Japan's a different ballgame than us,
but democracy-wise, and people are people,
there's no issues with individual Chinese folks
by any means, but yeah, I feel as though
the kind of global solidarity and alignment
that would be required to get on the same page
about what are we to turn into,
what is the human experience to be,
what is the global community to bloom into
beyond the present human experience,
because we're not really gonna be able to stop that train,
hopefully we can guide it,
hopefully it can be something other than war
that drives it forward.
So that article articulates what my hoped vision would be,
which is not war, which is solidarity,
but I'll tell you, to get to that solidarity,
that's, there's gotta be a smarter guy than me for that one.
Sometimes just parts come from different kind of
experience and background.
It's been true with certain religions that
some religions, they just do not wanna get along
with other religions or other competitors.
They demand submission.
That's what they're demanding.
However, we fool ourselves in this part of the world.
That doesn't change their status quo and default state.
So it seems like there is a fundamental disconnect
between the Chinese Communist Party,
and I'm not dividing based on good and bad
or any kind of ethical or moral judgment,
but they're just coming from a very different kind of a place
and looking for a very different kind of an outcome
than the United States.
I think that is certainly the case.
What I will say about the United States,
as absolutely horrible as I think we're doing right now
on the global stage from Trump to you name it.
I mean, as just brutal as our perception is globally,
our value prop is, it ain't that bad.
It ain't that bad, man.
I mean, there's a lot of countries that dig our value prop
more than whatever they were rocking with
before they had it.
And I'm now, am I advocating for colonial,
not even freaking close, right?
But somebody would misinterpret that
because that's the world we live in right now.
What I will say is that just as a culture,
the general value prop I think is really strong.
It's very hard for China to,
so I believe there's a permutation of a Machiavelli quote,
something akin to, and this might be bastardized
and I apologize, but something akin to,
when you take over a country or a county or what have you,
you have the choice to let them keep their arms
or to take away their arms.
But you can't let them keep their arms
and then later take away their arms.
And I think that when it comes to China
selling their value proposition to other countries,
those countries would have to be at brutal war
with each other for a very long time
and essentially lose all semblance of a stable democracy
before you would say yay to the kind of vulgar tyranny
of the Chinese Communist Party.
And so I think that the sale of their schtick
is a tougher sell.
And so if we have nothing else going for us in the States,
it would be that you can tweet what you want,
including about the man who purportedly runs the country
and you're gonna go to bed just fine.
Yeah, the fundamental American values,
there I say constitutional values, absolutely.
Dare you say, yeah, you're a Bible thumper, aren't you?
Must be, and white supremacists, I guess.
Anyway, but yes, I just think about them as,
in the OECD, I have a great,
I have a really warm and abiding respect
for the OECD as an organization.
I really recommend people interested in solidarity,
certainly in sort of the broad Western dynamic
versus the hardcore communism
to learn more about the OECD,
but they refer to it as like-minded nations, right?
It's not any one person's constitution.
It's just, can you say what you want
and nobody breaks your legs?
Can you pray to what you want and nobody breaks your legs?
Can you come together and congregate how you want
and nobody breaks your legs?
It's just basic stuff, it's just basic stuff.
So for me, it's not even constitutional,
it's just like-minded nations
where somewhat essential sort of freedoms,
as far back as Greece or we wanna tie to John Locke
or I don't really care who gets the credit,
just the kinds of freedoms that we enjoy, right?
So I can extrapolate it even beyond the constitution
if we wanted to.
Yeah, interesting.
Transparency is the key, definitely.
Are you at all confident and optimistic
about decentralization on the basis of blockchain
to reach some of these goals?
I don't know enough about blockchain
to have a square opinion there.
What I will tell you is this,
there appears to be very little blockchain
tinkering its way into the actual enterprise right now.
Now, the same could be said of AI,
but AI is much farther along in let's say big banks,
big media companies, e-commerce, manufacturing.
Artificial intelligence is eking its way in in the corners.
I'm not saying it's easy and at a fun time,
but it's making a difference.
It's clearly going to be transformative.
Blockchain, I don't think that the use cases
are so nascent that I really don't have firm opinions.
When I look at the intersection of blockchain and AI,
which I have done some research on,
it's nascent to the point
where I literally don't care about it yet.
I mean, didn't you talk about that with Ben Gertzell?
Because Ben Gertzell's Singularity Net is-
And I have a tremendous respect for Gertzell, by the way.
I mean, I consider Gertzell, in my personal opinion,
he's one of probably four living intellectuals
who I would say have really influenced my thought
and who I consider to be toweringly intelligent.
And so I have a great respect for Gertzell.
But yeah, I mean, and I hope his firm succeeds.
I'm rooting for him.
I'm rooting for Singularity Net.
It still seems to me to be a great many different ideas
that they're exploring in terms of what the business model
will be and how it's going to work out.
And if anybody can do it, hopefully it's him.
But I think-
Yeah, what can lead to AGI?
That's the thing, because we don't really know
what can lead to AGI at this point.
That's exactly it.
Yeah, we don't have a clue yet.
So Ben's got some theories, though,
and he's got more informed theories than me.
He's been thinking about it since I was five years old.
Fascinating, fascinating individual.
We talked about having an hour long conversation,
so I don't wanna leak.
Yeah, you have a two o'clock, unfortunately.
Okay.
I'm gonna blast with you.
It's been a real fun day.
Yeah, man.
Dan's website is emerge.com.
Go there and find all the other information.
Let me ask you the last question I ask all my guests.
That if you come across an intelligent alien
from a different civilization,
what would you say is the worst thing humanity has done?
And what would you say is our greatest achievement?
Good gracious, brother.
I have no idea.
What is the worst thing we've done?
Well, I mean, tribal and religious wars seem pretty rough.
That's a very big umbrella.
I apologize for the vagary there.
And in terms of the best things that we've done,
I think it's determined ways to both govern ourselves
and progress forward in terms of our potential
at the same time with reasonable periods of peace.
I think that that's a worthy,
it's a laudable achievement for hairless apes like ourselves.
And I think we can deserve a pat on the back for that one.
I think that's a worthy achievement for hairless apes like ourselves.