In the Greek traditions, philosophy, science and religion were not different.
Plato is talking about all these things, Aristotle and Pythagoras, they were exploring the mysteries
and so I actually think the goal of religion, the goal of philosophy and the goal of science
is the same which is to try to understand the nature of the reality that we live in
and I actually think that most religions are founded when somebody peeks outside the simulation
as I like to call it, they peek outside the game and then they come back and they try
to describe what they saw which is very difficult to do because the base reality as it's called
may be very different than what we're used to here, so the laws of physics really could
be just the physics engine of our specific game.
Rizwan Virk, welcome to the 86th episode of the New Human Podcast.
Thanks for having me on your podcast.
It's a pleasure.
How are you doing in California with the pandemic and this crazy world that we're living in
right now?
Well, things were actually pretty calm where I am, California obviously has its set of
problems always related to wildfires especially today, we've got all kinds of haze from
fires all over the Bay Area but it just started yesterday, there was a little bit of lightning
and I guess they'd set some places on fire but other than that, I actually live right
down the road from Google and it's actually been quite calm because their 40,000 employees
have been staying at home so this area as I said hasn't been too crazy.
Let's start with your background, the work you've done, the lives you've lived and what
are you mainly focused on now these days?
Sure, so I got my degree in computer science many years ago from MIT and became an entrepreneur
in the software industry, started off doing a bunch of enterprise software, kind of boring
stuff for some people, big IT departments used our product, thousands of them and then
after selling my last enterprise software company almost 10 years ago, I moved out to
Silicon Valley and got involved with video games and that was around the time that Facebook
had released games on its platform and also the iPhone had come out in 2007 and in 2008,
they introduced the App Store and so I got heavily, heavily involved in kind of this
nascent industry which was mobile gaming with a company called TapJoy which became one of
the biggest advertising companies in mobile and we made a game called TapFish which is
one of the top games in the early days of the App Store.
We ended up selling that to a big Japanese company and then I became more of an investor
and mentor and advisor to different startups and then a few years ago, I went back to MIT
and started PlayLabs which is a startup accelerator for playful technologies and also decided
to focus a little more on my writing and so I came out with the book The Simulation Hypothesis
last year on the 20th anniversary of the release of The Matrix which was March 31st, 1999 and
my book was released on March 31st, 2019 last year and so now I'm involved in a combination
of kind of futuristic types of activities around virtual reality.
Also I'm an investor still in many different startups, I'm writing new books and kind
of parallel with my journey in the software world, I was an explorer of many states of
consciousness whether it was meditation, Tibetan dream yoga, lots of other practices and so
I became interested in consciousness and how it interacts with the physical world and so
the book The Simulation Hypothesis was a way of tying all of that together really for me
for areas that I've investigated over many, many years.
That's awesome and it really is this combination of consciousness and simulation hypothesis
that you're talking about that interested me initially about I thought I need to talk
to him and you also have a new book called Startup Myth and Models What You Won't Learn
in Business School, I want to talk to you about that a little bit later but let's start
with The Simulation Hypothesis and MIT computer scientist shows why AI, quantum physics and
eastern mystics all agree we are in a video game.
Can you describe the thesis of the book and what interested you beside Matrix to write
the book at the first place?
Yeah, well you know a few years ago I was heavily involved in virtual reality startups
and so I was actually visiting one of them and they had a VR ping pong game that was
going to be released by HTC who are makers of the Vive headset which was one of the big
headsets along with Oculus when virtual reality was sort of making a comeback and so as I
was playing this ping pong game, I found that it was so realistic in terms of the responsiveness
that I forgot I was in a virtual reality.
So much so that at the end of the game I decided to put the paddle down on the table and lean
against the table.
Of course there was no table, I was just in a room with these goggles on and so the controller
fell to the floor and I almost fell over.
And how long did it take from the time that you start playing the game to being convinced
that you're basically in that environment?
It didn't take very long.
I mean these were relatively short games so it was less than 10 minutes total that I was
playing and what's interesting about that is that it wasn't even the resolution.
So when we talk about the Matrix, we think of super high resolution virtual worlds which
look just like the physical world and we'll talk about how we get there.
But in this case, the resolution graphics were not that realistic.
It was more the physics engine.
It was the way that I heard the sound of the ball just when I was about to tap it and depending
on where I tapped it, it went and it reacted based upon how I hit it.
And so really the responsiveness was actually the key to this immersion more so than what
we think of which is the pixel resolution.
Turns out that we have pretty good pixel resolution already and most movies you see when we had
cinemas open like Star Wars or Blade Runner 2049, they're digital these days and they
get sent at a 2K pixel resolution.
Well it turns out we have 4K resolution screens and 8K on the way and so we're getting very
good at getting the pixel resolution but it was really that responsiveness.
So I started to think, well what would it take for technology to develop to what I call
the simulation point which is the point at which we can produce simulations that are
so realistic that we would not be able to distinguish those from physical reality, completely
immersive like the Matrix really.
And so that was how I started writing the book but then as I started to investigate
this idea, I realized that it was being taken seriously now whereas 20 years ago when The
Matrix came out, it was considered science fiction and before that, the works of Philip
K. Dick were very inspirational to the makers of The Matrix but also in providing a framework
in science fiction to talk about the idea that what you're seeing might not be real,
that there may be invented worlds or false memories for example.
And so that led to the writing of the rest of the book and part of the book really delves
into the idea that this isn't a new idea, that all the world religions have been talking
about this for some period of time and so I was able to kind of tie that together as
well.
Very interesting.
I'm glad that you mentioned the effect of sound because I'm coming from the background
of sound design and I've been working on this, making the shift from the 2D kind of
an environment into VR and AR kind of an environment and there's a huge difference between how
those sounds for example or visuals are being produced.
There's a big difference between stereo sounds and binaural sounds that you feel like
you're in the environment and as you're saying, if you close your eyes, it takes a
matter of seconds for you to feel like, yeah, I'm walking in New York City.
Right and with the sounds, this idea of 3D sound for people that aren't familiar with
it, it's the idea that if sound is coming from over there, that corner of the room,
it will hit my ear slightly differently, my right ear and my left ear versus something
that's right in front of me or something that's right behind me and so trying to
simulate that digitally by knowing the X, Y, Z coordinates which is actually a lot of
what we do in virtual reality visuals.
If you go back to the 1980s when I started writing video games, my first game was a tic
tac toe program on the Commodore 64 and then on Apple II computers.
Back then if you asked somebody, can you make a fully immersive 3D world like World of Warcraft
which it's not fully immersive, it's not even virtual reality but it's a 3D world
that you play on your computer and the answer would be no, there are just too many pixels.
There's no way we could render all of that and keep track of all of that and so what
happened between then and now, well, Moore's Law happened which states that the computing
power doubles every 18 months but more than that, we came up with optimization techniques.
We came up with ways to compress the data and so the rule of thumb was look at your
point of view inside the virtual world, inside the 3D world and render only those pixels
which can be observed by your avatar and so anything that cannot be observed, you don't
have to render.
That was a key optimization technique that allowed for 3D graphics with games like Doom
back in the 90s which was so popular that it was bringing college networks down because
it was a first person shooter and when you turn left or right, it looked like the world
moved with you and if you look at like really old versions of this, Microsoft Flight Simulator
which was supposed to simulate flying an airplane back in the 80s or 90s when they first came
out with it, you could see the lines being rendered across the screen every time you
move so you turn to the left and you would wait for it to render the scene.
Today, they have a version of Flight Simulator in beta that is based on Bing maps and they
took all the maps of the physical world that they could, satellite images and they created
using AI 3D models of like a billion buildings so you could literally fly over New York City
and look down and have it look like the buildings in New York City and so it's pretty impressive
what's happened and a lot of this was because of 3D rendering techniques, that's kind
of how we got to where we're able to do it.
It's very similar now with 3D sound, there's a lot of work being done on how to reproduce
that digitally without having to worry so much about where the physical sound is and
then you add that to the goggles, now you're in a very immersive type of world.
This advancement depends on the computational processing power, right?
So we're based on silicon right now but my understanding is that we are reaching the
limits of silicon and we have to move to the next mode of computation.
How is that going to affect the future of simulating our world I guess?
Well, we do seem to be approaching a theoretical limit but what you find is that that was thought
to be the case before and so I remember when I was in business school at Stanford here
just down the road, we had a case study from Intel saying that if they had continued to
make processors the way that they were making them, you know what happens is the processors
get smaller and they do more computations and when they do more computations, it produces
more heat and so the engineers were doing a little analysis that said okay as the number
of computations increase, how will the heat increase and they said it was going to be
hotter than the sun if it keeps going after a few years.
Now what happened was they came up with different computational techniques and so optimization
was actually the key.
Turns out that was the normal like the 286-386 Pentium processor and that was the normal
track but there was a parallel group at Intel making processors for laptops which used a
lot less energy and produced a lot less heat and they used reduced instruction sets so
reduced number of computations so it's all about optimization and so I think we're not
quite at the theoretical limits and won't be for a while because people will come up
with new optimization techniques and adding other hardware like GPUs so graphics processing
units are pretty common now and they were invented primarily for video games and entertainment
like what do you need graphics for, right, it's to render these kinds of things.
Now if you look at virtual reality headsets, there was a wave back in the 90s where you
know they had to be hooked up to like very big machines and then in 2012 I think it was
Facebook bought Oculus for a couple of billion dollars and that was kind of the new resurgence
of virtual reality but one of the problems was you know just like with my headset here
which has this wire, you had to be connected to the computer with a wire because the computer
was doing the processing and so the difficulty with virtual reality is not so much displaying
it on a small screen which you know they have the two screens on your eyes, it's calculating
what should be rendered in real time so that when you turn to the left or you turn to the
right, it doesn't do what the old flight simulator would do and show you line by line
I'm re-rendering what it might look like but now you know we have the Oculus Quest
which came out last year and HTC has its own kind of version where you don't need a computer
and you don't need a phone, all the computation is done in the headset itself so we're already
seeing kind of standalone virtual reality which is showing that we'll be able to do
more and more computation.
That said, there is a lot of work being done on light so the reason we have fiber optics
is instead of transferring over copper wires, you basically use light to transmit bits of
data because in the end, our computation today is all based on bits, ones and zeros.
I know how we're talking right now, I'm not really talking to you, I'm actually seeing
bits that were transferred over the internet and they're being re-rendered on my side
and I'm being rendered on your side and one of us is doing the recording etc.
So there's some work being done there but I think really the next frontier for computing
that a lot of people are looking at is quantum computing and the basic idea there is that
instead of using regular bits, so a regular bit has a one or a zero value, you use quantum
bits or qubits which have both a value of one and zero, it's called quantum superposition
and this quantum superposition has been one of the biggest mysteries in the world of quantum
mechanics and I talk a lot about it in the book in general but as we apply it to computation,
what it means is that just like the old story of Schrodinger's cat where Schrodinger came
up with this analogy because he thought it was just ridiculous what quantum physics was
saying, unfortunately it's been verified, that's what it's saying which is that if
you have a cat in a box and it has some radioactive material, that after an hour, the cat has
a 50% chance of being alive and a 50% chance of being dead.
Now to us it seems logical that the cat is either alive or it's dead, we just don't
know which one, it can't be both, it's just one or the other.
What quantum physics tells us is that it is both alive and dead until somebody opens up
the box and makes a measurement or an observation of what's inside the box and so it exists
in this weird state of probabilistic reality and it turns out quantum computers are going
to try to use that to say you have a qubit and suppose you have 50 qubits, each of them
can be zero or one, well that's a pretty big number, it's two to the power 50 that
you can do whereas right now we have 32-bit or 64-bit processors on our computers but
with that you basically can do one measurement across all of them and so it makes it a lot
faster and now it's kind of confusing how it works but the basic idea is you have it
explore all the possible values.
So if you were to explore all the possible values of 64-bits, you would have to go through
two of the 64 iterations but with a quantum computer, you kind of let that run in this
probabilistic world and as you make a measurement, you collapse the probability wave just like
looking at Schrodinger's gap to see if it's alive or dead and so the idea is that that
would result in much faster computers.
Now there's some debate over whether quantum computers are really faster or you can optimize
classical computers to do the same thing and so I think IBM was able to get up to a certain
number of qubits now but it's still early days, it's kind of like 1980 for personal
computers when it comes to qubits or even earlier like 1960s when most computers were
mainframes so most quantum computers are like these giant things that sit in these super
cooled labs using superconductors.
The really hard thing about quantum computers is error detection and turns out this is another
basic optimization technique or algorithmic technique we use in software which is how
do you correct errors if you have millions of bits, if 10 of them are wrong.
Right now, same thing with your picture coming to me, what happens if a couple of those bits
gets transmitted wrongly?
Well we can figure out using error correction techniques, my hair should be this color,
my shirt is black, therefore that's probably should be black, it shouldn't be necessarily
a bunch of white bits there and so we use checksums and things like that and so that's
really where a lot of work has to be done still as well as the physical storage of these
qubits is still pretty hard because you have to do it at these very cold temperatures.
Is IBM the leader?
Because I know there's one company in Canada, D-Wave, that they've been right on top of
it for many, many years and they sold I think their machines to Google, that army company
McDonald something and so I'm interested to know who is the leader at this point in
quantum computing.
Well, so D-Wave was one of the earliest companies, maybe the first one to come out with a quantum
computer.
There's some debate over whether it's a true quantum computer or not and we won't
dig into that but they're out there, Google has a pretty big quantum computing department.
Microsoft actually is spending a lot of money on this as well and in fact, they're all
using slightly different approaches to the physical storage of these qubits.
It's kind of as if back in the day when Apple was making a personal computer, IBM
was making one, Commodore was making one, instead of all using silicon chips, one was
using Swiss cheese and one was using copper and one was using silicon.
That's kind of the stage we're at is they're still experimenting with what is the best
way to physically store these bits and I think Microsoft had a breakthrough where they were
able to do it at normal temperatures which is pretty important if quantum computing is
going to get out there more, you can't require this kind of negative 200 degrees Celsius
or whatever the temperature is to store these things.
All the big guys are actually running after it right now and then there's a lot of startups
that are working in this space more on the software side trying to come up with different
algorithms.
There's a lot of research, IBM put out a paper I think last year stating that there
in fact were some algorithms where there was quantum supremacy which is to prove that a
quantum computer can do this way faster than a classical computer.
It's not as easy as it sounds because even though theoretically it can be done, the way
you have to go in and measure these bits and collapse that probability wave is kind of
tricky even for a traditional programmer like I was trained as a traditional programmer,
you have to think almost very differently to make that transition into quantum programming.
Is the role of the programmer will become obsolete when we move to quantum computation
because of all the possibilities that exist that we inevitably have to rely on some kind
of AI or AGI ultimately?
Well I don't think it will become obsolete, I think it will change from the way we think
about it today.
Today we're writing procedural software or object-oriented software and already within
the coding world, let's see when was the basic programming language was invented?
I was probably back in the 70s or 60s so it's been about 50 years that we've had programming
and we're now getting to the no code stage which is a popular term in programming which
is for somebody who doesn't have to write any code, you just drag and drop things but
people have been talking about that for many years, I remember Steve Jobs making a big
deal of this when he left Apple and he created an X computer back in the 90s that you could
just take these objects and put them together.
Well it turns out it wasn't that simple, you still needed to do lots of actual code
writing and so today there's a big trend towards no code solutions but it's still
not there, we still have to write a lot of code so I think with quantum computing it
will be different, if you go to IBM's website, there's actually a way where you can upload
a program, a quantum computing program up to their computer and have it run on a time
shared basis.
So it's kind of like mainframe computers used to be like back in the days when Bill
Gates and Paul Allen before they started Microsoft in Seattle or at Harvard, they were working
on these mainframe computers and they would only get them for a certain period of time
and they would submit their programs and wait for them to run and get back the results.
So it's kind of in that world but there's visual representations of these bits, there
are languages like Qsharp which Microsoft is coming out with but I'd say it's still
a wide open area, I don't think the way that we do quantum programming today will be the
way we do it tomorrow so there will probably be some transition, I don't think right
away that AGI is going to be able to do computer programming but we're not even at AGI so
there's a big debate about whether we think we'll get there soon.
Now we're getting closer and closer, there are these text generation modules that didn't
quite pass the Turing test yet and your viewers may know about the Turing test which was put
forward by Alan Turing back in the 1950s I think when he said he called it the imitation
game and he said if you had a computer behind one curtain and a human behind another and
you're talking with them, back then he was saying you're sending teletype messages,
that's how they did that.
Today it might be an actual voice conversation or it might be a chat bot but if you can't
tell the difference between the computer and the human then that computer has passed the
imitation game and then you're at the point where it's AI, it's intelligent enough
because you can't really tell the difference between one or the other.
So we're not quite there yet, estimates range from a decade to several decades, most people
think we'll certainly get there within the century, I'm not so sure personally, the argument
is if you can't tell the difference between a machine and a human then we have basically
simulated consciousness.
So this is a big debate that says what is consciousness?
Wow, that is a huge point, yes.
So is a machine that acts like a conscious person actually conscious or not and if we
can't tell the difference, does it even matter?
And so this gets into the debate of can we take human consciousness and download it into
a computer.
So I talked about in this book the road to the simulation point, there are these 10 stages
and one of the stages is artificial intelligence bots that we can talk to but another stage
is this idea of being able to download your consciousness into a computer.
It's a very popular topic in Silicon Valley and people like Ray Kurzweil who I think his
official title is Chief Futurist at Google has been talking about this as a way of achieving
digital immortality but it's not something that we don't fully understand consciousness
so the question is can we really reproduce it and is it really you if you reproduce your
bits and this is where we overlap with philosophy and religion.
A lot of guys who talk about the simulation hypothesis, they don't like to talk about
religion, they'll talk about philosophy, they'll take it that far but they won't
take it but if you think particularly in the Eastern religions, you don't even have to
draw an analogy, they basically say that you have a soul or something that exists outside,
you download into your avatar which is our biological avatars in this case and then at
the end of the life, you upload back to wherever it was and there's some information from
this lifetime that is stored and then you go to the next lifetime, you're playing
the next avatar so you have this kind of upload and download of consciousness.
They don't even define what that is and there's actually one of the interesting differences
between say Hinduism and Buddhism is within Hinduism, you have more of an indestructible
soul which is a term we're more familiar with in the West because the Western religions
also have this idea of a soul that exists in eternity after you die somewhere else but
in the Buddhist traditions, particularly what some Buddhist scholars say is that it's more
like a bag of karma.
The only thing that gets uploaded and downloaded is the information about what happened to
you in that life and previous lives and in Silicon Valley, we would say that's just
storing stuff to the cloud, it's just a bag of information that gets stored somewhere
out of sight that is not part of the rendered game world as we call it in the video game
world.
But yeah, we're touching on very big issues when you get to that point.
Well, it seems like it's inevitable to talk about religions and philosophy and we're
reaching a point that everything is kind of coming together and we have to address all
of them and get any kind of information, any kind of a tool we can from wherever to make
sense out of basically what we are doing.
That's part of my point in this book and one of the criticisms I often get is why did
you dedicate a third of the book to talking about consciousness and religion and unexplained
phenomena when you should just talk about the computer science and the physics.
For me, it was actually important to realize that as you go back, humans have been searching
for the truth about reality for a very long time and you go back to the Greeks and Plato
had his analogy of the cave which is very popular in philosophy which is the idea that
if we all live in a cave chained to one side and there's an opening but we can't really
look out into the real world, all we see are shadows against the wall and what happens
when somebody goes outside and peeks to see what's out there.
Well, first he gets blinded by the light because he's lived in a cave his whole life but then
when he comes back and tries to explain it to the other people, nobody believes him because
they think reality is just these shadows that you're seeing on the wall and within I think
the Greek traditions, philosophy, science and religion were not different.
Plato's talking about all these things, Aristotle and Pythagoras, they were exploring
the mysteries and so I actually think the goal of religion, the goal of philosophy and
the goal of science is the same which is to try to understand the nature of the reality
that we live in and I actually think that most religions are founded when somebody peeks
outside the simulation as I like to call it, they peek outside the game and then they come
back and they try to describe what they saw which is very difficult to do because the
base reality as it's called may be very different than what we're used to here.
The laws of physics really could be just the physics engine of our specific game as opposed
to being the same out there so it's very difficult to talk about what base reality
is like and that is what creates the three blind men and the elephant phenomenon I like
to say with religion where each one saw a different part of the elephant, they're
actually seeing the same thing but they like to come back and tell it so that one says
it's more like a tree, one says it's more like a house, one says it's more like a snake
because of the trunk of the elephant and that's a phenomenon that we see in our religions.
I think it's very profound what you're saying that even the laws of physics could be just
limited to our experience which I keep telling people, I call them involuntary baggage that
you identify with your culture and your religion and what your parents have told you, what
your society have put upon your shoulder but really the point is to look at the definition
of who the I is, who are you beyond all of those things because these are the things
that they have defined you on that basis, it's not you.
I think for a lot of younger people, this idea of the video game is a great way to think
about that question because if you were an avatar in Fortnite, who does that avatar think
he or she is?
What are the laws of physics in that game?
You can fly, you can do this, you can do that but you don't really have to go get a car
to go places so there's a set of laws and so that becomes in this model another set
of baggage but by having this idea of saying that there's a player and a player character,
it becomes a new way to think about it and within the world of the simulation hypothesis
and simulation theory, there's actually two different versions of this hypothesis and
I like to call it the NPC version and the RPG version and the NPC version stands for
non-player character or non-playable characters which is the term used in video games for
a character that is just an AI that you just interact with inside the game so you might
have like the tavern barkeep or the owner of a bank where you're giving some information
and so NPCs have gotten more and more sophisticated visually with games over time but if you go
all the way back to the text adventure games, there might be very limited characters, there's
characters you can ask very limited things to and they have a limited dialogue and even
nowadays a lot of the dialogue is you still have to just click on choose A or B. If you
go to like the Game of Thrones or Walking Dead games from Telltale, the guy will say
this and you have to choose your response A or B so it's still pretty basic but in
the NPC version, we're all NPCs and we're all running on somebody else's computer
and therefore the world around us is the only world we know.
In the RPG version, it's more like what we think of as video games where we have a player
and we have an avatar inside the game and we are so associated with that avatar like
in The Matrix, we forget that there's a part of us outside the world.
Now those two are not mutually exclusive like when you go into video games today like MMORPGs,
you have both, you have PCs, player characters and NPCs interacting and so it's very possible
that you have a combination of the two but for me, both of these versions creates this
interesting question of what is consciousness.
In the NPC version, consciousness is just what the NPC thinks they're doing whereas
in the RPG version, consciousness exists outside of the simulation.
You still don't know what it is but it's something different.
It's observing what's happening within the game and watching the gameplay.
I think one of the disconnects for a lot of people about the simulation hypothesis or
theory and however they want to talk about it is that, well, who's running the simulation
and the idea is that nobody really needs to run it.
If you look at, I'm reading from Wikipedia also showing it to our viewers, The Game of
Life by John Conway that it's a zero player game meaning that its evolution is determined
by its initial state requiring no further input.
All you have to do is start basically and it evolves in the way that it's supposed
to evolve and it's completely based on trial and error and chaos and uncertainty and momentary
orders out of them.
Right, and then it evolves based on a certain set of rules and in that case, they tend to
be very deterministic rules but it's a big question who runs the simulation and why.
Your question of do you really need somebody to run it or do you really need our set of
initial conditions and a way to get going.
One of the ways to think about it is why do we run simulations?
We run simulations sometimes to predict the weather or to predict stock forecasts or the
basic idea of a simulation is you have like populations of fruit flies.
Every year, you look at it and you say how many fruit flies have died and how many were
born in the next generation and that's a very non-graphical simulation, it's just
a numerical one but that's one reason.
The other reason though is we play video games, why?
We play video games to have experiences that we can't have outside the game.
I can't fly on a dragon in quote unquote real life but I can inside a video game so
I can have these experiences that I might not be able to have otherwise.
If you think of an MMORPG, a massively multiplayer online role playing game where you have lots
of individual people playing the game like Fortnite or World of Warcraft or one of these
other ones, you have millions of people, there was a concert in Fortnite last year that had
like 12 million people attending it.
It's like the largest concert ever and so it's possible that we are playing the game
for our own reasons to have experiences with each other or it's possible that we were
all just running on a computer somewhere and there's a set of deterministic rules and
those tie right into that dichotomy of the NPC version or the RPG version that I talked
about earlier.
That's amazing.
That's also how I like to think about the concept of God, quote unquote God, that there
is one thing whether conscious and it's an endless stream that has always been and always
will be and we are having our subjective experiences of it and the collection, decentralized collection
of that is what I can think of as the concept God or being higher power or whatever which
is unknowable and that's the nature of it.
We're just experiencing our own part of it.
Right.
So that's an interesting way to think about it.
Within the kind of Judeo-Christian line, you have this idea in the Bible that God created
the world in seven days and said let there be light and then basically gave humans free
will to decide what they were going to do and that there are entities outside the physical
world watching us and in the Islamic traditions, they get very specific about this.
There's names for the recording angels and in Washington DC, there's a statue of a recording
angel with what they call the Book of Life in the Bible and in the Quran, they talk about
the scroll of deeds which is a list of every single action you've done in your life and
so I like to draw the analogy that well, this was all revealed, written depending on your
beliefs a couple of thousand years ago and if it was done today, we wouldn't use a
metaphor of the book and writing down.
How would we describe a situation where there are entities watching every move we make and
then they replay it for us at the end of our life where we have to go back and review everything
that was done?
Well, we do it all the time in video games.
We record everything in the 3D world so that it can be replayed and we stream it on Twitch
and we put it up on YouTube and so I was involved in a video game company a couple of years
ago where we took a 3D game called League of Legends which is very popular in the e-sports
world and you play the game on your computer and you have an avatar and you're fighting
and you're doing all these fun things and they recorded it but then they let you replay
it by putting on a virtual reality headset and if you had shot someone, you could actually
replay it from their point of view so you could see the gameplay from any XYZ coordinate
but most interesting was to put the coordinates at other players.
Well it turns out as you explore this world of consciousness and you explore what people
have been talking about in the religious traditions but more recently in near-death experiences
and there have been thousands and thousands of cases of near-death experiences since Raymond
Moody coined the term back in the 70s and they're remarkably similar and many of them
have about some percentage have this thing called a panoramic life review which is basically
they recall seeing everything that happened in their lives but seeing it from the point
of view of the other people they affected and so there's a friend of mine named Daniel
Brinkley, he wrote a book called Saved by the Light and he was basically struck by lightning
and had a near-death experience back in the 70s and he's had several since then when
he was doing heart surgery etc.
But he said he used to be a bully and he used to literally beat people up in school and
then he joined the army and special forces and was literally shooting people.
He had to go through and relive those experiences from the point of view of the other person.
If you think about how could that work and that's kind of how I like to think about
things being a computer programmer is how would that work?
Well, it wouldn't be that hard if it was a simulation.
If it wasn't a simulation, nobody would know how it could be done but if this world
was being recorded and you could replay back any time slice at any time at any speed from
any position, then that's where the simulation hypothesis intersects very much with what
a lot of the religions have been saying and with this idea of angels being these other
entities that are watching us and then God being the creator of the simulation however
you would define it.
So there's a lot of different ways to think about that concept I think.
I think this is a good place to read a tweet by Scott Adams, the creator of Dilbert said
the closer a civilization gets to being able to program a simulated universe, the closer
it gets to discovering it is one.
Right.
Well, he's a big proponent of the simulation hypothesis and there was an Oxford professor
named Nick Bostrom who wrote a paper in 2003 called Are You Living in a Computer Simulation?
He's probably the person most responsible for getting this to go from science fiction
to academics talking about it more seriously.
He's a philosopher and what he said was if any civilization ever gets there, he said
first of all there are three possibilities.
Civilization never gets to what I call the simulation point where you can create those
simulations.
Two, it gets there but it decides not to create these ultra realistic simulations or three,
it creates these simulations but it creates lots of them and so he said if any civilization
in the galaxy ever gets there, they're going to create lots and lots of simulations because
all you have to do is crank up another server in the cloud and he estimated that the number
of beings that would be in the simulated universes would be way more than the number of beings
in the physical universe and therefore if you're a being, then what are you more likely,
a simulated being or a physical being?
Well, there's more of these than those so simple statistics says you're more likely
one of these than one of those and so the idea was if anybody can ever get there, then
somebody has already gotten there and if somebody has already gotten there, who's to say we're
not inside the simulation already and so that is referred to as the simulation argument.
So when I started writing my book, I was exploring the technology, we would need to get there
and my conclusion was we'll get there within a hundred years maybe, definitely and so if
we're going to get there in a hundred years, that's not very long in the overall scale
of the universe assuming it was a physical universe so probably a civilization that was
a million years ahead of us so think of where video games would be in a million years and
this is a point that Elon Musk makes is that if you assume any rate of improvement at all
with video games and you look at today's games, it's funny because I use ping pong
as my example that got me really thinking about this but he makes the point that pong
was the first widely available computer game in the 70s which was just like two squares
and a dot moving back and forth and it was from Atari, it was the first widely available
video game and you look at where we've come in 50 years, we're at these ultra realistic
virtual worlds like even with this new version of flight simulator I was talking about and
give it another 50 years where will we be but give it 10,000 years suppose it goes more
slowly than that, we'll definitely get there and so if we're going to get there, who's
to say we aren't already there inside the simulation ourselves.
Absolutely, so your time frame is 100 years and you said there are 10 steps to get to
the point of indistinguishable simulation, you mentioned AI, what number of step would
that be?
Well, it depends on where the AI is but in my model, it's one of the later steps because
I think getting to AGI will take us a little while so it's like step nine, eight or nine.
Before that, we're currently at sort of step four where we have augmented reality and virtual
reality.
Now, the difference between those two with augmented reality is you wear glasses and
you see objects around you placed in the physical world that aren't really there and there's
a great depiction of this in the HBO show Westworld in the second season where they
would put on these little glasses and then somebody will appear who's not really there
and you can talk to them.
Then the next step is kind of photorealistic AR, VR without headsets.
If you think of like in Star Wars in the prequels when Anakin Skywalker is talking to Master
Yoda who's on another planet, he sees a little hologram or Princess Leia hologram.
The ability to create these holograms and have them be realistic without the need to
put on glasses means that we're starting to blur the lines of distinction between what
is a physicality.
We're already at the point of hologram though with, do you know Hatsune Miku, the virtual
Japanese pop singer?
Yes, that's right.
I have heard of some of them.
You had the Tupac, was it the Tupac hologram as well?
Right.
So Hatsune Miku, entirely virtual.
Her band are all human but even her voice is virtually generated and we went to see
her show in Toronto and people are interacting with it as if it's a real artist and they
are very happy to be there.
They have the very same experience and we were given glow sticks that was programmed
with the light.
It's just insane.
Right.
So this will just become more mainstream, you were saying.
Yeah, become more mainstream and the technology is miniaturized where you can do that.
You can take it with you if you will, right?
But yeah, we're on that path.
Each of these stages isn't like a single, hey, we're there or we're not there.
It's more like each of them has a certain percentage of completion if you will to get
to that point and with 3D printers are kind of part of that same idea which is that we
can take pretty much any physical object now.
You could take this water bottle and you can print it using pixels and the only thing that's
different is that we don't have all of the materials yet to be able to use pixels but
it used to be every 3D printed object was this kind of gray plastic epoxy and now you
can start to do it with metal and with living human tissue.
I mean they've actually taken blood cells and created skin like what happened with skin
that was grafted on before was it wouldn't interface with the rest of your skin because
it wasn't really alive in the same way that your skin is alive because it has blood cells
in there and so they were able to print skin at least in the lab and graft it on and have
the rest of the body think it was just like a regular skin with the same kind of blood
cells using that person's own cells and printing up the skin and so you're getting biological
3D printers.
Now, they're still in the early stages but once you can do printing of different materials,
there's a pretty common scene in the old Star Trek The Next Generation where Captain
Picard goes into the replicator and says, Tea, Earl Grey, hot and it not only
materializes the cup but it materializes the Earl Grey liquid inside and then he takes
that and he starts drinking it and so that's kind of an advanced 3D printer that can print
food as well as physical objects.
We're not that far away from that.
So what we don't have is these brain-computer interfaces and so that's like stage 7 before
getting to AI and then downloadable consciousness and so brain-computer interface, if you remember
the Matrix, Neo thought he was immersed because when he woke up, Keanu Reeves' character
outside the Matrix, he had a wire going into the back of his head into his Neo cortex and
so that's actually an area that's pretty popular these days.
Elon Musk has a company called Neuralink which is putting some chips in the head and there
are other groups that have done research where these chips can be used to help with deficiency
or if someone is paralyzed but BCIs are still in the early stages and much of them are non-invasive.
What they do is they just measure the EEG signals coming out of the brain and they use
those brain waves along with other cues like muscle impulses.
There's a company that I wrote about recently, an article about BCI where they want to speed
up your ability to play video games and so from the time it takes you to say I want to
shoot this person to pressing the button on the controller, it takes a couple hundred
milliseconds and so they detect the electrical impulse in the muscles and they go and they
do it in the game much faster than you could on your own and so there's a lot of tricks
like that that are being used today in BCI.
I actually think this is where this idea of what is the mind, what is the brain, what
is consciousness really comes up.
There's actually been some experiments done at Pair, the Princeton's Engineering Anomalies
Research Institute where they showed they were using quantum random number generators
and the idea is that over time, they should be 50-50 if it was just doing ones and zeros
or coin toss right after a thousand tries or 10,000 tries and they found that a human
could influence those quantum random number generators based upon what they were thinking.
That's a form of observation, right?
It's a form of observation or measurement, better to say.
Measurement but they found that if a person sat there with an intention, it would actually
change.
The measurement didn't happen necessarily until later so there's the measurement side
of it but leaving that aside for a second, they found that when they measured it, depending
on what the person was thinking, that it would go from 50-50 to like 40-60 which is actually
a pretty big variance when you get to 10,000 tries.
When you're doing 10 tries, that's not a big deal at all but when you flip a coin that
many times, it shouldn't vary that much and they had Pair published peer-reviewed research
in that and there was a company, they made something called a mind lamp where you can
actually think of a color that they're using quantum random number generators.
Now that's a way to try to get that brain-computer interface without actually physically tapping
into the physical brain.
I was talking to somebody the other day and they said, well, that would be a mind-computer
interface as opposed to a brain-computer interface so that's all part of this big stage and
I think to get fully immersive, we would have to be able to beam signals into the brain
and then take signals out of the brain and then there's AI which would be realistic
characters and then there's this idea of downloading consciousness which is kind of
wrapping up our whole consciousness within that and then we get to the simulation point
and so when I laid these stages of technology out there, I thought about my other research
into the realm of consciousness and realized, well, we already have all of these stages
of technology in biological form and we do it every night, they're called dreams.
We have these simulated worlds, we're completely immersed in them, we're forgetting that
there's a part of us outside of that world that is kind of like Neo laying there.
We take our input from our mind and the world changes based on that input.
We get things sent to us in very high resolution, it's fully immersive.
So what we're really learning to do is reproduce this biological technology that already exists.
So I thought that was kind of an interesting realization when I looked at the technology
but yeah, back to your original point, I think a hundred years or so is roughly the time
frame.
Some people think it will be much earlier.
I think that the AGI in particular part will prove more difficult than people think.
Hey, speaking of already existed biological technology, did you look into the effect or
influence of psychedelics in the context of simulation hypothesis?
A lot of people have brought that up to me to say that this is a great way for people
to explore it.
I haven't personally explored it but there have been people that have written about it.
There's a couple of things online about it.
I remember I was sitting down with director Oliver Stone with his son, Sean Stone, who
is a documentary filmmaker and he goes, Oh yeah, all you have to do is try some of these
psychedelics and you'll realize that this is all just a simulation.
Smoke DMT.
Yeah, DMT, exactly, ayahuasca and you'll see you don't need any further proof than that.
So I haven't experimented with that but I have heard a lot of people tell me that the
experiences they've had there seem like you get into these other levels of reality and
so there's obviously a lot of debate about these things in the scientific community.
What's really going on?
Same debate as with near-death experiences, what's really going on?
Is it just the oxygen in the brain, seeing something that looks like a light but there's
lots of counter-arguments there.
So I actually put some stock that this is something that shamans have done for a long
time in many traditions and they have what they call non-ordinary reality that they visit
with the use of psychotropic plants or power plants as they're called.
In some cases, what I have experimented with is simple shamanic journeying using drumming.
What happens is you use a rhythmic beat and meanwhile your breathing stabilizes and you
can kind of visit these other worlds which is the technique that shamans have been using
for a long time.
What's really interesting, getting back to this idea of dreams, you might say well
these are just individual hallucinations is you can have group shamanic journeys so you
can have multiple people go and see things and report back and you can see commonalities
between what different people saw which leads you to believe that there is a reality to
this non-ordinary reality.
So are there other levels of this reality out there which is perhaps similar to what
people might experience although much more intensely I think with DMT?
My first experience with NNDMT, not the 5-Emeo that comes from the Toad, but NNDMT, I saw
massive pyramids and Aztec kind of symbology.
The days later I was like these people probably had the similar kind of experience that you
see similar kind of shape buildings from Australia to Egypt to Peru and Mexico and we're not
even talking about any of them, you're all aliens.
Right, that's true.
There's a lot of alien phenomena theorizing particularly on the history channel about
these things but I do believe that a lot of ancient civilizations had much better understanding
of consciousness and that might have led to different states of consciousness.
My girlfriend and I visited the pyramids many years ago and when I was there, I remember
having these visions that included things like out-of-body experiences in places like
the pyramids and it kind of led me to believe that there's something going on here that
I was either remembering that was related to research that I had done later after that
on out-of-body experiences and lucid dreaming and what happens when you're dreaming.
That's why I find dreaming to be such a fascinating subject.
It's probably one of the oldest subjects for people to write about and going back to
the Bible because it's so universal but it's also so complicated.
I mean I've talked about shamanic journeying, I used to study that with a gentleman named
Robert Moss who is an Australian who studied with Aborigines and learned about their ideas
of the dream time and how there's a dream reality and then there's this reality and
what is the real reality and so this metaphor of the dream was used within Buddhism and
other places and I studied a little bit of Tibetan dream yoga and the idea was if you
can wake up within a dream using lucid dreaming techniques and they have other techniques
beyond what we would call lucid dreaming which is the more modern way of talking about it
but if you can wake up and know that it's a dream and know that there's a part of you
outside the dream, then they use that as a wrench if you will or a lever to kind of get
you to realize the illusory form of the waking reality that there is another part of you
that's outside of that and so that's why I spend a whole chapter talking about dreams
not just as a metaphor which is very much how it's used that life is like a dream
or the play, in the Hindu traditions there's the lila, the grand play which is a metaphor
that Shakespeare used talking about how life is a stage and the men and women are merely
players on it but I like to think that if these things were written about today we would
say life is an interactive video game and we're all avatars within the game.
That would be the metaphor that we would use because it's one that makes a little more
sense and can bridge the gap between science, technology and a lot of these spiritual traditions.
Wow, well this book everybody should go and buy it, it's called The Simulation Hypothesis
and MIT Computer Scientist shows why AI, Quantum Physics and Eastern Mystics all agree we are
in a video game.
Before we wrap this up, I don't want to keep you too long but I can go on for hours
man, this is amazing.
The intersection of consciousness, technology and philosophy is a very interesting area
and a lot of people are very dismissive of it but I think that is exactly the point.
It makes people think in ways that they wouldn't otherwise and I think that's why a lot of
people are talking about it today but I also think there's a lot of people who normally
do not want to talk about philosophy or the nature of reality that this is a way in for
them to talk about these things.
Absolutely.
Let's also really quickly talk about your new book that came out in June I believe of
this year called Startup Myth and Models What You Won't Learn in Business School.
What is the summary of the book?
What is your thesis and what is the main message you want the readers to take away from it?
This book I wrote over the last 25 years of working as an entrepreneur, initially as a
founder and then as a board member and investor and then the subtitle of the book was supposed
to be What You Won't Learn at Stanford Business School but it was published by the
Columbia University Press so they said, well, we can't really take a pot shot at Stanford
but when I was at business school, what I found was that a lot of what they taught us
applied to mature industries and applied to public companies but it didn't always apply
to startups that startups needed a different set of models for thinking about how startup
markets evolved.
I remember in one of the classes, literally the guy who wrote the textbook on decision
modeling, it was a textbook on how to make extremely complicated Excel spreadsheets
and you would plug in all the numbers, scenario A, B, and C and then you would see the results
and you'd say, oh, this number is better than that number which is not as good as this
number so we're going to pick C and I remember raising my hand and saying, well, what if
you just change the numbers on the left, the inputs, he goes, well, then all the numbers
on the right change and I said, well, how do you know what numbers to put in?
He said, well, that's where you have to use your gut as a manager, that's why they pay
you the big bucks and turns out as an entrepreneur, spreadsheets are pretty meaningless because
there isn't any history now in big companies, the best bet of the future is the past.
You look at probabilities of what's happened in the past but the whole reason there is
a market for startups is because the past is not equal to future.
I grew up in Detroit, Michigan and one of my friends went to work for General Motors
and when the Toyota Prius came out as a hybrid car a few years ago and the Japanese companies
were coming out with hybrid cars quickly, I asked him, why hasn't GM released one
and he goes, well, we did the spreadsheets and it just didn't make financial sense
for us.
One of the main messages in the book is that the startup world is different than the traditional
finance world and that you have to follow a different set of rules and they're not
really rules, you can't systemize everything, everyone's like, I want to know if I do
A, B and C, 1, 2, 3, then I will have a successful startup and my degree at Stanford is in management
science but management is partly a science but it's partly an art, there's a lot
of interpersonal stuff that happens and I would say the same with startups.
You can teach you how to put together a deck, how to do a market sizing, how to put together
a business plan, how to build a product, how to be a product manager, how to measure results
but you can't guarantee that following any of those steps will lead to success so there
is a formless element and it's much more like an adventure so I use the idea from mythology
of Joseph Campbell's hero's journey.
He looked at all the myths of the world and found that many of them from the Odyssey to
Beowulf and even more recent ones like Lord of the Rings or Star Wars follow these stages
and turns out the entrepreneurial journey can be summarized in these stages where you
have a call to adventure, you might refuse the call, you cross the threshold and you
find yourself in the road of trials which is when you release the product and you realize
oh my God, things are not going like I thought they would and you have to get out there and
figure out how to get through these challenges that crop up along the way.
You have these archetypes like mentors and gatekeepers just like in the old stories,
these colorful characters, it's like a video game in a way and then you often have a trip
to the underworld, I mean Odysseus literally went down to Hades in the Lord of the Rings,
they went to the mines of Moria in entrepreneurship.
Often there's a life or death, not necessarily your physical life or death but life or death
of the company and so the book is laid out in the stages of the hero's journey to then
find the treasure which you might think of means selling your company for a lot of money
or going public but really the treasure is as Joseph Campbell would call it, a magic
elixir that you can take back into the normal everyday world and so it's really about how
this journey changes you as a person and how you make decisions along the way.
That's kind of a long summary of what this book is about.
That's amazing.
It reminded me of something I think Naval Ravikant was talking about that even if you
talk to successful people how they did it, they can't really tell you or the honest
ones are not like I don't know.
That's right, the honest ones will tell you that there's a lot more luck involved than
just follow steps one, two or three and luck may not be the right word.
I think it ties very much to the situation and the personality of the person in that
situation so there's the internal and the external side of these things and then those
have to align and when they do that maybe leads to more financial success but in either
way you will learn a lot about yourself on the entrepreneurial journey.
Well, Riz, we definitely have optimized many years worth of knowledge in this almost an
hour, a little more than an hour conversation, really appreciate it.
What's next for you and where our audience can follow your work?
Sure, so they can go to my website which is zenentrepreneur.com or follow me on Twitter
at Riz Stanford and I'm working on some additional books right now in the early days
and still doing technology investing and helping entrepreneurs get their game companies and
virtual reality companies off the ground and at some point I may try to establish an institute
doing research on all of these different stages that I talked about for the simulation point
to be a focal point for bringing all this stuff together but that's probably in the
long term.
Yeah, so you're still investing in startups and people can pitch to you.
Yeah, so I'm a venture partner at a couple of venture funds, one's called Griffin Gaming
Partners and one's called Ridge Ventures, one does enterprise software and one does
more video games and so you can connect with me on LinkedIn or go to my website and contact
me there as well at zenentrepreneur.com.
Okay, amazing.
Let me ask you the last question that now it has a different meaning to me because you'll
know why, I ask all my guests that if you come across an intelligent alien from a different
civilization, what would you say is the worst thing humanity has done and what would you
say is a greatest achievement?
But now I'm thinking how do we know who those aliens are in this simulation hypothesis?
Right, I mean I'll answer it using superheroes.
What happened in the 19th century is we got a much better understanding of the physical
universe and there are stars and there are planets.
So what's happened is a lot of the superheroes in the 20th century were like supermen from
the planet Krypton, right?
So they're from out there and they come here and they have different powers.
If you look at superheroes today, like when my nephews, they watched The Flash on TV,
they have parallel universes.
Supergirl is in her own parallel universe and you have Earth 1, Earth 2 or 3.
So just now, this idea of parallel universes and multiple timelines is starting to creep
into the popular consciousness and so this idea of aliens, it may almost be a 20th century
idea that in fact, if they showed up, it could be that they're piercing through from a different
level of reality.
So it's possible that those people out there who say they've seen UFOs and aliens and
those people who say the Fermi paradox is true and we have no sign of aliens, both could
be right in the sense that they're not actually physical aliens coming from other planets.
They're actually piercing through from another level of reality.
So my guess is they've already been watching us to a certain extent.
So what would you say is the worst thing humanity has done and what is our greatest achievement?
That's a good question.
The worst and the best are probably both represented by the world's religions, right?
I feel like they have brought out the best of humanity in trying to understand and how
we treat others but they've also brought out the worst of humanity in religious wars
and bigotry and in wanting to conquer each other.
So I guess I'd give the same answer for both.