when you overly centralize power
or you overly centralize the culture,
like the cultural permissibility,
you end up breaking the system.
And the fact of the matter is just that,
humans are different, like we're all different.
And that's the cool thing about us, actually.
It's what I love the most is,
when I talk to somebody,
you don't know what's gonna happen, right?
They could be end up being your best friend
or you could just be like, I didn't like that guy at all.
Right?
And it's just, that's our beauty and that's our curse, right?
Cause sometimes we're too different to get along.
And other times we're just different enough to cooperate,
but we're not gonna be friends, but we'll be colleagues,
like, you know, and everything in between.
And when you overly centralize power
to people of a specific kind of belief
or a specific kind of background,
you're always going to neglect the people
that are towards the extremity
of wherever you sit on that spectrum.
And so that is never going to create stability
because eventually everyone else
is gonna start teaming up on you
and you're going to effectively be an imperialist
within your own country.
And this happens whenever you see
the centralization of power, right?
Every single major historical example
of a complex society that has collapsed,
has collapsed effectively because it overly centralized
economic decision-making and overly pushed that
to deal with problems that it itself was creating.
["The 100th Episode"]
All right, Justin, Elaine,
welcome to what's supposed to be the 100th episode.
I know I told you that,
but my guests canceled on the day of,
so we're on the 99th episode of Neo Human Podcast.
Still a pretty good number.
That's a very good number.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you for your time
and thank you for being here, man.
Really appreciate it.
Yeah, thanks for having me.
I'm happy to be here.
I think this is gonna be fun.
Yeah, I saw you on War Room
and I thought your research
is about something very, very interesting.
It's about, from my perspective,
about the tool and the intention behind the tool,
which is AI and religion.
So I'm hoping that we get to that,
but before getting into any of that,
I'm talking about your book.
You also have a new book.
Congratulations about that.
Understanding Religion Through Artificial Intelligence,
Bonding, and Belief.
We'll be talking about that too,
but just so we can have some kind of a context,
let's start with your background,
the works you've done, the lives you've lived,
and what are you mainly focused on now these days?
Yeah, so I've lived many lives
in my short time on this earth.
I've been very blessed in that regard.
So I'm originally from the DC area,
kind of grew up in a really small town
on the Eastern Shore of Maryland,
where it's just chicken coops and corn fields mostly.
And that's, it kind of ties back in later,
which is why I mentioned this.
I did my undergraduate studies in religion, actually,
at the University of Vermont,
where I got really interested actually
in this idea that every culture
and every group of people
throughout all of human history has had religion.
And I grew up in the Methodist Church,
and I had a really positive experience in the church
as a kid for the most part.
And then, of course, I was in high school around 9-11.
And on the one hand, I have my personal experience,
which is positive with religion.
It was really a bedrock for my family growing up.
And then, of course, I also see
that religion can breed terrorism.
And so it kind of just led to a lot of questions in my mind.
And I kind of set off to try and answer the question of,
why do people do things that are so irrational
as kill themselves in the name of their God?
But then also, how can this one thing,
how can these deeply held beliefs
and how can our faith inspire both beauty and horror?
And it kind of set me off in that curiosity,
that curiosity set me off in my direction.
I realized around the time
that I was finishing my degree, actually,
that being able to program computers,
it was a skill that I had that was fairly unique
amongst people who study religion.
Most people who study religion, they read texts.
My languages in college were Latin and ancient Greek,
not Python or Java,
which is what I use to study religion now.
So it really kind of set me down that path.
And I realized I had to go to Europe
to kind of study this further.
American universities
are not into a scientific approach to religion.
They really want to push this sort of like
hard post-modernist ideology.
They want to look at cultural relativism
and everything has to be described.
And science is just kind of like
lensing this imperial patriarchy
over top of other people.
And that wasn't going anywhere for me.
It really, I needed to be able
to use the scientific approach.
And so I went to Belfast, actually, in Northern Ireland.
Of course, Belfast is well known for the troubles
that they've had between the Protestants and the Catholics
for years, for decades at this point.
And so living there kind of also framed it.
And I said, okay, well, I've studied conflict,
I've studied AI,
and now I also want to try and study stability.
And so I did my doctoral research at Oxford University
where for part of that, actually,
and I did my doctoral research
in anthropology department, believe it or not,
where I used data science and AI
to try and answer critical questions
about why large scale religions persist
the way they do today.
And I went to Singapore actually to validate this
because Singapore is the most religiously diverse nation
on earth.
And it is insanely stable
given its levels of diversity on every metric.
So it's kind of an anomaly.
So I wanted to study that and see, you know,
what can I learn?
How can I compare it to Belfast?
How can I compare it to what I see in America?
You know, what does that kind of mean?
And that kind of set me off on my journey
of what brought me to Europe and went back,
did some teaching and some work at Boston University
for a few years as a postdoctoral fellow
at the Center for Mind and Culture
and then came back to Europe and started working,
really doing consultancy and then started a private company
that does work in simulation and data analytics
to try and help people, you know, navigate social media
without having to rely on censorship
and without having to rely on the sensationalist algorithms
of like Twitter and Facebook
to kind of promote material in a negative way.
So trying to, you know, make social media fun again.
That's a noble objective.
Thanks, I might be doomed to fail, but I'm doomed to try.
Well, I mean, it really is about,
you mentioned you were wondering about how religion
give birth to the worst and the best of humanity,
but it really seems to be the natural,
undeniable natural reality of who we are
that we are capable of doing the worst
and we are capable of doing the best.
And, you know, some would even say
that one wouldn't exist without the other.
So we have to take them all together.
So this is an interesting point with respect to religions
and then AI, because AI is being used
as an underlaying of some kind of a system
that as you put it, brings some kind of a stability
with respect or we're having in mind
to have a certain degree of respect
for diversity of thoughts and ideas and perspectives
and, you know, all those kinds of philosophies
and worldviews.
Yeah, I think, yeah, and I also think, you know,
it's interesting to think of those things
as, you know, the positive with the negative.
You know, in some cases, religion is a tool
that people leverage for their own means, right?
A lot of people pick and choose different things
in a religious text just to justify what they're gonna do
and what they really wanna do is political actually.
And they just want religion to justify it.
It's a flag that they fly more than anything else.
And in that regards, you know, any tool
when it's used for good can do great things
and when it's used for evil can do horrible things, right?
So, you know, AI also is like that.
Artificial intelligence, of course,
can automate all sorts of interesting things.
You know, it protects us from fraud on our credit cards,
but it also is exacerbating social instability globally,
I think, because of the way that it selectively promotes
sensationalism on social media
and the way that it's constantly pinging us,
you know, in our brains, basically, you know,
quite literally, I guess, you know, in our pockets
to constantly pay attention and go for social validation
for something that's not real.
And insofar as social media is real,
it's not what's really important.
You know, religion has had a tough time.
Religions generally have had a tough time
making the jump to the social media space, right?
Even the, you know, the Pope has a lot of followers
on Twitter, but you don't hear about the Pope
going viral on Twitter, right?
And I think part of it is because religion
is fundamentally something that is really deep rooted
in face-to-face interactions.
And social media just doesn't, you know,
it doesn't capture that energy in the same way.
And so social media might be an interesting place
for religious groups to post reminders
or, you know, reaffirmations,
but you don't see a lot of online religions
growing very fast, at least not the way you'd expect.
Do you think it's because that the values
within that social context that you mentioned
is defined by very few people, relatively speaking,
who are also practicing their own kind of a religion?
You know, it is not conventional kind of a religion,
but it's a worldview and a philosophy
that determines this is good, this is bad,
this is right, this is wrong, right?
Because that seems to be the main job of the religion,
which by the way, going back to 9-11,
I grew up as a Muslim in Iran.
I went to school as a Shia Muslim.
So my biggest shock when I moved to the West,
first in Canada and then US,
was how people were treating Islam,
because it was very clear to us
that Islam is inherently a political religion.
It is used for political reason,
because it exists for political reason.
So, you know, all those extremes-
I mean, it was born out of political struggle, right?
Absolutely.
I mean, it's-
The book describes it quite clearly.
It's a book of rules and laws
that includes every single aspect of your life,
including how to govern and how to do all of that.
And it's a very big question
how the true followers of that religion
would ever be able to assimilate to Western society,
because they don't care about the laws that are man-made.
They care about the laws of Allah.
Right.
And this is interesting too,
because the separation of religion as a thing, right,
is actually a very new idea.
And it's a very Western idea,
because it's rooted very much
in the idea of a separation of church and state,
which is, you know, not quite even 300 years old yet.
So in the grand scheme of human civilization,
this is like the newest idea that we've had, right,
is to make religion a separate thing.
A lot of cultures throughout the world
don't even have a word for religion.
It's just, that's what they do and what they believe.
It doesn't need a word.
And I think when you look at, you know,
almost any non-Western tradition, but Islam,
definitely being one of them,
the separation of like the secular and the sacred
just doesn't even make sense.
It's just, it's not, it's a non-starter.
That really only exists in the West.
And I think it's something that,
I think it's one of the reasons why the West
has had trouble understanding Islam,
is because, you know, from our perspective, right,
from, you know, the North American perspective, let's say,
or even the European perspective now,
there's very much this idea of like,
well, you know, that's just a religious thing,
but they don't understand that
it's not just a religious thing.
It's actually, it's religion, it's culture.
It's kind of everything about the context.
Exactly, it's a life thing.
And a lot of people don't really understand that,
but it's on the other side of that,
kind of getting back to the comment you made earlier,
one of the things that's interesting about that
is that a lot of times there are people doing things
religiously and they don't see how religious they're being
in a secular space.
And social media is exactly this.
So myself and two of my friends and researchers
that I work with,
Laurent Schulz and Kevin McAfrey,
we studied online behavior on Twitter
using some of the AI systems that I've developed
for analyzing texts on social media
to try and better understand what people's concerns are.
And what we started to find out
is that the moral signature of the far left of Twitter
actually mimics the moral signature that experimentally
is usually more common to conservatives,
particularly conservative religious churches.
And it kind of led us to kind of think,
well, maybe this isn't just an anomaly here,
like theoretically, right?
You have a group of people on the very far left of Twitter
who have certain beliefs that cannot be violated.
And if you do violate them, you should basically be
excommunicated from the community.
Yeah, you should be erased, you should be canceled.
But then if somebody tries to critique
your sort of leadership, right?
Your priesthood, then that can't be tolerated.
And generally, you'll just deny that it's happening
in order to resolve the cognitive dissonance.
And if something bad happens within your group,
you're gonna try and push harder to try and say,
well, even though what's happening
is not right ideologically,
if I can get more people to join my group,
then it justifies my beliefs
and it still makes me look like I'm right.
This is the original research for cognitive dissonance,
which happened in a UFO cult, right?
And that exact idea of like, our leadership is failing us,
but if we get more people to join our side,
then it justifies my belief and my identity
of being part of this political party.
I mean, you see that every four years
in the United States now.
It's almost wild to see if it weren't so scary
to see the way that the political parties in the US
now basically operate as sort of secular religions.
That is very true, and they don't see it as a religion
at all because they're using religion as,
it's so funny, I was telling somebody that religion
by far leftists are being used the same way that,
for example, Israel and America were being used
for Iranian regime to have this ultimate enemy
because of which everything else that you do is justified.
So it just feels like the moment that they managed
to remove that in God we trust from back of the money,
it will be replaced immediately by in the state we trust.
And the value and the religion of state is determined
on the basis of very fundamentalist
and uber conservative kind of religious values
that are secular.
Yeah, it's interesting to reflect on that too, right?
Because even when you look at the political parties
as religions, it's not just a matter of belief too.
Like we have our own rituals, our own secular rituals, right?
Like anyone who looks at the inauguration of a president
can obviously see the ritual that goes there.
When you look at the way that the Senate is,
like the way that the halls are actually set up,
they're set up like churches.
Like all of the people sit in the pew,
the one guy goes to the top pulpit and speaks.
You know, they have like the sort of like, you know,
all of the pomp and circumstance behind them
of whatever altar, whatever sort of structure there is.
And it's, you know, it was deliberately done that way.
I mean, when you go into the,
I think it's the Capitol Rotunda and you look straight up,
it has George Washington being sworn in, right?
And that was done in a very ritualistic way
because they felt it had to be done like a ritual,
but they weren't sure how to do it, right?
So he wore his Freemasons outfit
because there were already,
there's an entire ritual structure to Freemasonry.
And he went, well, I don't have any better ideas.
So everyone that was there was kind of, you know,
they were in Freemasonry as well.
So they just kind of did this Masonic-like ritual
to be part of the inauguration.
The Bible that they swore him in on, if I'm not mistaken,
was actually a Bible from the local
Freemasonry Lodge as well.
And so it kind of reflected this idea
that they needed ritual there.
And the, if I'm not mistaken, the title of that work of art
in the Capitol Rotunda is called
the Apotheosis of Washington, right?
Which is, you know, the becoming,
the man becoming God is basically
how you could translate that in Greek, right?
And Washington does exist kind of as a quasi deity in a way.
And what I find interesting and very frightening
is that in the U.S. now, you know,
our founding fathers were always well-respected,
you know, if not kind of quasi-ideified,
at least in a secular sense,
not in a sort of faith or real religion sense.
But now we no longer agree in the United States
that the founding fathers are to be venerated
or are to be even respected.
And in some cases, you know,
we're actively taking down statues of the founding fathers
and people are arguing that even like,
people as important as Abraham Lincoln
should be kind of re-edited into a modern lens.
And I, that is something that's very troubling
because when you look at how schisms start in religions,
that's one of the main causes is people disagree on,
you know, the role of a founder.
And that is what can make or break,
you know, just about any religion.
And you can even see that in
how Protestantism split from Catholicism.
You can see it also in the Sunni-Shia split historically
as well had to do with, you know, leadership
and who had sort of the right lineage at the right times.
You see the same thing in Buddhism as well.
Almost every major religion can,
if there's been a split or if there are multiple branches,
you can trace those multiple branches to an argument
over the lineage and over the founders.
Yeah, I was going to say that bringing down the statues
of George Washington and Abraham Lincoln,
I see literally no difference between that
and Taliban exploding the Buddha statues in Bamiyan
because it's about the status quo, it's about the ethos.
And so it makes total sense that the American religion
or American Dharma, as Steve Bannon put it,
is being challenged by the woke Dharma
and the woke religion.
Yeah, and in a way, I mean, sadly,
I wish it were more complex and to an extent,
I guess it's more complex than what I'm about to say,
obviously, but heuristically speaking,
it does make sense to kind of say that, you know,
there's the American identity
and then there's the woke identity.
And currently the woke identity is anti-American.
It doesn't stand for American values.
It is, you know, when you look at Antifa protests
and Antifa riots, you know,
they're burning American symbols,
they're spinning, they're burning the American flag
and they're doing that and they know exactly
what they're doing when they do it, right?
They're arguing that, what was it, New York City,
I think it was, just took Thomas Jefferson
out of the city hall.
Yes.
Like these events are symbolic,
but they're very real when it comes
to constructing an identity.
And I think one of the ways that you see this
is it starts as a slippery slope
and then it happens quickly.
Historically speaking, when you look at, you know,
moves like this and shifts like this,
it starts slow and then it starts fast
and then it ends fast.
But also you see this, you know,
as part of the slow start, I think,
was getting rid of the Pledge of Allegiance in schools.
I think that that's one of those things, you know,
I had a very good friend growing up
who was a Jehovah's Witness
and he claimed a religious exemption
and he wouldn't stand for the pledge.
And I don't have any problem with that.
If that's a religious exemption, that's fine.
But as a society, you know, the bulk of us,
the most of us should have something that we do
that repeats and reaffirms our identity as a people.
And every people should have that, right?
Because it helps them to create their identity.
And people who have stronger identities
are generally happier, right?
If, you know, you get into a situation and times are tough,
you know that you have people in your group
that can help you out.
You know, you have common experiences, common beliefs
and the reaffirmation of something like this,
the Pledge of Allegiance,
very much functioned to do that psychologically
for a very long time, even though, you know,
we did change the Pledge of Allegiance
at a certain point, right?
And added in God we trust on our currency at a certain point
to reflect that our identity was different
than the rise in the communist identity during the Cold War.
So it had its particular function, historically speaking.
But at the same time, you know, we can change those words.
What's important is that those words reflect core values,
though, and that they're repeated often enough
that we all know where we all stand.
Yeah, a common big picture to strive towards,
to give meaning to this experience that you're having,
you know, otherwise, what's the difference of being anywhere?
You know, it's- Exactly, exactly.
And you see this in some of the thought leadership
on the woke side of the United States right now,
where in the past, you know, free markets,
freedom of expression, you know, free speech,
these were certain rights that were just fundamental
to the American belief, you know,
we can disagree on different things, you know,
we don't have to be the same religion
or like the same kind of drinks,
or even drinker, drink beer, not drink beer,
or whatever it is, those are just details.
Even vote Republican or Democrat or third party,
those were kind of details,
because we all agree things like free speech,
freedom of association, you know, a free press,
like, you know, help, and then little things too,
like helping your neighbor, right?
You know, being someone that you can rely on,
respecting your elders, giving up your seat on the bus
when somebody needs it, like,
there were these little cultural things
that kind of built up, you know,
who Americans were as an identity and as a people.
And those things, a lot of them have come
under attack quite directly, you know,
some of the woke leadership, you know,
I was watching an interview on Democracy Now,
not that long ago, with Ibram X. Kendi,
who was at Boston University at the same time I was,
actually, or he still is there.
And he mentioned that to be anti-racist, right?
Which was his, like, neologism to try
and kind of create a mental gymnastics leap.
For racism.
In his books, yeah, for racism, right?
It's basically to be anti-racist is to be racist,
but a different kind.
And it's a kind that he thinks is a good kind of racism,
which boggles my mind, right?
When I was at Boston University,
my office was in the School of Religion and Theology,
which is the school that granted Dr. Martin Luther King
his doctorate.
And at that same university now,
there is a man who is perpetuating racism
under the guise of equity and inclusion,
and just kind of spinning on the greatest speeches
and teachings that Martin Luther King
ever gave the United States.
And that just blew my mind.
It made me very uncomfortable to be there at the university.
And it made a lot of the students uncomfortable as well.
I got very close with some of the students
who were not okay with the woke direction
the university was going with.
One of them is Joe Allen,
who's now a correspondent for Steve Bannon on The War Room.
Joe's still a good friend of mine to this day, actually.
We disagree about a lot of stuff,
but we respect each other.
We know that at the end of the day,
we have those core values, right?
So when he and I go back and forth on AI and transhumanism,
we really get arguing,
but we do it out of a place of respect.
And at the end of it, we both know
that we're still gonna have a cheers of our beer
at the end of the conversation,
and everything's gonna be fine,
because we know that those fundamental core values are there,
and those are the guiding lights.
The debates are just how we kind of take turns
to right the ship as we move forward.
But I think we can't have progress
without those fundamental values being there.
Ibram X. Kendi on Democracy Now recently said
that to be anti-racist is to be anti-capitalist.
And the repercussions of that,
particularly in light of the leadership
of the Black Lives Matter movement,
saying that they have an ideology,
and they are trained Marxists,
and the relationship between wokeism
and social justice warrior terms and neo-Marxist terms,
being very clear.
And we've spelled this out actually in research
that we've published online as well,
showing not only using an analysis of Google Books,
which is the largest corpus that's digitized
in the history of humankind,
we also were following Twitter conversations online.
And we were finding that you do still see this relationship
between the sort of like neo-Marxist ideology
and the social justice worship,
taking off slowly from the 80s,
and then really propelling exponentially
into the 2000s.
And these things are all related.
And I think that's what's really defining
the rhetoric of the left.
And it worries me because that's the dominant rhetoric
on social media.
And ideally social media is a place for all of us to speak
and for all of us to kind of have our discussions,
even if we disagree.
But what we're seeing now is a partitioning of social media,
or what we've seen recently is a partitioning
of social media, of the Twitter and the Facebooks,
and then your alternatives, right?
Like Minds, Getter, Parler, and the other.
And I don't, I mean, I support those
alternative social media sites.
I have accounts on most of them,
and I use them of different levels.
I use them all more than I use Facebook
and more than I use Twitter.
But I think that we need to have a common dialogue.
And Reddit has a lot of different people there.
It has a lot of diversity of thought.
But it also has a censorship issue, in my opinion.
They're too quick to censor.
So we're at the point that our digital and our analog,
online and offline lives are suffering,
if we wanna use that term, from the same kind of gridlocks,
that they all go back to monopolization
of values and ideas.
Would that be fair to say?
Yeah, I would say that like, yeah, the monopolization
of values and ideas is really unhealthy socially.
And social media kind of, I mean, the foundation
of it offline has existed for a little while,
but it was kind of, you know, it was a little bit here
and there in the media.
But now, recently, it has been just, you know,
it hits us over the head every day.
One of the things that we found in our research,
and I gave a talk about this recently,
the talk's actually on YouTube, in Cyprus,
at the Reflect Festival in October,
I presented some interesting research that shows
that when you look at crime rates in America
and perceived crime rates in America,
so the actual crime rates,
and then how people think the crime rates going,
they basically, like, they have data going back
to like the eighties and the nineties.
And so it basically kind of keeps going down
and down and down, and it's true,
both the crime rate was going down,
it's been going down for decades
when you look at the general trend.
But it goes down and then all of a sudden,
there's a divergence,
where the crime rate keeps going down,
but the perceived crime rate starts to go up.
And when you look at when this divergence happens,
the divergence keeps getting greater and greater and greater
between actual crime rates and perceived crime rates
as adoption of broadband internet
in the United States starts to go up,
and the rise of social media usage
starts to go up in the United States.
That's one of the things where it's just a very clear tale
of that constant media stream
with algorithms that are perpetuating
and promoting the most sensational news, right?
Which is typically violence or instability
or riots or robberies.
These are the things that are gonna get promoted
by these algorithms,
because those are the things
that are gonna get the most engagement
and it's gonna get the most people talking.
And we've suffered in the real world,
psychologically because of it.
And I think that was a very large part
in setting up the context and the motivation
for the riots that we saw in 2000,
where a lot of people were frustrated,
some justifiably so,
and some were just there because they perceived the world
in a way that wasn't true.
You mean 2020?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, 2020.
You know, in 2020 and to an extent, I guess 2021,
but it's really kind of died down recently.
But in 2020, there was a lot of anger
and it was very much being promoted by social media
and the actual media.
I mean, generally I try and follow both sides of the media
to kind of get a sense of what's going on.
And then I have a few sources that I really like
because I think they start from a place of balance.
And then I have a couple that I like
just because they're keeping people in line.
Project Veritas, for example, is one of them.
I follow Project Veritas
and sometimes I don't like the way they frame things
here and there, but on the whole,
I think that he is doing really good work
in exposing a lot of nonsense.
And one of the things that was exposed by Project Veritas
was one of the CNN producers.
You know, and he literally said, if it bleeds, it leads.
And they had the coronavirus infection and body count
going all the way through the election.
And then after the election, it just went away.
The virus didn't go away,
but all of a sudden the media coverage went away.
And now they're caught in between this,
like want to basically propagandize
for the Biden administration at CNN
and make it look like everything's going well
and he's solving the coronavirus problem,
but also kind of push their narrative
that the coronavirus problem is, you know,
getting out of hand and that they need more lockdowns.
And so they're really kind of caught
in an almost Orwellian doublespeak.
It's like, it's almost like watching 1984 unfold,
like it was written as a handbook instead of a fiction.
Yeah, so I think a lot of those approaches like,
how can you be that stupid to say fiery, but mostly peaceful?
You know, like, you know.
Right?
It's like, are you, you cannot possibly be that stupid.
So there is a reason, there is an intention behind,
you know, kind of nudging things to the direction
that they want to be led towards their bigger narrative,
which goes back to monopolization of values and ideals
that are being practiced in a very religious kind of a way.
Now, I want to say that all of this has hyped up perhaps
because of use of computers and use of internet
and more recently use of artificial intelligence
and machine learning, use of modern technology basically,
which is evolving exponentially while we're experiencing
in a very linear kind of a fashion.
So that's why maybe it seems like everything
is getting out of control.
But the problem is that these AI systems
that are now being built and monopolized
by a lot of these people,
they are following the same kind of monopolization
of values and ideals and objectives and goals,
because the same people who have caused these problems,
you know, right now in this world,
they're behind developing these systems
that they can later on use for like a social credit system
and, you know, on and on and on.
Yeah.
I mean, the idea of implementation
of a social credit system is one of the,
in my mind is one of the scariest things
in the AI debate right now.
A lot of AI honestly is useless and unimpressive.
And when you look at really what's being developed out there,
a lot of it's not that interesting.
A lot of it's nonsense.
A lot of it's like, you know,
make your face look like a turtle.
It's just stupid stuff.
But there's certain ideas that are being implemented in,
you know, for example, in China, the social credit system,
it should be the biggest wake-up call
to the West generally that has existed since the 1930s.
And I don't see any other way around it.
And I mean, I almost, you know,
I don't want to come off as hyperbolic,
but when you look at what's going on there in China,
when it comes to the social credit score,
when it comes to, you know,
the concentration camps that they have in Xinjiang,
when it comes to the way they're manipulating the media,
the way they treated the COVID lockdowns
by just welding the doors shut
and just helping people fend for themselves
and then acting like it didn't happen.
And then, you know,
not even to necessarily go down the rabbit hole
that is the lab leak,
but it's just, you look at that and you look at China today
and the way that it's utilizing like child labor in Africa
to monopolize things like
critical rare earth materials and stuff.
It's just, there's nothing going on there
that suggests that this is a peaceful interaction
that we're going to continue to have.
Everything suggests that this is a Cold War scenario
led by a World War II level dictatorship.
Perhaps more dangerous because Nazis could even dream
of, you know, having this level of technology,
this level of tool.
Yeah, I mean, Nazis didn't have the bomb, right?
And China does, you know, they didn't have AI.
When it, you know,
they had to go around and check on people's papers
and they were just looking at people to kind of, you know,
see, oh, do you have your papers?
Are you the right, do you go to a synagogue?
You know, what religion do you have?
What's your last name?
How do you spell it?
You know, do you speak Yiddish?
They were looking at these things
and they were looking for that.
They were looking for all sorts of people, right?
They were looking for the Roma, for the gypsies as well.
And, you know, the gypsies typically have a darker skin tone
in this part of Europe.
So a lot of times they were easy to spot and round up.
But in looking at what China's doing,
I mean, they are using AI
and there are patents that have come forward
that say we can identify Uyghur Muslims.
And then they act like, oh, no, no, well, that's,
we didn't really say that.
And it's like, we saw, you said that.
This is obviously happening.
And these systems are being put into place
where you can just round people up using AI
for saying the wrong thing, for looking the wrong way,
for having the wrong belief.
And I mean, ultimately they're doing to the Uyghurs
what they wished they could have done
to the Tibetans before that.
And it's only a matter of time
before they find someone outside of their border
that's standing in the way of the regime's dominance
of the CCP and they're gonna target them too.
That's the scariest thing, I think.
They already installed automated robots
at the border with India
that they're automatically shooting at Indian soldiers.
So they're using-
I've read reports of this.
They're using all the tools at their disposal
for the objective that they have,
this bigger picture that they have,
point of alignment that is defined by the Communist Party.
And I think this is a point of difference
between me and someone like Joe Allen,
who I had about two hour long conversation
with him on the phone, mostly about AI, I think.
He told me he had a long conversation with you on AI.
And I enjoyed it.
I actually approached him and said,
dude, you're doing a very good job
because these kinds of stuff,
I've talked with a lot of people during this podcast
that politicians aren't even talking about it.
And these are the most consequential things
that are happening.
And the most valid answer I got is that politicians
aren't talking about it because this is not a worry
of their constituents.
Constituents don't even know these things exist
and these things are happening,
which brings an entire issue with
how are we dealing with democracy as a system of governance
when you have a centrally driven monster and dragon
like China on the other side of the equation.
But my point is that we cannot get rid of tools
to defeat tools.
We need to use the tools based on our intention
and our own values and perspective
in order to defeat enemy,
whoever you wanna call it that are using very freely
and openly whatever kind of tool that is available to them.
And I think this is a point that I take part
with a lot of people on the right
who are saying, no, all this technology,
the modern technology, AI and all that,
they're demonic, they're evil, they're satanic.
We shouldn't be using them at all.
They're like, well, you're not gonna survive them.
Yeah, it's funny, cause actually I feel like,
not to talk about Joe when he's not here,
but I feel like Joe kind of struggles with that too.
Cause when he and I talk about that,
he has this kind of tonality to it as if it's like,
this is like a struggle against sort of like,
you know, this almost like demonic technology.
And I don't view it that way at all actually.
I'm very pro technology.
I do think it's a tool
and I think it's a tool that we can use, right?
And so we've been working,
so my company has been working with minds.com.
We started a project about,
I guess it's about a year ago now,
where they basically,
they read a paper that we did on simulating censorship.
And basically our conclusion based on running
20,000 different simulations
of how individuals interact on social networks,
that centralized censorship
actually increases radicalization.
And that allowing people
to just choose with whom they interact
and saying, ah, you know, that guy,
he's being a dick, I'm gonna block him.
And so you just block him
instead of having Facebook come in and remove him entirely,
that centralized censorship increases radicalization,
but the one-to-one censorship
doesn't have the same sort of effect.
So I was speaking with the guys at minds.com
and they're committed to not censoring, right?
Unless it's illegal, they won't censor it.
If it's not safe for work,
they ask you to tag it so you can blur it
so that if you're using minds.com at work,
you don't have something pornographic
scroll up your feed, for example,
like they don't block pornography, right?
It's legal, it can stay on the site.
Just respect others who might be checking this at work
and blur it out for them is what they ask.
And so I really like that approach.
I really support that approach.
I think it aligns with free speech values.
So the question then is how can we also make sure though
that radicalization and hatred don't breed on that site?
And on the one hand, not censoring already helps,
but on the other hand,
what causes radicalization is not using the internet, right?
There's been tons of studies on this
and none of them have really shown
that internet use is a strong predictor
of radicalization or extremism.
What is a predictor are real life experiences.
And what seems to be happening,
particularly with people who are like,
for example, if they're white supremacists
and they are to the point of extremism
where they may commit violence
against another racial community.
What typically has happened is that their understanding
of that racial community just is not realistic at all.
And it's usually because of isolation, right?
They've never actually spoken to someone of another race
or had to interact with them.
And so it allows them to breed hatred.
And I think that's why guys like Daryl Davis
have been so effective in de-radicalization.
Daryl Davis is part of the project with us actually.
Oh, awesome.
Yeah, yeah, he's been great to work with.
So we were working with Daryl Davis
and the late Jesse Morton was also part of this with us.
And we have Bill Ottman, the CEO at Mines
is working with us directly on it,
as is Jack, the COO at Mines.
So it's been a really fun, a really cool project
where we've brought in all kinds of experts globally
on radicalization and said,
look, what are your proposals?
And we hear them out and we just tell them like,
censorship is non-negotiable.
That's not on the table for us.
Like we're gonna figure out
how to address radicalization and extremism,
but we're not gonna sacrifice these core values.
And that's been a really interesting project
because everyone's response in social media is,
just ban them, just get rid of them.
And the issue is that that doesn't solve the problem.
That just makes it so that you don't see the problem.
And that's a very different solution.
Yeah, out of sight, out of mind, they think,
but it'll always come back harder and more extreme.
Like you can't get rid of the information.
Yeah, like one of the things that boggled my mind
was the general media response to like,
what was going on in 2020 and even all the way up
to like the January 6 protests and everything.
It's like, people were so surprised.
And I was like, why are you surprised by this?
You're just not listening.
If you're surprised, you're just not listening.
And I think part of it, and one of the reasons
why I think the January 6 protest
was so surprising to people
is because those were the kinds of voices
that have been algorithmically silenced.
And so people didn't realize how widespread,
not QAnon, not any particular conspiracy theory,
but how widespread frustration with the government system
leading into the election
and then frustration with the election.
And the idea that they did not have a voice heard
in the justice system, that was suppressed online.
So nobody saw it coming when it instantiated itself
the way that it did on January 6.
And that I find very interesting.
Then the media of course has now used this as like impetus
for domestic terrorist reform,
the likes of which we've not seen since 9-11.
And that I find very confusing
from a legal perspective, from a policy perspective.
Because while I agree if a group tries to take over
the Senate during a proceeding,
that is just by letter of the law.
And you look at how the FBI defines what terrorism is,
is basically any sort of use or threat of violence
in order to achieve a political end.
It's a very vague definition,
maybe problematically vague actually.
But if we take that definition,
I can see how you could apply that definition
to a small subset of the people present on January 6.
However, if you apply it to January 6,
but you don't apply it to Antifa in 2020,
it makes me question the extent to which
this is entirely politically motivated.
It is entirely politically motivated.
And not really about its security.
Yeah, and that's the conclusion that I've come to.
And I think that most logical people will come to
as we say, look, here's our measuring stick.
If it fits in this box, we get to call it terrorism.
And they throw January 6, and basically people go,
everyone, and some people say everyone.
And then I go, you're not looking
at what they were doing there.
And then they go, some of them.
And I go, okay, some of them,
I can see how this fits the definition, yes.
And then I would say, okay, insurrections, Antifa, right?
What about Chavez, right?
They declared an independent nation
within the United States, and they took over a courthouse,
which sounds familiar, right?
They took over a government building,
declared an independent nation,
and then guarded it with arms for like a month.
But that wasn't an insurrection or terrorism.
And it just makes me really worried
because the key to stability in a democracy
is an independent judiciary.
And if we don't have an independent judiciary
in the United States, effectively you have regulation
and legislation by the executive, right?
By enforcement.
The law is what the person at the top says what the law is.
And in the US, that person at the top
can change every four years.
That doesn't make for a stable society.
It doesn't make for stable investments.
Like, how can you plan a business
if you don't know if your business
will be legal in four years, right?
And I think the marijuana industry has seen this
in particular, right?
Those guys have struggled, not just socioculturally
about acceptance or not acceptance
or the morality of using or not using marijuana,
but just legally speaking,
those guys don't know whether they're coming or going.
Yeah.
Cryptocurrency also is the same way right now.
Cryptocurrency, which is probably the largest opportunity
and it's probably the biggest wealth transfer
to like the little guy that we've ever seen.
When you look at how many guys got into cryptocurrency
before banks, well, banks were still saying
that it's nonsense and it's a Ponzi scheme
and all this other stuff.
Guys were buying Bitcoin.
And a lot of these guys are just little guys
who now can afford apartments
that they never could have afforded
because they invested in Bitcoin
when Bitcoin was at like, you know, four or 500,
maybe it was at a thousand or 2000.
And now it's sitting at $40,000
and they've outperformed the best hedge funds on Wall Street.
And now of course the SEC wants to come in
and act like they have the authority to regulate.
It's not clear that they do,
but they're gonna regulate by enforcement
and they're gonna say, well,
we're gonna take you to court.
We're gonna sue you and ruin your life and your company.
And then we'll see whether or not you broke the law.
And that's not rule of law.
That's not healthy.
That's, you know, what a dictatorship does.
Yeah, at the same time,
there are people who are running right now
for Senate, Josh Mandel in Ohio
and Blake Masters in Arizona.
They already called for Fort Satoshi Nakamoto
as a new Fort Knox for United States government
to hold Bitcoin.
And you know, this contrast I think exists
exactly because there was a power struggle
for a vacuum that hasn't been created
as a result of four years of maybe five years of Trump,
who I consider to be a psychedelic.
Trump was a psychedelic.
You know, it's like.
I like that.
The entire world tripped on Trump really hard.
And some people have been having very bad trips
because their entire identity and worldview was shattered.
That how is this even possible?
I like that.
I've not thought of it that way before,
but I really like that.
Trump was a trip.
He really was like a psychedelic.
Cause in a way you were like, is this real?
There's aspects of reality to some of these things.
And then some of these things, I don't know.
Some of it was, some of his behavior,
I personally found kind of bizarre.
So I guess.
He also revealed that it doesn't really matter
who's elected president.
There is a class in DC, which I have a friend.
He's a White House correspondent.
He's saying DC is not even America.
You know, it's like an occupied zone basically
by people whose interests is not shared
with absolute majority of American people.
And they've taken over this country.
So absolutely it has everything they're doing.
It has political incentive and political implication,
but I think they've overreached.
And that's like a silver lining in all of this to me,
that they just gone overboard.
That's why they're becoming very overtly coercive
and violent.
And it's just not sustainable, you know,
because United States is not North Korea.
Exactly.
And one of the things that a lot of the work
that I've done in the AI space has allowed me to do
is kind of investigate what causes things to go wrong, right?
What happens when you overly centralize an identity,
when you overly centralize power,
or what happens when you make it like super distributed?
And one of the patterns that we've seen in this research
is that when you overly centralized power
or you overly centralized the culture,
like the cultural permissibility, you end up breaking
the system.
And the fact of the matter is just that, you know,
humans are different, like we're all different.
And that's the cool thing about us actually.
It's what I love the most is, you know,
when I talk to somebody,
you don't know what's gonna happen, right?
They could be end up being your best friend,
or you could just be like,
I didn't like that guy at all, right?
And it's just, that's our beauty.
And that's our curse, right?
Because sometimes we're too different to get along.
And other times we're just different enough to cooperate,
but we're not gonna be friends, but we'll be colleagues,
like, you know, and everything in between.
And when you overly centralized power
to people of a specific kind of belief
or a specific kind of background,
you're always going to neglect the people
that are towards the extremity
of wherever you sit on that spectrum.
And so that is never going to create stability
because eventually everyone else
is gonna start teaming up on you,
and you're going to effectively be an imperialist
within your own country.
And this happens whenever you see
the centralization of power, right?
Every single major historical example
of a complex society that has collapsed,
has collapsed effectively
because it overly centralized economic decision-making
and overly pushed that to deal with problems
that it itself was creating.
So like, for example, in this,
you can actually read the guy
with Cambridge University Press actually published a book
called The Complex of Complexes,
or The Collapse of Complex Societies.
His name's Joseph Tainter.
He's a professor at Utah.
He surveyed over 20 different complex societies
and basically found that what happens
is when a society makes an investment into something,
some problem that it has,
there's an effect of declining marginal returns
in the economic sense.
And basically what that means is that
when you put a dollar in the first time,
you get a dollar out.
But when you put a dollar in the second time,
you only get like 98 cents back out.
And then when you put a dollar in again,
maybe you only get 90 cents out.
And the more money you put into these problems,
the less value you actually get out of it.
And at a certain point,
society, you start putting money into problems
that the problem solvers have created.
And when you get to the point
where you're putting resources,
if it's wood in the Roman Empire,
if it's olive trees in the Greek Empire,
like the Greek Empire was built without wood.
Like a lot of people don't realize
how much wood does not grow in Greece.
So because of that, like they had to rely on trade.
So when they were investing in social problems,
there was a very clear declining marginal return, right?
This works in barter systems.
It works for gold.
It happened to the Mayas and the Incas.
And to an extent, I think we can look at this
also happening in the United States today.
And that's one of the biggest worries that I see.
It happened in the Soviet Union, right?
But at the point in which your government is saying,
oh, this is a problem, I can fix it.
I need some money.
And we go, okay, here's some money and they fix it.
But then later, their fix created a problem
that they then need more money to fix.
We can start to see how our returns
on our tax money investment
are getting lower and lower and lower.
And with a US national debt that gets so high
that it's interest payments alone
are no longer able to be paid, much less the principle.
You start to see how we start to get
into an unsustainable trajectory
where our money is not getting,
it's not solving our problems as a society.
And there's becoming so much of it because of inflation
that it's not even getting us that far anyways.
So between inflation of a debased currency
and overly centralization of decision-making in a society,
that's what really leads to very serious
and systemic issues in societies that otherwise, right?
Like most major empires don't fall because of the military.
They fall internally.
And these are the mechanisms that like some
of the AI systems that we've been studying
are addressing aspects of this.
Different economic models from archeologists
even are seeing this.
And this is a recurrent pattern.
And they say history doesn't repeat itself, it rhymes.
And I worry that this is what we're looking at right now.
And unless we really find a way to kind of get back
to local communities and just address
what the people of the United States are worried about
and not be worried about what the people in DC
are worried about or coastal elites
and cities generally are worried about
and kind of get back to the ground, right?
Get back to the earth.
We're not gonna be dealing with an ideological reality
that can solve the very real problems
that we're gonna face over the next,
let's say 50 to 100 years.
Government justifies its existence as a problem solver.
So solving problems is against the interest
of government's existence.
Because if you solve problem, there is no government.
Right?
I think this is one of the main reasons
why the biggest structural change
that Americans should mandate, right?
Make it a non-negotiable or term limits.
Because, and this actually comes from something
I remember reading from Thomas Jefferson
is that the politician should not be a job,
being a politician should not be a career.
It should be something you don't even want to do, right?
It should be something you're forced or obliged to do
because you feel it is your duty as an American
to be a government servant.
But that through term limits, you're forced
to deal with the reality that you create.
So that if you're a farmer, when you go in,
you got four years, maybe we'll get you six years
in the Senate or something like that.
And then after those six years,
you're gonna go back to farming.
And if you screwed up the country,
it's gonna make your life harder.
What the biggest risk and one of the reasons
why I think we see what we see in America today
is because Nancy Pelosi can get in in 1985
and she doesn't have to do anything except stand up
and say a bunch of nonsense, ruin a bunch of people's lives.
And then she comes out with a net worth of $120 million,
which given taxes, I saw a funny thing,
a napkin calculation that I was doing is that effectively,
if we assume, right, her salary is 233,000 a year.
So if we assume that she lived a very, very,
let's say a life within her means, which she didn't,
and that she invested $100,000 a year on average
since she basically got into politics in like 1987,
then her average returns must have been about 30 to 35%
investing in the market.
It is how she could have had to have made that money.
That makes her the greatest investor
in the history of the country.
Warren Buffett's average annual returns
are about 20% on average a year.
So we need to stop reading Warren Buffett
and we need to choose whatever strategy
Nancy Pelosi has chosen in her investments.
And that I think is interesting question to ask is,
well, if she causes the problems,
if she solves the problems and she contracts the companies
that are going to or are not going to solve these problems,
is it possible that she was doing something
that she shouldn't have been?
And obviously it seems very clear
that she's been insider trading for 35 years,
because otherwise you can't save enough.
It would take her like a thousand years
to save that much money.
It's not a chance.
And the beauty of this era is that the jig is up.
You know, the curtain has fallen.
So we'll see where it leads.
I don't think Nancy Pelosi was an early investor
in Bitcoin or anything like that.
So it's...
Not according to her financial returns.
Maybe she's not.
I mean, is she lying?
I would not be so sure.
Nancy Pelosi lying.
I think the funniest thing about this, right?
I think my favorite thing about the news
that I heard about her recently
is that she's moving to Florida.
Yes, yeah.
So it's like, so she's actually,
she's from Maryland originally.
So she's like from my neck of the woods.
And then she moved out to California basically as,
you know, because her parents
were well connected in politics.
So she gets out to California,
ruins California for 35 years, and then goes,
oh, you know where I'm gonna go?
I'm gonna go to Florida.
Even though she was one of those people
that was calling DeSantis basically a murderer
because he wasn't gonna do long-term.
They all did.
AOC was here partying.
She was calling DeSantis murderer.
I heard about this.
Yeah, they were saying, oh, this is murder
and all that you're killing innocent lives.
And it's like the first place you guys go
when you get a chance to go somewhere is there.
And then AOC got COVID for partying,
maskless in Florida.
And she's been awfully silent about it.
And I think that's funny.
But hey, I think AOC revealed something very fundamental
very early on when she said that
it's more important to be morally right
than factually correct.
And that's all we need to know about how they operate,
how they see the world.
And this is my concern
that the very same people are in charge
of these AI systems that are being built,
that AI ethics and AI ethicists are hell-bent
on monopolizing them on Google.
And there's been a civil war going on
in the Google AI department for a while
and in many other places.
So this localization that you're saying politically,
which is absolutely the way,
it seems to be the absolutely the way for AI as well
to decentralize this development of AI
that even if it's going to lead to AGI,
which for example, Ben Goertzel believes
that we're gonna reach AGI in like 10 years, 15 years,
and he's building his singularity net because of that.
So AGI wouldn't be owned by them.
Yeah, I'm all in favor of that kind of an approach,
but it also begs the question
that how are we going to be decentralized
yet operating on the basis
of some kind of a point of alignment,
which goes back to the beginning of our conversation
that there are certain values
that define the identity of the perspective.
Exactly, and I do think that that's one of the things
that Ben's not taking into account.
It's kind of funny, he was at Oxford for a conference.
He did like the AGI conference,
global conference was at Oxford while I was there.
And I got to go out and have a couple of beers with him
and with Dave Hansen as well, who-
His partner.
Hansen Robotics.
Yeah, yeah, they do a lot together.
They're very like, they're friends.
They're like honest friends too.
They were very interesting guys as well.
I had met Dave Hansen before actually
at the Harrison Institute.
He was doing some work on BINA-48,
one of the first like robots that he worked with.
Martin Rothblatt.
Yes, yes, exactly.
And so I was there, it's in Vermont.
So it was actually not far from where I was living
at the time and got to meet them and talk to them.
And they have a very utopian view,
which in a way I like their positivity,
but I do worry that sometimes positivity can lead to naivety.
And I like the idea of if there is going to be an AGI,
it needs to be decentralized because any centralization,
like I said before, right, is prone to issues.
And just like AOC wouldn't want Trump in charge of the AGI,
I wouldn't want AOC in charge of the AI, right?
You don't have enough natural intelligence, I sure as hell
don't want you to have the artificial one.
And that's something I think that's interesting.
And you mentioned Google, for example,
and Google's big issue in AI ethics recently, right,
hasn't even been, you know, should we build this?
They just kind of build it and then move on.
There has been some issue with DeepMind.
DeepMind doesn't want to be part of Google anymore.
And I'm very interested to know more about why that is,
but not much has come out about it,
except for the fact that they asked
to basically be spun out.
But the biggest AI issue in Google recently
hasn't been mass surveillance, hasn't been data protection,
hasn't been data ethics, the right to be forgotten
or any of these other things.
It was Geberu, it was, you know,
the fact that one of their AI researchers was,
who has done actually really good work too, by the way,
like I'm not trying to throw her under the bus.
I have a lot of respect for some of the work she's done,
but she did not want to go through a peer reviewed process,
right, and she said, if you don't,
if I can't go around this peer review, then I'm resigning.
And Google said, we accept.
And she said she was fired.
No, she was not fired.
She resigned, she gave them the ultimatum
and they called her bluff, I guess.
But the fact of the matter is that
that was in a nutshell, right?
It's better to be morally right than factually correct.
Exactly.
That's what that was,
is I don't want to put myself up for critique
to be shown factually correct,
which is bizarre to me, right?
Because one of the findings that like Geberu
and some of the colleagues
that work on those problems have found, right,
has to do with like things like gender and racial biases
in AI and they've mathematically proven
without a shadow of a doubt that biases exist
in the way that they've presented them.
You can't deny, like it's just, it's mathematically provable.
It's undeniable that those biases exist.
And so for me, it's like, look,
that it aligns with her ideology.
She does go more towards the woke side.
And I think that that's fine, right?
If there's a systemic bias in our AI,
we need to either address it
or know that it exists and be comfortable with it.
And if we're not comfortable
with certain racial or gender biases,
many of them there personally,
I'm not comfortable with them.
I'd like to see them.
I'd like to see us understand how we can address them
rather than just going in and addressing them.
I think we need to raise those questions,
but saying either you stop asking me these questions
or I quit, that's not something that I think is very helpful.
Just criticizing the high priest,
like exactly what we're talking about.
Yeah, right.
You can't, or ex-communication befalls you, right?
And I think this is exactly the kind of thing
that worries me about the fact that most AI developers
and most people making big decisions in AI ethics
come from, I'm not so much worried about left, right,
so much as I'm worried about woke, the woke ideology.
People will always be more left or more right.
And it's largely a meaningless designation anyways, right?
Because for me, I know people who are really far left,
but they're also anti-authoritarianists.
And I actually get along really well with them
because fundamentally, I kind of agree with them
because they're anti-authoritarian.
So whatever nonsense they might believe that I disagree with,
they're not gonna force it on me.
And so I'm like, all right, that's cool.
You do you, I'll do me.
And the same with people who are on the far right,
that are further right than I am.
I, you know, so long as they're not authoritarian,
I'm okay, it's just a disagreement.
But the moment they go, oh,
and I think you should do this too, I get worried.
And a lot of the people who are on the AI side
are also saying, and here's what I believe,
I've designed AI to try and mimic what I believe,
and I'm going to force this AI to force you
to conform to my beliefs.
And the biggest way that that is,
that's instantiated today, I think,
is in censorship on social media.
For example, I mean, and some of these are horrendous, right?
So for example, not being able to even discuss the laptop,
Hunter Biden's laptop right before the election.
And oh, it was a bombshell to manipulate the election.
It was like, yeah, and the entirety of the media
before then was, you know, no blood on anyone's hands
on trying to support a candidate before then,
that's when it started, right?
It's nonsense.
Now, all the people who came out,
retired people from intelligence communities
who signed that letter that this is Russia propaganda.
So what's going to happen to those people?
You know, this is a problem.
Is there going to be any recourse to that?
I mean, but when you look at what happened
with the original Russia game, right?
I mean, so much of that was shown to basically,
and basically in the end, when they investigated it,
the Democrats, you know, the opposition
looked just as bad or worse than Trump and his crowd.
If anything, I think it made Trump look rather inept.
You know, not this grand conspirator.
He was not the wizard of Oz here.
You know, he was not the man behind the green curtain.
If anything, he was kind of, you know,
the tin man sitting around waiting for everybody else.
Meanwhile, you see people like, you know,
Hillary Clinton in the background in her campaign,
trying to pull all of these little levers,
and the further we dug into it, the further it looked like
this was just a lot of nonsense on all sides,
but this media narrative became unbreakable, right?
It became like, Russia game became like blue anon.
It was just like the Democrats' version of the conspiracy
that the further left you go,
the more you find it to be an unassailable truth.
And it was, yeah, it was really,
it was really worrying, I think, to see that.
I think, you know, there's a case for moderation
to be made when we look, and I mean moderation,
like moderating our own behaviors
and supports towards social media.
When you look at the fact that they don't allow us
to speak about certain things because of a political agenda,
and then they tell us they're apolitical,
it's like, don't, you know, don't tell me that.
Like, it's obviously not true.
Just be honest, if you're gonna be away,
just be honest about it.
Just be honest about it so that I know
not to use your social media platform
if you're not gonna allow me
to participate in a conversation.
And I think, you know, you mentioned earlier, right?
That having the conversation is critical to democracy
and people just don't even know about the AI that exists
and the problems with social media.
One of the reasons for this
is a very suspicious event that happened, right?
When Frances Howigan, who previously worked for Facebook,
released all of these documents as a whistleblower,
she releases all of these documents.
It goes onto the Wall Street Journal.
She ends up appearing before the Senate
and all of this stuff.
When those documents were released,
they were going viral across several social media channels,
but they weren't going viral
on the largest social media channels
basically in the world, right?
Facebook, WhatsApp, and Instagram,
because all three of those companies
are all owned by Facebook.
Now, since the revelation, right?
Now they change their name to Meta
and not Facebook anymore.
So they're all three being accused
or it's being demonstrated
that they knew that they were bad for society.
They knew that they were being politically manipulative
and politically manipulated by external forces.
And instead of going viral on Facebook,
all of the Facebook servers just shut down
for, you know, what was it?
Eight, 12 hours.
Now, any social media researcher will tell you
that when hot news breaks,
the first six to 12 hours after it's posted
is critical to determining the amplitude, right?
How high it will go.
It'll go a little viral,
but is it gonna go three million viral
or is it gonna go three billion viral?
And that Francis Howgood news had the possibility
to go three billion accounts viral
across all of the different social media channels.
But it didn't happen.
And the reason it didn't happen
is because somebody made a coding error at Facebook
at exactly the right time.
And all of those servers mysteriously went down
for an unrelated reason.
And it's like, come on.
And you see that they'll give you a slap on the wrist
for questioning about Hunter Biden,
but they will shut the whole farm down
if it makes them look bad
and it exposes what they've knowingly been doing for years.
Yeah, so more liberty, less secrecy,
more transparency, less secrecy,
more decentralization, less centralization.
A hundred percent, man.
The world's weird and chaotic.
Let's love it.
Yeah, absolutely, absolutely.
Yeah, right with it.
Unfortunately, we're reaching the end
because your time is limited
and I really appreciate this conversation.
It was awesome.
Let me ask you the last question I ask all my guests.
If you come across an intelligent alien
from a different civilization,
what would you say is the worst thing humanity has done
and what would you say is their greatest achievement?
What is the worst thing,
like single event that humanity has done?
Or something we built,
worst and best in humanity.
The worst and best in humanity.
Okay, that's a hard one to answer.
That's a good question.
So for me, I think that the worst of humanity
has been embodied historically
and the biggest threat to humanity
is also the biggest threat to humanity in the future.
And that is Marxism.
That as a ideology, what it's done, right?
It saddens me.
And then I live in a post-communist country now, right?
So the Iron Curtain is like 20 minutes from here.
I can walk along the Iron Curtain
and they have names of people
who were literally eaten alive by dogs
for trying to cross the Iron Curtain
and just get to Austria to get to their freedom.
And I've lost track of the number of people
that I've spoken to here
that were smuggled out as children to freedom in the West.
And so having learned about it is one thing,
but then having heard the stories of people
who have lived through it here in Slovakia.
And as I learned the Slovak language,
I can talk to the older generation, right?
Who couldn't learn English, right?
And I get to hear their stories and stuff.
And that is, I think, that's our darkest moment,
I think, is Marxism and communism.
And it's still today.
Our greatest achievement, our greatest achievement, man,
in a way, I would say that our greatest achievement
as a species was probably, is probably the internet.
Yeah, I would say our greatest achievement is the internet.
Our finest hour is this massive technological
ridiculousness that is both beautiful and it's energy
and it's complicated and it's complicated
beautiful and it's energy and it's communication.
And my hope is that we realize that no matter
what it is we create as people,
and no matter how beautiful something
like our greatest technologies are,
nothing is ever going to be better or more beautiful
than just walking out in the woods
with your friends and loved ones
and actually turning the phones off
and sitting around a bonfire.
That would be it.
So maybe my other answer, if I can have two,
is the greatest achievement humans ever had
was figuring out how to light a fire.
That's, I'll keep it with that.
Beautiful.
Awesome.
Thank you.