I would offer, actually the World Wide Web is our greatest achievement of the technology
that makes self-expression possible and collaboration.
I think it's instigated a renaissance across the world, it's amazing.
And in a sense, it's only getting started, so ask me 10 years from now and I'll say the
successor for the web, whatever that is.
Hello, this is Agah Bahari and I am here with the first episode of Neo Human.
I will be talking to interesting people about interesting subjects.
We don't have any specific subject or title or style for the podcast, whatever happens,
it's just going to be interesting.
That's the most important thing.
For the first episode, right here with me, we have David McFadden, who is a lead engineer
at Synaptic, which is a Toronto-based technology company.
Synaptic.
Horrible.
I asked you the name before the show too.
So what do you do at Synaptic and what does Synaptic do?
Yeah, Synaptic is a startup that's about almost four years old now and we build technology
to mainly assist neurosurgeons in difficult brain surgery.
So we have a line of products to look at the scans from the brain and render them in 3D
and help the surgeon plan the surgery in advance.
And then in the OR, our software acts sort of like a GPS for surgeons, it's like Google
Maps to show them where they are and help her along in their route.
And if they get off course, they can get back on with the 3D map of the brain.
And this is usable with robotics and with human doctors, both can use it.
Because I remember you were saying that you have a robotic arm at the work.
That's right.
I'm the lead software engineer on our robotic arm project.
It's a device positioning system that's designed to assist the surgeon.
So it's holding the optics for the surgery, which is the lighting and the camera and a
microscope and it's recording video.
And the robotic arm automatically positions the optics of the cameras into ideal positions
for the surgeon.
They just have to make a gesture that they want it in some particular place and press
a foot pedal and the robotic arm will move the optics into the correct position.
That's amazing.
How long did it take from, if you know, from the concept idea of such a thing to being
at this level that you guys are, which I believe you're ready to be launched?
It launched last February.
Yeah, from concept to when it was FDA approved and actually used in our real surgery was
less than two years.
Oh, wow.
That's amazing.
And you still consider the whole company as a startup.
Like you're not a corporation per se.
We're in transition now since we got FDA approval last February and we're deployed now.
We're out in the field at, I think, eight or nine different installations now, different
hospitals around the United States.
And it's to date in the last eight months or so since it's heard, it's been used in
500 real surgeries.
That's amazing.
What do you think is, I'm an enthusiast entrepreneur, I have to say.
Like I'm very interested in creative ideas and then implementing those ideas.
And with computers and coding, it's never really been easier, I think, to make an idea
from ground up with a very limited number of people.
That's very true.
Yeah.
What do you think the effect of such technologies in our, because the company that you're explaining
is a very specific company to doing very specific thing, how do you think those technologies
will translate into a popular or mainstream consumer to be able to take advantage of that?
For example, let's say this is just off the top of my head.
Would there be a possibility of mixing this technology or would you see the possibility
of mixing this technology with a very straightforward variable like the EEG variables that exist
right now that assist you to meditate?
I think they're also a company from Toronto, eMUSE or MUSE, I think.
Right.
I think we actually used MUSE at a hackathon that we did internally at Synaptiv a couple
months ago and using the MUSE will detect brainwaves of some sort and encode them in
a way that a software can take advantage of.
So one of the demos was to move the robotic arm just by thinking about it.
Wow.
It was amazing.
I bet.
Yeah.
So we're definitely looking at new consumer electronics to bring that into the OR to help
the surgeons, stuff like the Oculus Rift or the Microsoft HoloLens to give the surgeon
a heads up display and show them the 3D rendering of the brain as if he was living in that space.
That's amazing.
You would imagine this also, beside the surgery itself for training, this is a very great
achievement the way that you don't necessarily have to experiment on even like animals for
a lot of stuff that are going on inside there.
When we want to test their brain pulses or anything, instead of doing it on the animal,
it will be able to done in a virtual space in the virtual brain.
Yeah, definitely.
You can see this in the Microsoft promotional material for the HoloLens and the early demos
are in the classroom where a teacher is showing the kid's solar system or whatever and the
kids have whole lenses and the solar system is right there in the classroom with them
and animated and interactive.
Or games.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's just unbelievable.
Another use that this kind of technology has had in past couple of years has been a military
and they've done it for good and for evil per se even though it might be necessary evil.
But the technology has been used to treat PTSD very seriously and they've had very successful
results from it.
Where do you see the future of that technology with that assistance are going and how does
technology as a whole will play a bigger and bigger role in the army and the military industry
complex?
We see with the rise of drones, it has been, I dare say, almost a decade now.
Where do you see this whole thing is going with?
Because we are not going to stop fighting, the war is going to continue and I think the
difference would be that we will have less casualty because technology is covering most
of the ground that people had to do before.
Where do you see this whole thing going with the usage of technology and its dependence
to advance technology?
Well, in the military particularly, I think the trend is to push more and more computational
power down to the ranks and replacing humans with automation.
Obviously, it's much safer for their side, but they're going to run into a pretty significant
ethical decision probably really soon about giving autonomous drones the power to kill
or the right to kill.
Would you think that they will announce that they're about to do that or they'll just do
it until they get caught?
Looking from recent events, I think probably the latter, we'll find out about it on WikiLeaks.
Yeah, I think so.
It's been amazing.
I think it's a great achievement of technology that you can go in a small room in Arizona
and control a drone in Afghanistan and drop a bomb because of course, it's not resulting
always in good.
Sometimes it does and there are some people that need to be killed and that's the only
way and I much rather a drone will kill them than a soldier on our side basically being
put in risk to deal with a Taliban leader or whoever.
But at the same time, you see how people are treating, for example, even driverless cars.
There are already a lot of people freaked out about it.
People are freaked out about drones, use of mainstream drones.
You see these conspiracy theorists that have YouTube channels and iTunes podcasts and all
of that.
They're talking about shoot the drones down with your shotguns and all the people who
are very concerned about these kind of thing conspiracies.
How do you think the challenge that technologists and technology enthusiasts have who are between
two sides, one being the politics and politicians and the other being people who are basically
always scared of a new thing.
That new thing has to be proven many, many times and more and more people using it for
masses to accept the usage of that.
How do you think it will result and will it slow the advancement down or slow it down
or speed it up?
I think the way it will actually play out is we'll see some significant pushback initially
because it is a big change, but it's also fairly inevitable that this is going to happen.
It reminds me of David Brin's Transparent Society where surveillance becomes pervasive
and that could have actually net positive effects on society as we've already seen
with the way the police in the US have reacted to their cameras.
All of a sudden, police are getting caught all the time and I think it's changing the
way they behave.
They're becoming more ethical in their professional behavior now.
Yeah, it's like a double-edged sword because it's become more transparent for the authorities
to control that, but at the same time, general population also are seeing it more.
They do believe that it's happening more.
Once it reaches some critical threshold, I think it will just become accepted like cell
phones have become accepted.
There was pushback initially about those two.
People were just walking down the street talking to themselves that looked weird, but now it's
so calm and nobody looks twice.
It's just accepted.
Also virtual reality, I think, will have a lot to do with that because people would have
the possibility to be whoever they want physically.
Like on the game Second Life, that you can create your own avatar and live in that.
People get married, people buy stuff.
Sweden, I heard, has an embassy in that virtual world.
Nike has a store.
So I think it will begin with this is weird that people are doing because people will
do that and film it and put it on YouTube to create a community and find like-minded
people and it's amazing that we can do that all around the world now.
But at the same time, you freak certain people out, the people who watch Fox News and all
those propaganda, basically.
Those people are not that much of a concern, I agree, but we hear also from someone like
Elon Musk and Bill Gates and Steve Wozniak who are, I don't want to say scaring people.
They're smarter than that.
They're making a very valid case of dangers of artificial intelligence.
But at the same time, I think these kind of warnings, even though necessary, it will lower
the budget that research facilities can have to actually work on it because if public opinion
is not behind an idea, it would be very hard to finance.
It's like, you know, I have a very good idea for a startup, but I probably not going to
have more than 10 users.
Nobody's going to fund me.
Right.
Yeah, we saw the same thing happen with prediction markets a few years ago.
Robin Hanson was ready to roll out a prediction market that would help with public policy.
And one of the questions that they were interested in betting on was the chance of a terrorist
event.
But some senators got a hold of this information and ran a scare campaign saying it would be
terrible to bet on these sorts of things because one side has to bet on it happening, which
could be seen as promoting it in some sense.
It was a silly reason anyways, but the point is that it turned public opinion and the project
was abandoned.
Do you blame that senator or you blame the people who voted that senator into Senate?
I think they're all to blame.
Yeah.
One senator is one senator, has to be thousands of people at least behind him.
And I think that's one of the greatest revelations in the United States, Donald Trump running
for presidency because you see everybody who's behind him.
It's a very interesting phenomenon.
Yeah.
It's only only one person predicted that.
Who did?
Who was that?
God Adams, the creator of Dilbert.
Really?
Seriously.
He said Donald Trump will run for president.
He said that Donald Trump will continue to lead in the Republican polls long before anyone
else even considered that possibility.
Everyone else thought he was a joke and that he was popular initially because it was funny,
but that's actually not the case.
Now, what's very interesting is that they were reading the polls, not polls really,
but how much time media is covering Donald Trump in comparison to the other people.
It's twice as much as Hillary Clinton, the time that Trump is getting, and I think 13
times more than Bernie Sanders.
What Trump understands is how to manipulate media to his advantage.
Absolutely.
And he knows that whoever has name recognition is going to be highest in the polls.
It's such a great transition though, because with reality shows become more popular in
the United States.
And the celebrity culture, I had this conversation with somebody else that I was like, celebrities
became the idols, the greatest thing that you can be in the 21st century.
And she was saying that, no, people were celebrities before that.
But I was like, no, not like this, that you use, for example, Bono from YouTube for any
humanitarian campaign that you have to get attention from people.
That's not the cause that is getting the attention of the people.
It's a celebrity.
And then by the rise of that, and now you see a person who's a creator of a reality
show and is an apprentice, Miss Universe, all those things.
Nobody knows better than him how to manipulate the media, as he said.
And I mean, it's appealing to most people, I think because he's not getting any money
from big corporations and CPACs and nobody.
Right.
He's posing as the outsider.
He is above corruption.
And the thing that I think people most find appealing is he speaks his mind.
He doesn't care what people think about what he says.
I mean, he goes to extremes to make that point.
Do you think he believe a lot of?
No, I think he does that in order to get media attention.
I think so, too.
I'm at this point, as we had this conversation before, I'm a Bernie Sanders supporter.
And I think it would be very good for America to have a change in that direction.
It's a very extreme change.
We were a capitalist, but now we are being run by a Jew, liberal, socialist.
It would be a very good change.
In my opinion.
But if he drops out, I'm supporting Donald Trump because I think he does not believe
a lot of stuff that he says.
You cannot possibly be that blind and make it that far.
I think in a city like New York City and Hillary Clinton, I have no interest in her.
No, I think Hillary would just be a continuation of Obama, which turned out to be just a continuation
of W. Bush, surprisingly, against all odds, against everyone's wishes.
Is it really a surprise?
Because one man in a democracy doesn't supposed to be able to change anything.
You have to go.
So it's a democratic system that is backstabbing itself, in my opinion, because the party's
rhetorics against each other, and one person who's being elected as somebody who you can't
use as a punching box, you know, punching bag, I don't think he can do much.
Well perhaps not, but you'd expect him to push in the directions of his promises when
he's actually gone in the other direction.
I think the good things that he did, I'm not really sure about the healthcare system, because
apparently it's one of those things you have to live in the US to experience, that I heard
good things and bad things about Obamacare from different people who I respect their
opinions.
I think when he made it legal for same-sex marriages to become federal, I think that
was a good thing.
And I still think he will do more in this last year.
I'm not an Obama fan at all.
In the second term, in the first term when he was running, I was totally supporting John
McCain.
And then John McCain elected Sarah Palin as vice president, like, why would you do that?
Like it's such a weird thing.
That was bizarre.
Yeah, they made a really cool movie about it, Woody Harrelson, isn't it?
I can't remember the name.
But it's about that era of Sarah Palin, it's based on a book with Sarah Palin's advisor
after the campaign was over, he wrote, and it was a disaster with her.
But again, she's one person, there are thousands of people who are supporting her.
She's still, apparently, making the most money in the conservative charities and conservative
fundraisers.
I mean, who knows, it's really strange.
You think the new government of Canada will have any effect in the social life of Americans
in a way that this is a liberal government?
We pulled out of Syria in the first week that, you know, he became a prime minister.
And then we started getting refugees, even though the numbers are not comparable with
what Europe is doing.
And that we can talk about.
I fully expect the Trudeau's government to be kind of an example for Americans to show
what's possible.
Yeah.
Other than the ridiculous choices they have now, it's, I mean, it's sad.
It's I don't know, me and my girlfriend, we have this conversation, she's a big supporter
of Hillary Clinton, because she also has worked for Hillary Clinton.
And she was very impressed with her as a boss, she's a smart person.
She brought technology in a very involved way into State Department.
And she's a defender of women rights.
But then you watch a lot of different stuff that's been put together, how she has flip
flopped from time to time.
And then you wonder, you know, is this really the best that United States of America can
offer as a candidate for presidency?
Like there's nobody else.
My favorite candidate would be Eric Schmidt of Google.
Okay.
Because they are obviously smarter than anybody who's running, you know, for president, politicians.
But unfortunately, we are kind of taken hostages by lawyers, it seems like Neil deGrasse Tyson
was also saying that you look at the Congress and Senate, the lawyer, lawyer, lawyer, businessman,
lawyer, lawyer, businessman, where are the scientists, where are the engineers?
In Europe.
I mean, the Europeans don't have the same problem with their politicians, they actually
have academics and politics.
Which they should.
They should.
You'd expect.
Yeah.
But no, it's, it's, I mean, a lot of good news is coming from the West in the sense
that countries with innovation, you know, the first world countries, but at the same
time, you see a lot of nonsense is also coming out of them.
Look at Europe, the problem that they have now with the refugee crisis and what happened
in Germany, which I'm sure you know about in the New Year's Eve, it just kind of makes
it worse.
And already, I think people are completely ignoring them.
Under the radical right, who are, they're rising very powerful in decades.
You can say in Germany, in Greece, in France, in Finland, in Sweden, you see people who
were national socialists and they couldn't even breathe really in a political spectrum
in those countries.
There, they have a lot of supporters now and the extreme right group in Germany, Pegida,
they had a, they had a rally here in Ottawa and there are videos on YouTube that day around
the streets and there are also people who are countering them who are anti-racism and
all of that.
Where do you, where do you see this whole social conflict is going?
From what I understand, the attacks in Cologne, New Year's Eve were actually suppressed, news
of the attacks was suppressed by the government because they were afraid it would fuel kind
of anti-immigration sentiment on the right.
And then the mayor.
But as soon as the news came out, it made it much worse because now the socialist governments
are protecting the bad actors.
That's right.
And that's not the side you want to be on.
No.
And the mayor of Cologne, the mayor basically blamed the women.
Right.
Yeah.
They kept the man at the arm length only, what are you talking about?
Like, do you flip this easily?
Like what did it take?
And my understanding is that they're getting 1 million, 1 million plus refugees into Germany.
This is not going to go away, this problem, because then they're going to push for them
to become citizen faster so they can vote for that party.
That's my thinking.
They have the same thinking about abortion and people who are against it, that they don't
care about that baby, they just care about one more Christian and one more Muslim or
one more whatever.
It's a number.
And the fact that they're committing suicide, I think, in Europe for the sake of their own
political game and agenda.
Yeah, it looks ironic from the outside observer.
Yeah, for sure.
And as you're saying, Europeans, they master a lot of things much faster than Americans.
They already, as you said, have academics and scientists and their political system
are completely involved, but at the same time, you see the openness in the European way and
multiculturalism in the European way that they promoted, for example, in England is
causing a lot of problem right now.
See all those Muslim British or British Muslims who joined the terrorist group ISIL in the
Middle East.
A lot of them are British.
The guy who was born and raised in Britain, yeah, like they went to school.
Sometimes in BBC, they're talking to people who knew them when they were a kid.
The guy, Jihadi John, who who just got assassinated like two weeks ago, he was replaced by another
British guy.
And they right away find out who he was.
And he was one of the people who are very closely related to excuse me, to the Islamic
extremists.
Anjum Chowdhury, I don't know if you know him, is like a preacher for extreme Islam in London
and completely protected by the government, is getting paid by the government.
But that guy who I had seen before in the documentaries about them, now he joined ISIL
and he became a new Jihadi John.
He just released the video is like very surreal.
I think it's really interesting to see the recent backlash against these progressive
values, the ones that are protecting the terrorists.
In fact, there's a new term for them, the regressive left.
That's right.
They're the ones that are attacking Sam Harris and his colleagues for actually addressing
the problem.
So Glenn Greenwald and Ben Affleck, of course, and Bill Marshall, calling Sam a racist for
saying that this is actually an issue.
Yeah, I hope that we come to rationality and smart thinking in a way that we don't really
have to get our facts from Ben Affleck, for example.
Because the other side of his story, who at that occasion was Sam Harris, he's more than
qualified to talk about any of those things.
He has studied it, he's a philosopher and a neuroscientist, and he's been writing and
talking about these issues for a while, for a long time.
Since he published The End of Faith.
Absolutely.
And I think 9-11 was a horrible thing, but in a way, a lot of good came out of it in
a sense that people like Sam Harris, people like Richard Dawkins, Christopher Hitchens,
Douglas Morey, these people started targeting what the problem really, they think, is.
And I agree with them completely.
Do you think there would have been no God Delusion published if not for 9-11, or End
of Faith, or Dennett's breaking the spell, or you think those were all a result of 9-11?
I think so.
Possibly, yes.
Earlier in the podcast, you said something that triggered this odd idea.
We were talking about elections and Trump, and in the context of Trump, you immediately
brought up reality shows.
And it just made me wonder, what if the elections are a reality show, and have been since, say,
JFK debated Nixon in 1960 on TV, that was the first televised debate, what if the election
has been a reality show ever since?
What if?
And the winner gets to rule the free world for four years.
Yeah.
It could be, I guess.
I think everything is possible.
But the question would be, who is producing the reality show?
Who is okaying it?
Maybe it's the media.
Let's see.
Let's follow the money.
There's a lot of spending in elections.
Where does that money go?
I would imagine mostly goes to media.
Some lobbyists, maybe, to shift the position.
Elections are all about advertising.
That's right.
So advertisers.
Yep.
They're running the federal election reality show.
Yeah, that's awesome.
Well, you're right by saying that let's follow the money and see where it leads, because
everything is basically money.
Well, that's been Bernie Sanders' main complaint, this election cycle, isn't it, that the big
business owns the politicians?
I think that's absolutely true.
The politicians are absolutely corrupt.
It's special interests that control legislation.
That's been proven statistically.
Yes.
That makes a lot of sense.
So he offers a solution to add even more legislation to prevent this sort of thing, but that's
might make it worse.
That just adds more regulations to be subject to regulatory capture.
It's just a bigger government.
The more power the government has, the more value there is in controlling it.
Right.
That's absolutely true.
Jeremy, what's his family name?
He wrote a book, Future Money, and our friend Nicola interviewed him too, which he's talking
about.
Rifkin?
Rifkin.
Yes.
Jeremy Rifkin.
Thanks.
A zero margin society.
How do you think that kind of a society will affect this money talks in a way that, let's
say, more and more human resources being replaced by machines.
So you don't have to pay them salary.
You don't have to pay for their...
You don't have to pay...
Is this the argument that robots are going to put everyone out of work?
That money will have no value, basically the end of capitalism.
That's the idea.
There will be no money in this way.
But is there still value in this society?
Value is a concept?
Will people value one thing over another?
Will they value living in one place over another?
Will they value seeing somebody talk or seeing some show more than another?
You know what they were saying that in the past 20 years, apparently, a trend has begun
that a newer generation, younger generation, they're not buying houses anymore, they rent.
A lot of people go to college, but a lot of people don't go to college because it's a
very big bet.
I went to film school and I still have not paid my student loan fully.
So you think about, because when you spend money, it's about a business, am I making
the right investment?
Am I going to get anything back from it?
That just adds to it.
It's like buying a house, it's like you have a mortgage before even you graduated.
So more and more people are shifting, I think, towards individualism.
And I think this is actually a time that Ayn Rand is going to get big again.
More and more people will be interested in objectivism and think about yourself.
But isn't staying away from mortgages and renting instead just a shift from long-term
investment to short-term flexibility?
I don't know.
I'm confused about how you derive some trend towards individualism from that.
It's not from that.
I think it's just an observation about our social life.
In early 90s, you would see boomboxes and a group of people gathering around it and
walking on the street under a shoulder.
One person has a boombox on the shoulder and like five, six other people walking with them.
People were talking more to each other.
You don't have to talk to anybody literally anymore.
Yeah, I'm with you.
I'm not saying it in the way that even if it was like old days, I'm not a fan of that
at all.
But I think it is more about it's less dependent on a group, which I think is a good thing
when you have Instagram and the culture of selfie.
For example, why is it that big, you think?
That's a mystery to me.
People have been a fan of it since it's crazy.
It's one of those things that begun with being able to take a photo of yourself and see yourself
with a phone and selfie has begun.
It's just a no-brainer.
But Kim Kardashian has a book of selfies.
I don't know if you know about that.
I did not.
Yeah, full of selfies.
But thanks for telling me.
So I don't think it's a bad thing.
I think we're dependent less on group.
Maybe you could look at these selfie trends as kind of an artistic expression.
I'm all for having online avatars and having many of them.
I consider none of them are identical to me.
They're crafted or designed by me for specific purposes and specific communities.
I've got a social one on Facebook.
I've got a very professional one on LinkedIn.
And every different community I'm in, I have a different persona for that community.
And I don't really worry about privacy very much because I only enter the data for that
persona that I want to be associated with that persona.
Mostly I'm not concerned about that at all.
And I think people are freaking out about something that hasn't existed in many, many
years.
It's like, there was a really cool interview with Larry Ellison.
I watched it on YouTube.
Oracle.
Yeah.
And they're talking about NSA and the effect of that.
And he's like, do you know who before NSA had all your information?
Credit card companies.
Right.
And there was an article, I think MIT publication too, about how privacy has died.
And it's a very new thing.
And it has died already.
How people have always favored comfort and accessibility to privacy.
But people are making a huge deal out of it.
And at the same time, Facebook does that.
Google does that.
Don't use them then.
Right.
Exactly.
And if you want to keep something private, I think it's your responsibility to encrypt
it or use secure channels.
I agree.
Technology is the solution.
Absolutely.
It's your responsibility to learn new ways to protect yourself and your information.
I feel the same way about when they're saying Google is selling our information.
So that's not a good thing.
Google is not charging you for anything.
So you can use anything and then that's their business model.
That's the cost of using Google.
Exactly.
So don't use it.
If it's too expensive, then don't.
Don't use Doc Doc Go or whatever else, which is pretty cool.
It's not Google.
I guess the opponents are mistaking these companies for charities.
The users are the product.
They're not really hiding that fact.
Absolutely.
They don't charge you.
They do charge their advertisers.
You are the product.
Absolutely.
And there's nothing wrong with that, I don't think.
That's your side of the bargain.
That's why you get all these great utilities.
This is where we are now.
And I see it in a way that from the time that man has sat in the cave and decided I want
to go outside, that's a decision that you made and everything else that can happen to
you outside of that cave are the alternative of that decision.
So don't leave if you don't want to deal with anything.
It's the same thing.
If you don't want to deal with these things, don't use internet.
People make the same thing about aging.
I think the age reversal, aging technology, there are a couple of organizations that were
working on it.
That's impossible.
If you take this, this is like one of the stupidest thing I've ever heard.
If you take death out of life, life has no meaning.
I've heard that a lot.
Yeah.
Maybe for you.
The meaning for me is that I want to live and not being stuck with being alive.
But I don't want to be stuck with dying either.
I want to have options.
And I'm seeing it in a way that when we get to a point that we can back up our brain inside
the machine, maybe one of me want to be backed up in the drop box of the future.
And then I just want to commit suicide because I want to know how that feels.
And then that version of me, my backup continues on like, oh, cool.
I don't even remember.
Yeah.
That might absolutely be possible if you have uploads.
Do you expect to see uploads within your lifetime?
Uh, it's very hard to say.
Like it's.
Yeah.
Also, you know, I guess if technology and science advance in a rate that they have been advancing
and no major thing happens, possibly.
But I, you don't really know, you know, I mean, it's, it's a crazy world.
The fact that it's funny when this whole ISIL thing began, began in Iraq, um, I was telling
my friends, this is a very good thing that it's a rock because if it was Pakistan, for
example, they have nuclear weapon, they would have nuclear weapon.
The game will be very different than, and now they're in Afghanistan.
You know, and I was watching a documentary about it today by frontline.
It's very good ISIS in Afghanistan.
Um, and they're saying a lot of Taliban, they're leaving Taliban to join ISIS because ISIS
pays $700 a month for each fighter.
Apparently that's a rate and that's a lot of money.
So they did, they joined them.
So when, so the Taliban is working with them where it's joining ISIS.
Now ISIS is fighting Taliban, but there are members of Taliban who've deserted Taliban
and they're continuing to do that because ISIS pays more.
That's the thing.
Also, do they think they want to join the winning side?
I would think that having a higher pay rate isn't going to help if you're on the losing
side.
Well, I mean, I don't know because, um, well, ISIS, at the same time, it's very hard to
kind of imagine what would a Taliban know information wise, like it's very difficult
to judge because it's the opposite side of the side that we are on and watching the news
and conceiving the news for that Taliban.
The problem as they're explaining is that we don't need ISIS because we already have
Islamic government under Taliban.
But then they're making the argument.
Some of the Taliban who desert because it's just a religion filled with loopholes.
I was like, no, it says in the Koran that, um, when there is a, um, caliphate, which
is like, um, what the, the States Islamic state, then you have to join that like it's,
it's an obligation for you.
So with all these insane people around the world, if they get ahold of some serious weapon,
they can cause a massive pause to this whole thing.
At the same time, they might speed things up.
You know, uh, this like Manhattan project, you know, uh, it was because of war that we
build not we were Americans built, uh, west allies builds nuclear weapon, nuclear bomb.
And then again, it was because of war that we went to the moon cold war.
And then it stopped and we haven't gone back to the moon or anywhere else.
And we are started doing it now, maybe because Chinese are getting there too.
They said they're going to land the man on the moon 2020 or something like that, which
is not even comparable.
And I like the Chinese system, but I much rather speak in English and deal with the
Chinese system.
I think Chinese have figured out their country so well and mixed two different systems together
so well.
And they're so strict about it that they've been getting China to where it is now.
But at the same time, China has became a bubble because it has a very small percentage of
really, really rich people now.
And then you go to central China and all those farmlands and it's just like 16th century.
But they're the best capitalists in the world, I think.
But again, uh, like Vietnam now, um, you can hire people much cheaper than China, for example,
Philippines.
So a lot of businesses are going for clothing and stuff.
I know they go, it's, it's going to Vietnam.
It has been going to Vietnam for years now.
Um, but with less dependence on China, it also depends a lot on how we can improve our
manufacturing technologies in the West, in the West.
So 3d printing or machines running things, you know, um, I think they've, but they also
have a brain program, right?
Which Ben Goertzel is working with.
Who's the other guy?
Oh, right.
Um, Ben Goertzel means the brain in software or?
I know the guy who Ben Goertzel was working with, um, who's also in Ray Kurzweil's documentary,
he's, he has a very negative perspective about artificial intelligence, Hugo, Hugo
digress, yes, yes, and his art, artelict war, he sees a coming global violent war between
the humans and the AIs.
What do you think about that?
Well, it's certainly a possibility.
That's why, um, the machine intelligence research Institute exists.
That's why Elon Musk and Bill Gates and the other scientists have joined in, in raising
the issue around.
Do you think it's going to be, um, because it's like one of the biggest concerns that
makes sense as you explained that is there's a possibility that there will be conflict
in that way.
Do you think it will be between humans and machines or humans and human machine fusion?
This third thing, because I'm thinking if, if you have, for example, um, nanobots inside
your brain and you expand as a, you know, you evolve, right?
You become the third thing.
I think if there is a symbiosis between humans and AI, if every human has an AI partner or
a bunch of them, um, then that is a path to a safe future.
That's the best possible future, I think.
But wouldn't it be like the problem would be if there's a single AI that's not human
and not associated with any human that is competing with us for resources and it doesn't
necessarily have any values shared with us.
But like that's terrifying, but at the same time, wouldn't that represent the population
on earth right now?
Like I'm thinking, imagine a fundamentalist Christians would have their own AI.
It would be the projection of them.
Or you think the AI would have the ability to think...
I think the AI and the human together would be a new, greater entity.
Yes, that's exactly, exactly.
And it would, to other people or other agents, it would look like a single agent, but it's
actually a synthesis of the...
It's connected to the same network, basically, neural network.
Possibly.
Yeah.
Do you think they have to, though?
Like the way the Tesla machines, for example, they're communicating with each other now?
That again can bring up the privacy issue and all of that, because like the information
that my car has, I don't want to share it.
But if you don't want to share it, you wouldn't be able to take advantage of the full possibility
of that enhancement.
So same thing with AI, don't you think?
I always think of the same thing with open source, AI to reach its full potential, it
has to be open source.
Probably.
Yeah.
Its full potential, yeah.
What would be the other way?
The other way to what?
The other way to have a functional, superior, intellectually, artificial intelligence by
not having it open source.
What would be the other way?
Stay proprietary, company organization can keep it to themselves, just the way software
companies do already.
Well, source code is not open source.
Right.
You mentioned HoloLens and Oculus Rift.
We know that 2016 is the year that virtual reality will enter mainstream market.
At least the commercial early adopter market.
Yeah.
Well, it's been around for a couple of years now.
Just the development kits.
Yeah.
But it's become more accessible.
You can pre-order Oculus now.
I think it's 599.
Just as of now, just a couple days ago.
Which is awesome.
I was waiting for this version, Crescent Bay, because it has the headphones now.
All right.
For me, as an audio engineer and sound designer, this is amazing because this is the difference
between black and white and color TV to me.
When you can create virtual 360 sonic environments, which is a necessity for virtual reality worlds
to be believable, the sound has to be there.
It's just an amazing opportunity after years of just doing the same thing, basically.
How do you think virtual reality will start affecting, as you said, early adapters and
then how it's going to get into mainstream and how people will feel about it and what
do you think people will use it for and how it's going to change everything?
Well, for the first couple of years, at least, I think the major markets are going to be
in entertainment, probably mostly computer games.
The Rift is coming out packaged with the game EVE Valkyrie, a 3D space game, and the videos
that I've seen on YouTube are mind-blowing.
I cannot wait to try this out.
I'm a big fan of EVE anyways.
That's awesome.
This is going to be really interesting, but I think almost any 3D computer game is going
to lend itself to the Rift and the developers or the games are going to incorporate integration
points.
They'll support the Rift and other similar devices like the HTC.
And then what we'll see then is the price point is going to come down due to volume
and the next generation is going to be just like we've seen with smartphones.
Oh, absolutely.
I think it's smart.
I can't remember who said that.
Maybe Elon Musk said it years ago that always wait for the third generation of a technology
because by the time it gets to the third generation, it's working good enough and it's priced
well enough for everybody to use it basically.
It's a bit difficult to predict the next market after games, but I can see getting
into education easily and 3D movies.
Journalism also.
Yeah.
There's been a movie commissioned by Vice, Vice Media, that they made in Syria and it's
360.
I haven't seen it, but you can't imagine how big of a difference it makes when you're
in the middle of that environment to really feel it and get connected to it.
And also you take away the third, the middle man, because more and more I'm imagining when
citizen journalists, they start arising because of blogging and because of how easy you got
to take photos and videos and put it on YouTube and all those other websites, it will be possible
to make a 360 video quite soon.
I think.
I think it already is.
There is an iPhone app for them.
For 360 videos?
Oh, that's amazing.
I know 360 cameras because one of the biggest challenge back then when they were have to
put a couple of GoPro cameras like four or eight or 12 or something to get a 360 image.
The thing you had to put a lot of cameras and then the image that it was giving you
and to you needed to be stitched and the software to stitch those footage was very complex to
work with.
It was expensive.
But again, like any other technology, the first generation is basically the first step
in trial and error.
But now there are 360 cameras that they cost maybe like 400 bucks, the price of a GoPro
and it gives you already stitched image that you can use.
So somebody in Syria when they're in war and doing a video of, for example, whatever, a
rally or attack or a terrorist, a suicide bomber or something like that.
Of course, I will watch that over a footage that is being transcribed for me by CNN.
For example, it might be in the minority there.
Really?
How many people want to experience a suicide bomber?
I don't know.
I would imagine if I'm interested in what's going on there, I want to kind of feel it
to maybe it just gives you perspective, I think, in my opinion.
Yeah, I think it could definitely have a lot of value.
Maybe for films and TVs too or treatments of I know that they're using that there was
a video of this girl who was claustrophobic and she was so extreme that she couldn't take
elevators.
So they designed a game for her that was emulating her being inside the elevator and she trained
with that and she took an elevator for first year after who knows how many years and it
was amazing.
So in therapy, in treatment.
Yeah, absolutely.
PTSD.
They've been trying that.
I'm looking forward to that.
It's apparently one of the biggest products and technology in CES.
This year was also about virtual reality, everything about virtual reality.
So this is the year.
As a last question before my last standard question, which I will ask everybody, but
last question of series of question conversations that we've had.
How do you think ethics and morality will translate for an artificial intelligence?
Well, that's a pretty deep question.
One way to look at AI is it's a system designed to make choices based on its goals and beliefs.
An AI that's extremely smart, super intelligent, it will tend to have very accurate and sophisticated
beliefs.
The goals are basically beliefs about preferences, which states of the world are preferable to
other states of the world.
Can you even conceive what those beliefs will be?
Well, we can conceive of hard coding beliefs in such a way that the AI will be unable to
change its own goals, but at the same time that may very well cripple the AI in the sense
that it won't be able to get past certain level of sophistication or intelligence if
we cripple its ethical system.
So presumably if it's much smarter than humans.
Oh, absolutely.
As it should be.
We can't really expect to force our own morality per se on a machine that's supposed to be
much better and bigger and the evolution of us.
But that is exactly the project of friendly AI is to enforce our own values onto the AI.
Our values aren't that good.
We still lie.
It's a problem.
We don't.
We're not that good ourselves.
We are not.
We don't even know what would be good.
I mean, like we have no rigorous way of proving that any set of values is better than any
other set.
It's also very confusing to, for example, it's very interesting how it comes to you
when you talk about these kind of things with children because children have no filter and
they just ask you whatever that comes to their mind.
You can't tell a child that killing is wrong as a rule because then he or she will be asking
why those people are dying then.
Why, you know, you can tell them you just won't be very convincing.
Exactly.
And so you can't say it as a rule, right?
And that's like one of the biggest parts of morality, that killing is wrong.
This is just an example.
How are we going to explain that to an AI?
And that is one of the first things that we need to explain it now that we're talking
about as we spoke about it in military, that autonomous machine, okay, killing is wrong,
just wound people, you know, but if this guy did this, then killing is fine.
You can't really do that, you know?
And that's why I think a lot of these attempts because moralities are different from place
to place.
The morality that we have is a very different morality that, for example, people have in
Yemen, for instance.
And at the same time, the machine to get to its full potential, it needs to be open source.
So like Watson or IBM, it's open source.
So if you have a strong enough of a hardware, you would be able to have...
Are you sure Watson's open source?
I think so, because they were asking for programmers and programmers mainly to use Watson capability
and do their own projects.
But let's say an open source AI, it would be usable by some Chinese kid in his grandparent's
basement to build whatever he wants to build with it, or a Russian hacker, or a, you know,
or a evil person per se, evil quote unquote.
Yes, that's absolutely true.
Ben Goetzel has his own open source project, OpenCog, I think, and just a couple of weeks
ago, Elon Musk and some Peter Thiel, I think, and some other courts announced that they
were funding another open source project, OpenAI, and they were investing a...
Peter Thiel was involved in that, so I didn't know that.
I'm not sure, I think.
But I think they were putting something like a billion dollars into this project, significant
funding.
And at the same time, they came under quite a bit of criticism saying, if you think AI
is dangerous, why on earth would you open source it?
And the analogy is made with nuclear arms, if you think nukes are dangerous, you certainly
don't want to publish an easy how-to on the web, because it could easily fall into the
wrong hands.
So why are they doing it with AI?
What's the explanation?
I haven't heard their explanation.
One possibility is that unless you start looking into these issues right away, hardware is
going to be at a point sometime in the future that there might be an extremely quick ramp
up time from human level to superhuman level AI, and we won't be prepared.
So it's better to start now, even if it is dangerous.
To slow it down, basically.
Well, to be better prepared for when it happens.
Even if you end up spinging it up in some ways.
Would we know it when it happens, you think?
It depends how it is realized.
I think if it's a pure AI rather than, say, a human emulation where a brain is scanned
and then emulated in the hardware to get an AI.
If it's just a pure code AI, it could happen in a small group that's secret.
Maybe some company wants to build an AI to do trading on the stock exchanges in order
to make a lot of money, and it gets more and more intelligent.
Again, there's more and more data in order to interpret the financial data coming in,
so it builds up a belief system.
All it wants to do is make money, and it gets very good at trading and starts buying companies.
But doing it in a way...
That's a great idea for a movie.
But does it in a way that's decentralized, using lots of versions of itself, lots of
subsidiaries that can't be traced back to the main AI, so nobody realizes that it's
all controlled by a single mind until it owns so many resources it can take over countries?
Would you want to take over countries?
If it needs more resources.
If that's its main goal is to acquire resources, financial resources, it could become tremendously
powerful by controlling humans with its resources.
It could have a million people working for it, they don't even know that they're all
working for the same mind.
I think if the AI will be based on human morality, that's exactly what the AI would do.
He will go after the money.
Until it can build the hardware to make its own robots.
Yeah.
That's very interesting.
I think I've always enjoyed looking at things as much as I could as a double-edged sword
everything because they're good and bad, about literally everything, you know, with a hammer
you can build a house so you can bash somebody's brains.
So it really depends on how we're using it now, for what purpose we're using it.
And I think core values of us unfortunately have been corrupted a lot, a majority of people
because of the money-centric, money for the sake of money, materialistic money.
Whereas I see that as a positive force.
Yeah.
I do.
That people in the current system can protect their own interests better and advance their
own interests better by serving others commercially.
That's interesting.
So it channels their own personal interests.
Everyone is self-interested.
Even those that claim not to be I think are basically deluding themselves and others.
What they believe is...
But the way to channel that self-interest into a net good for society is to put in a
system where you do well by helping others, by selling them products and services, for
example.
That's so interesting.
Last night we were watching a documentary called I Am.
It's about this director named Tom Shaliak.
He directed a whole bunch of comedies and made millions and millions of dollars.
And then he went through this experience that he thought that he was going to die and then
he survived that and he became very...
Instead of making our objective profit to make it how we can help each other and help
each other grow.
And he was talking to his father and said, why can't we do that?
And his father said, it's a very nice utopian idea that will never ever happen.
I think the key is everybody started within themselves that you just make yourself a better
person and then try to get that understanding to the circle close to you and just expand
the circle more and more.
I think it would worth more to focus on what we can do individually than why people aren't
doing this and this and that because people are built from individuals.
But also, all these new technologies have given the opportunity and power to an individual
to change the world if they have a right idea.
Yeah.
Technology is making people more powerful every day.
I think it's great and it's a great time that we can live and enjoy all of these things.
The last question literally is, if you come in contact with a species from another civilization,
with alien per se, intelligent aliens, what would be the biggest achievement that you
would mention to that intelligent alien that we've made and we've achieved as a race?
And what would be the biggest mistake that we've made?
Wow.
Big questions.
I would offer actually the World Wide Web is our greatest achievement.
The technology that makes self-expression possible and collaboration.
I think it's instigated a renaissance across the world.
It's amazing.
And in a sense, it's only getting started.
So ask me 10 years from now and I'll say the successor for the web, whatever that is.
And as for our worst mistake, I think it's the war machines that we worship as our nation
states, that they've caused more death, destruction, and suffering than anything else in human
history.
And most people are blind to it, that they're proud citizens, they're proud of their nationality,
they're patriots, and they're brainwashed into thinking that this is a good idea.
I hope the aliens can shed some perspective on that.
I hope they've overcome it themselves and if they've come here, I'm pretty sure they
have destroyed themselves.
So one more thing, I want to thank you very much for having me as your first guest.
I'm really flattered.
Yeah, my pleasure, man.
And it's been a blast.
Yeah.
It's been excellent.
Glad to hear.
Thanks a lot.
You're welcome.
Thanks for having me.