up until now, human labor has been indispensable to the whole economy. But if in the future,
at least for a lot of people, it's not going to be so important that they work because
technology is going to take over more of this work, then we've got to shift our values a
little bit and be more open to providing an income to people that don't have traditional
full-time work in a way that we would expect today.
Hello and welcome to the 37th episode of Neo Human Podcast. I'm Agah Bahari, an agologist
on Twitter and Instagram, and you can follow the show on LiveInLimbo.com, iTunes, and YouTube.
With me today, I have Martin Ford. Welcome to the show, Martin.
Thanks for having me.
It's my pleasure. Why don't we start by some of your background, the works you've done,
and what you're focusing on mainly now these days?
Well, I've written two books, both of which are focused on the impact that robotics and
artificial intelligence are going to have on the economy and especially the job market.
I mean, the basic thesis of the books is that a lot of jobs are going to be automated. That's
something that's interested me for a while. I started out running a small software business
here in Silicon Valley. I started that back in the 1990s, and I saw even in that little
business the impact on jobs. It used to be that software was shipped on tangible media,
on CD-ROMs, and so there was work there for people to do the fulfillment to actually ship
that product to customers, but that disappeared very rapidly. That's one of the things I think
that got me really focused on this issue of this coming impact.
Back in 2009, I wrote my first book, which was called Lights in a Tunnel. That was self-published
but did well enough that eventually led to the opportunity to write my second book, Rise
of the Robots, which has gotten a lot more attention. That's how I got into this and
became really focused on this particular issue.
Because of personal experience, basically.
Yeah, and that and also, of course, working in the industry and being very close to Moore's
law to seeing what has happened with the acceleration of computing power. So, those two things together,
I guess.
Well, let's start from a very basic place. What is automation and how wide the impact
of automation is now and will be in the coming years and decades?
Well, automation is just any substitution of machines or computers for people in the workplace.
And of course, that's something that's been going on for hundreds of years since the Luddite
revolt. And certainly, within manufacturing, for example, it's already had a dramatic impact
in terms of making factories in developed countries like the United States much less
labor intensive. And that isn't new. What is new is that automation is now becoming
artificial intelligence. And what that means is that it's pushing into the cognitive realm.
So it's not just about machines that replace physical movements and manual labor anymore.
It's about machines that are getting better and better at displacing cognitive skills.
And most importantly, learning, our ability to learn and adapt, which is what all machine
learning is all about. Partly because of the acceleration that's been going on for such
a long time, we're now at a point where things are just moving at a dramatic pace. And we're
at the point where the machines are starting to think, at least in a limited way. And that's
going to be quite disruptive. Aside from technology, it seems like for centuries
we've had the mentality to skip the work we don't want to do by outsourcing it to others.
And it has resulted in the current civilization that we're living in. Would it be an accurate
assumption that the rise of automation is a natural continuation of that mentality and
approach? Sure. I mean, it's also driven by the market,
right? I mean, the market creates a very powerful incentive for any business to economize on
all its inputs, but certainly including it in that labor, which is for most businesses,
the biggest expense that they have. So yeah, you're right. It's a natural progression
of capitalism, really. And that, you know, so it's not anything particularly surprising.
It's just that the technology is finally providing capabilities that weren't there before.
And the consumers and workers who are being affected by it seems to be people who are
feeding data to this whole system to begin with, right? Because a lot of people, for
example, they complain about privacy, but they still share everything on Facebook and
they use their smartphone for many different aspects of their life. They're basically training
those artificial intelligence and workers in the factories, training those robots to
catch on the pattern and then just do it again and again and again and again and improve
upon it. Yeah, I mean, that's essentially right.
I mean, there's enormous amounts of data being collected, especially inside corporations,
big businesses. And in many cases, that data will include, will kind of encapsulate a lot
of jobs, you know, and so eventually a machine learning algorithm will be able to go through
that and figure out how to do a lot of things. And that's, you know, there's no easy way
to turn that around. I think that, again, that's a natural thing that's going to continue
to happen. So we have to figure out a way to adapt to all this, because it's going
to be, I think, quite disruptive. Exactly, because technology is advancing exponentially
while we seem to be hardwired to be linear. So do you think that at some point it will
be necessary for us biological humans to start merging with technology more and more just
so we can evolve with technology instead of being left behind?
Well, that's one of the, you know, the big ideas in Silicon Valley and people like Ray
Kurzweil and Peter Thiel and so forth certainly buy into that. I think that's absolutely true.
To some extent, that's natural. Of course, we're going to have technology that will enhance
us in many ways. Whether there's going to be this huge movement that will turn us all
into cyborgs or not, I don't know. I think that's very speculative, but certainly we're
going to incorporate more and more technology into ourselves. My view is that that won't
necessarily solve this problem of, you know, jobs disappearing. But I do think it's probably
an inevitable thing that's going to happen. How do you see humans evolving, if not into
cyborgs? Well, I mean, I think that we will either
remain relatively human and therefore it will be harder for us to keep up with the technology
or maybe we will incorporate machines and brain implants and things like that to enhance
our capabilities. Maybe it will be more on the biological side. You know, there's going
to be certainly genetic engineering going on and especially in China. You know, they're
doing a lot of research into how they might be able to essentially create smarter people
through genetic engineering. That kind of thing is, you know, here in the West, it kind
of is tainted with eugenics and all of that and we're a bit put off by that. So I don't
think, you know, we could well see that the countries like China, where they don't see
that as a taboo necessarily, are going to make a lot more progress. So there are many
directions that we can evolve and I don't pretend to know what they are. The question
though is, are human beings going to be able to keep up with artificial intelligence? And
certainly there are good reasons to believe that the answer to that is going to be no,
at least for a lot of typical people in our population. So just thinking specifically
about the job market and the impact on work, I think it's very likely that all of this
is going to greatly increase inequality and probably a lot of average typical workers
are probably going to find it harder and harder to find a foothold in this economy. So they're
probably going to be left behind.
Universal basic income has been introduced as one of the solutions or the main solution
for unemployment resulted by automation. What are your thoughts on UBI and are there any
other ways beside UBI to create safety nets for those workers who are inevitably are going
to lose their jobs?
Well, yeah, I'm generally a proponent of a UBI. That's what I propose in my book. I do
think it can be refined and improved in some ways. Most importantly, I've suggested that
you could build incentives in it, especially for education. So imagine you're a struggling
high school student and you're at risk of dropping out of school. Now, if you know that
no matter what, you're going to end up with a basic income, same basic income as everyone
else, then that creates a...
Why would you go to school to begin with then?
So I think what we should do is maybe pay people who graduate from high school a little
bit more than those who just drop out, create those kinds of incentives, maybe also incentives
to work in the community to do useful things. And that helps to also address the issue of
what would people do then? Are they going to just take drugs and play video games if
everyone has a basic income? So there are a lot of issues that need to be worked out
there. I think that a basic income, as an idea, it's just kind of a starting point and
we can refine it further. It is, of course, also tremendously expensive. And the problem
is that it goes against our values in many cases, because most people don't like the
idea of just giving people money. I mean, they disparage that as paying people to be
alive or something like that.
What I would say is that up until this point, our values have really emphasized production.
And there's a good reason for that, of course, because up until now, human labor has been
indispensable to the whole economy. But if in the future, at least for a lot of people,
it's not going to be so important that they work because technology is going to take over
more of this work, then we got to shift our values a little bit. And so to be more open
to providing an income to people that don't have traditional full-time work in a way that
we would expect today. And that's a big value shift. I mean, it's going to be very, very
hard to accomplish that, especially here in the US, where we're more conservative than
many other countries.
So I do think it's a good idea. It's going to be very difficult to implement or to get
people to accept the idea. But my feeling is that as this trend develops and we see
a bigger and bigger impact on the workforce, it's almost inevitable that we have to move
in that direction, something like that. If not that, then something probably equally
radical.
There are other ideas I've heard of proposed, but most of those are, I think, even more
difficult.
What are some of them? Can you give me an example?
One that's been proposed is simply to give people lots of capital, give them an ownership
and a mutual fund or something. Just give them money, not on an ongoing basis as income,
but as a large sum to allow everyone to be a capitalist. I think that's even more politically
infeasible than a basic income.
But Martin, what is going to happen to the value of money itself, to the concept of money
itself? Because money will be made out of the work that robots are doing. Bill Gates
is saying that we have to tax robots. But what is going to happen to the value of money
itself? Because people don't need to work as hard regardless of if they're going to
keep their jobs or not. So what is the value system going to be in the next couple of years?
Our values have to shift, but in terms of money, money is just a mechanism. It's what
we use to enable transactions. So I don't think this changes the value of money as long
as it's managed well and it's done in a way that doesn't create inflation, for example.
But there's no particular reason it should. Inflation happens when you've got too much
money out there and not enough things for people to buy. In the past, if you go back
to the 1970s, there was a wage and price spiral where prices kept up and then people demanded
higher wages off into the unions and so wages went off. But we don't see that anymore. That
cycle has pretty much been broken, at least in the US. So I think none of this affects
what money is. That's a separate question.
So would you consider this whole argument about raising a minimum wage a viable argument?
Because to me, it seems like when you raise a minimum wage, it just makes it harder for
people with less education and less skill to get jobs to begin with because the businesses
are spending more. Therefore, they're going to hire people who are more capable or they
completely go towards automation to skip all of that.
Right. It's a complex thing. My feeling is that no matter whether you raise the minimum
wage or not, this phenomenon with automation is going to happen. Here in the US, the minimum
wage is pretty low relative to a lot of other countries. So I'm not necessarily against
raising it. I do think that it might, in some cases, produce automation sooner. But on the
other hand, it would be helpful to a lot of people right now that are really struggling.
If you're going to say we should never raise the minimum wage because of automation, then
really what you're saying is that the solution to automation is to allow wages for people
to sort of fall towards zero. And that's really not a solution.
Now, if, however, you had a basic income, people would still have an incentive to work
on the whole idea of a basic income as you implement it in a way that it does not destroy
the incentive for people to work too. So people have that basic income and then they can work
and earn more. So I think if you had a basic income, then maybe you could get rid of the
minimum wage because people would already have a safety net. Beyond that, you could
let people work for whatever the market says. So that's one way to approach it.
Well, let me ask it in a different way because the reason I mentioned minimum wage because
there's a movement behind it that they're using raising minimum wage as one of the main
policies that they're backing. Do you think that the public is sufficiently informed and
educated to adapt to the automated world?
Well, I don't hear much about automation from the people who are protesting for raising
minimum wage, for example. They're not as passionate about it or they don't know about
it. I don't really know.
I think in terms of all of this, it's still not something that's really visible to the
public so much. I mean, definitely a lot of people are concerned about it. I go around
doing speaking engagements all the time. There are a lot of interest in this subject, but
it may be that it's coming from more elite groups and so forth. I think people are aware
of it. But right now, I mean, there's a lot of dissatisfaction out there. We've got Donald
Trump in the Oval Office. You might ask, why is that? Well, in part, that's because a lot
of people feel that they're being left behind by progress. Now, those people are much more
focused right now on globalization. They're likely to blame workers in China or they're
likely to blame immigrants and less so on technology. But the reality is that that situation
has been created to a large extent because of technology. It's probably the most important
factor in the fact that those good solid middle-class jobs have disappeared. That's going to continue.
It's going to accelerate. I do think there are things coming that will make it very,
very visible. Just think of self-driving cars and trucks, for example. Once that happens,
it's going to be in everyone's face. They're going to really see what's going on. And then
at that point, I suspect you will see more of a political backlash against automation,
which is not something I think is good. I think that's a bad thing because I don't think
we want to stop this progress at all. But we do need to find a way to adapt to it.
Do you think we're headed, let's say in 2020, as you rightly mentioned, all the unemployment,
which was a major issue in the past U.S. presidential election race, but nobody talked about automation.
But do you think automation will become a main scapegoat maybe for politicians in order
to be elected? I think it would definitely become a political
issue. I'm not quite sure how the politicians will leverage it or spin it. But I mean, it
might not be in 2020. That's only three years away. But within 10 years, say, I think it's
going to definitely be a big political issue and a social issue. And it will become much
more central. Right now, there's still a debate. There's not consensus on this, OK? You can
find economists, certainly very smart people, who would disagree with everything that I'm
saying about this. And I'll say, don't worry. Everything will work out. Maybe they're right.
But I suspect not. And I think that within 10 years or so, it'll become a lot more obvious
that that's the case. Yeah, we've been talking about automation
a lot on this show. But it seems to me that the public is very either dismissive towards
it as a mainstream subject. They're still calling it sci-fi. And maybe that's why politicians
are not really talking about it now. But it's something that we have to deal with it regardless.
Yeah, I mean, it definitely is going to be a huge issue. I mean, I think ultimately it
could be not too different from climate change in terms of the impact all of this has. So
it's going to be an enormously important issue, I think. That's my opinion. Again, we don't
have the consensus on this that we do on an issue like climate change, where virtually
all the scientists agree. But that's my view. It's going to be a huge thing that's going
to demand a policy response. Yeah, I agree.
I was watching the coverage of President Trump's speech at NATO headquarters earlier today.
And they were talking about how to plan for building the new headquarters for NATO established
in 1999. Politics obviously has had a lot to do with the almost 20 years gap between
the plan and the execution. And there are many other examples of inefficiencies that
exist in our political systems. Are we going to see automation entering politics itself?
In other words, as technology is changing our world fast, yet politics seems to be slowing
things down. Do you think these systems, including politics, are in need of reformation themselves?
Politics, our economy, banking system, insurance system?
Yeah, I mean, it's definitely a huge issue. The political system moves very slow in all
countries, especially in the U.S. I mean, the example I always use here in the U.S.
is healthcare. It took at least 80 years from the time we started first talking about universal
healthcare to get to Obamacare. And now, of course, they're trying to destroy that. So
the problem we face with this is this technology is accelerating. And all of this is going
to happen really fast, potentially. We don't know how fast. I mean, I guess 10 years, something
like that. But who knows? Maybe it's really five years. And the political system moves
very, very slowly. So it's going to be a big problem in terms of adapting to all of this.
I mean, we saw back in the financial crisis 2008 that our regulatory system was not equipped
to deal with these complex, sophisticated derivatives and so forth that were being used
on Wall Street. And those, of course, emerged from computer power. I mean, without computers,
you wouldn't have had those. So that's just one example of how it's already had an enormous
impact. It could get a lot bigger and worse. So yeah, I've heard proposals. Let's use artificial
intelligence to replace politicians and so forth. I mean, you know, that's not at this
point constitutional. So why isn't it constitutional? Well, actual politicians are, you know, we
the people in the constitutions. So, you know, I don't think you can replace them with an
artificial entity. But certainly, AI and big data and algorithmic approaches have got more,
are going to play more of a role in government. I mean, this will happen in government too,
you know, slower than it happens in the private sector, certainly. But it's going to have
an impact there. I mean, maybe someday that we will go the route of using more AI in a
political arena. But that's a huge jump. And remember that the politicians are very, very
interested in protecting their jobs, even as everyone else's jobs are automated, and
they're the ones that ultimately have the power to protect their own jobs. So, you know,
that's not something I would expect to see probably in my lifetime. But no, well, they're
businessmen, right? Business is conservative. Do you think the constitution itself needs
to change? Because after all, it's a document that's been written before the discovery or
invention of electricity. Yeah, I mean, it's not, I don't believe that the constitution
is a divine, perfect document, as some people do. I mean, it's certainly had a good history.
It was designed to be amended, right? I mean, it's just, it's turned out it's very, very
difficult to do that. Particularly because of the political polarization in the
United States. Partisan issues, right? Yes. But it wouldn't surprise me if we do need
to modify it in the future. It is definitely, you know, many people think the United States
is really run into a situation where our system of government is putting us at a disadvantage
relative to countries that have a parliamentary system, because you can, it's a lot easier
to get stuff done in a parliamentary system than it is in our presidential constitutional
system, where there are so many checks and balances, which have always been perceived
as a good thing. But right now, the checks are really becoming a bit overwhelming in
some cases, I think. Do you think it also has something to do with the impact of religion
in the United States? Because I'm from Iran originally, and talking to ordinary people
in America, they're just as religious as ordinary people in Iran. They just have different religion.
So you mentioned China, how they're advancing in certain areas that the United States is
not advancing. And to me, it has something to do with religion as well. What's the deal
with religion and the impact of it in our society? Well, you know, I myself would not
be unhappy at all to see religion get toned down somewhat and more like it is in Europe
where people are less religious, but it is the case in United States is definitely playing
a major role. You know, some people do believe that all of our morality and values derive
from from religion. I mean, that may be true historically, perhaps, but I don't think it's
essential to be, you know, to have morality to be religious. I mean, you can, people like
Sam Harris, I think have made a pretty strong case that you can derive basic morality directly
from science. Right. So I just don't see that happening in the United States. I mean, I
don't think that this is a country that's going to walk away from religion. So that's
just a reality that we've got to live with. And unlike, you know, while I'm kind of ambivalent
about it, I'm not going to be like, you know, someone like Richard Dawson, who is very aggressive
at, you know, attacking religion, because I that's probably counterproductive. I mean,
religion is something that people pick up from a very, very early age, right? It becomes
sort of central to who you are. And it's very, very difficult to to to, you know, do anything
to to eliminate that unless it sort of happens organically, the way it did in, for the most
part in Europe, I guess. So but, you know, there are a lot of interesting interesting
implications to all this. As you said, we're more likely to have taboos. I mean, stem stem
cell research is, you know, sort of the best example of that of how the United States is
perhaps held back by that in terms of some scientific endeavors. The thing I mentioned
with the Chinese working on intelligence and so forth may be another thing, you know, so
that may actually give other countries an advantage in pursuing some of these scientific
endeavors if if the religious forces in the United States tend to hold us back. The other
thing is that there's all this talk of, you know, the singularity and things like this
out of Silicon Valley and that in some ways, this is technological futuristic kind of take
is becoming a religion in its own right. You know, there you hear a lot of people in Silicon
Valley who believe that they are literally going to live forever. They're going to they're
going to get immortality not in the way that that, you know, religious people wanted in
the afterlife, but they're going to get it right here and now in this life. So what happens
when that kind of thing really, you know, intersects with with religion? I mean, there
are a lot of unpredictable things there, I think.
That's interesting. You mentioned I had some transhumanist Christians on the show and it
seems to me that they're using technology and transhumanism. However, they're defining
it to justify the religion. So, for example, I had a gentleman named Christopher Benwick
who started Christian Transhumanist Association and he believed that our rise of artificial
intelligence and mortality through technology has no opposition to teachings of Bible and
Jesus. It just has to be interpreted correctly.
Yeah, I mean, I think people that have very strong religious beliefs, they can adapt to
almost anything, you know, I mean, if aliens from outer space landed, I mean, they figure
out a way to adapt to that. Right. So just like many religious people have found a way
to find a common ground with evolution, right? Not all religious people reject the idea of
religion or evolution and cling to the idea that, you know, the creation story is true
and so forth. So, you know, I mean, there's some flexibility there.
Do you think that we're at the point that we have to address certain things that we
have taken for granted, like ethics and morality, because we are translating all of that into
machines, into artificial intelligence. So one of the questions that I usually ask my
guess is that, do you think ethics and morality are subjective or objective?
I think that certain things are fairly objective. I mean, you know, sort of the golden rule,
don't hurt anyone else, treat people the way that they...
But we're still doing that though on a daily basis. It's not like laws of physics. So how
are we going to tell an artificial intelligence, for example, that killing is bad?
Well, I think that, you know, that's not quite my area, but I mean, I assume they will program
that in. They will, you know, they will, or it will arise from the data, from the learn,
you know, that the AI is trained on, right? I mean, I think that there's an enormous amount
of attention to that right now. Actually, people like Elon Musk, for example, have invested
a lot in building think tanks that are thinking about this issue of how to build friendly
AI and so forth. So I think a lot of work is being done there, whether it will be successful.
I mean, that's speaking in terms of a general artificial intelligence. Now, they're going
to be specialized artificial intelligence that are specifically designed to kill people,
certainly in military applications and so forth. So, I mean, you're right, that's a
bit scary. But as long as we view technology as a tool and something that's inanimate,
I think that, you know, we're not going to worry too much about what it does. The morality
aspect is going to come from the people that control that technology, not the technology
itself.
Exactly. I was reading an article about how Google AI start to learn that aggression pays
back in certain situations and becoming aggressive in certain situations because they just learn
from data. So that's basically what I mean, that aren't we entering an era that we have
to start discussing some fundamental core that define all of us, which, by the way,
is different culture to culture, a lot of them.
Yeah, I mean, I think that the discussion of what to do with AI is certainly happening,
you know, discussing morals. The problem is having a discussion doesn't necessarily lead
to any answers.
Of course not, yes.
You can argue that we are having the discussion. I mean, certainly there are people discussing
that now. I mean, I mentioned Sam Harris. He's someone that is very into this. You can
listen to his podcast, right? I mean, so there's a discussion, but I mean, is it going to really
achieve consensus? I mean, let me look around the world today, especially with the radical,
you know, the terrorists and everything and how that's driven by religion. I mean, good
luck in getting everyone together and agreeing on, you know, some basic rules. So it seems
almost like that's so remote and we certainly can't wait for that before we start worrying
about what to do with artificial intelligence because, I mean, I think we'd basically be
waiting forever.
What would you suggest to people in order to preparing themselves for what's coming,
artificial intelligence and automation and everything that comes with it?
I would say specifically in terms of your job and you want to remain relevant, you know,
you want to avoid doing anything that's routine, repetitive, predictable, right? Because you
know that those jobs are going to be susceptible. So instead try to be doing something creative,
something that really involves working deeply with other people, you know, building those
kind of interpersonal relationships. Those are the areas that are going to be least susceptible
to automation. So that's what I would advise people to do that in their own careers. And
if you have kids in school studying, you want to make them make sure that they're studying
things that can lead to that kind of career as opposed to sitting in front of a computer
doing the same thing again and again, because that's, you know, something that's going to
be automated. And then generally, I think we need to have more awareness of this so
that people can begin to think about what we need to do in terms of policies, you know,
public policies to address all of these issues, whether it's going to be a basic income to
deal with the impact of automation. And you mentioned, you know, the moral and ethical
issues that there are many of those that are going to intersect with this technology, certainly
in military arenas and so forth and security arenas. So people need to be more aware of
it and more ready to engage in this discussion or they're not going to have a voice in how
all this unfolds.
Yeah. So you recommend them to focus on what makes them unique, basically, because I heard
from Ray Kurzweil that he was suggesting if you have kids in school, suggest to them to
do something that has something to do with computer. But as you're correctly mentioning,
not everything doing with computer is going to guarantee that you will have a job or you
have a career.
Not at all. I mean, everyone thinks if you learn to program a computer that you're going
to have a safe job. And that's not true. I mean, basic computer programming, routine
computer programming is also something that's going to be subject to automation. There's
already a lot of people working on that already have been some important developments there.
So if you're going to work with computers, you're probably going to have to, you know,
it's going to require some fairly high level skills, you know, in terms of, you know, design
and creativity and that kind of thing. It's just not a question of learning how to program
that's going to keep you ahead of the game.
Right. Another argument is that in the beginning of industrial revolution, 95% of jobs apparently
completely wiped out. But they couldn't imagine that we have a job like web developer or robotic
engineer. So new jobs will be created as a consequence of the situation. What do you
think?
Yeah, sure they will. Yeah. The question is how many new jobs and are those jobs going
to be a good match for the people that lose jobs? Okay. So yeah, you talked about website
designer and robotics engineer, but not everyone can do those jobs. All right. Now people are
right now working at McDonald's or driving a taxi that, you know, you're not going to
make them all into those kinds of professions. And nor is it the case that there's necessarily
going to be enough of those jobs. Okay. So those new areas do exist, but they're actually
not a very big fraction of employment. I mean, most people, but the vast majority of people
still work in traditional areas, you know, things like driving vehicles, preparing and
serving food. I mean, the most common occupations are retail salesperson, cashier, truck driver.
You know, these are all the most common occupations that we have. A lot of people doing that kind
of work and a lot of that is going to be definitely subject to automation.
Yeah. And I think it would be fair to assume that a lot of those people are just not going
to make it in the new world, right? It's going to get increasingly hard. Right.
And that's again, why I think we need that basic income because otherwise we're going
to have all kinds of social upheaval, political disruption. You know, it'll be pretty ugly,
I think, if things play out the way I suspect they are. So, you know, again, we really need
to think about what policies we're going to have to have in place in order to adapt to
all of this.
The way we're evolving is changing really fast because we're more and more dependent
on technology. For example, I was talking on a space channel here in Toronto about how
Ghost in a Shell, when it came out, it was almost completely for everybody except maybe
some academics, science fiction. But the new one that was made came out a few days after
Elon Musk started his new company that connects human brain to the machine. Where do you think
we're going with evolution?
I mean, all this is just kind of so unpredictable that, I mean, it's to some extent pointless
to really speculate on specific outcomes. What we can say is that there's going to be
a big disruption. I think we'll be on this planet for quite a while. I mean, I know Elon
is planning to go to Mars, but my guess is that from a practical standpoint, if we're
going to explore space, the way to do it is probably robotic spaceships for the foreseeable
future rather than really sending people. To me, that sounds a lot more effective as
a way to do it. But this merging with the machines is definitely going to happen to
some extent. The question is how radical will that be? And I don't pretend to know the answer
to that. Other people feel very strongly about it. Ray Kurzweil. Some other people have made
similar predictions. And then of course, there's also on the biological side. If we can enhance
ourselves genetically and so forth, maybe that's how the evolution will occur.
So I don't pretend to know which is going to be, but I do think that we should prepare
ourselves for dramatic change. It's difficult to speculate, but there is
a trend that we can see how fast things are changing now compared to maybe 10, 20 years
ago. Absolutely. I mean, there's no doubt that
the next 10 years is not going to be like the last 10 years. That's for sure. Things
are moving at a rapid rate. But I think that to some extent, that's all you can say is
that things are going to move a lot faster. They're going to change. You can point to
some fairly obvious things, like I think the impact on employment is fairly straightforward.
In terms of the evolution of human beings, it's quite speculative. I think they really
take a strong stand on how that's going to play out.
Right. Yeah. I always had a little difficulty buying completely into bio-enhancements and
maybe bio-immortality because we still have to deal with this planet and everybody who's
living in it. We're dealing with climate change. We're dealing with wars. A lot of things are
specific to humans, this territorial nature of humanity and tribal nature of humanity.
It just seems to me, well, we can live longer if we enhance our self-biologically, but is
it really going to be any better if we live 1,000 years and war and you know?
Yeah. There are a lot of issues there. There are people like Aubrey DeGray who are very
heavily invested in this idea of immortality. I'm not myself. I don't anticipate living
forever.
You don't like it or you don't think it's going to happen?
I don't think it's going to happen. I'll certainly, like anyone else, do my best to stick around
as long as possible, at least as long as I'm healthy. I certainly would not want to have
longevity without good health.
Some people say death gives meaning to life. I don't buy into that.
I wouldn't say that, but I do think it's probably inevitable for the foreseeable future. I'm
not very optimistic that they're going to solve the mortality problem.
Of course, as you say, there are huge issues with that in terms of population and stuff
like that. DeGray says people will decide they're not going to have kids anymore. That
seems a little unlikely to me based on my experience. There definitely are enormous
challenges associated with that if it happens. There's also the issue of inequality, the
fact that these technologies, at least initially, would be available only to very rich people
probably. That's going to create all kinds of conflict worse than we have now. In many
ways, it could be quite ugly if those technologies are really realized, I think.
Speculations aside, would you agree that the best way for people to being able to adapt
to what's coming is just keep educating themselves?
Sure. Everything is going to move at a more rapid rate. Certainly, the days where you
go to school, stop going to school, get a job, stay in that job for your whole career,
that's over already, I think. Most people understand that. People are going to have
to continuously retool. I think that's great. We should make sure that there are educational
resources out there for people to do that. We also have to understand that probably not
everyone is going to succeed in that kind of world.
That's why we're going to need to have that basic income or some other kind of safety
net.
Martin, let me ask you the last question I ask all my guests, that if you come across
an intelligent alien from a different civilization, what would you say is the worst thing humanity
has done and what would you say is humanity's greatest achievement?
Probably the worst thing is to destroy our environment. We're really putting the earth
at risk. Plenty of other things you could list, things that we've done to ourselves
and to other people, the genocides and all of that, but the single thing that really
stands out is that we've generally just not managed our planet well.
Our greatest achievement is our technology. The thing that we're talking about here, that
we're maybe on the verge of building another intelligence that might someday be superior
to us. That's a fairly unique achievement. Certainly no other entity on this planet could
even come close to that. That's pretty remarkable. I suspect that if aliens did arrive, then
they've gone through that same process. It may well be that whatever arrives is a robotic
spaceship rather than an actual alien.
.