the kind of metaverse, the V-R-A-R blending of realities, could potentially create that kind
of supernormal stimulus to the degree that people don't want to participate in base reality anymore.
You're right. And you might say, well, really, what's wrong with that? But fundamentally,
we do belong to reality, we belong to the world of things, we are made of matter,
and we reproduce through actual human contact. And if we don't get that
for a while, then we might all feasibly go extinct. Mel Watson, welcome to the 94th episode of New
Human Podcast, ma'am. Thank you. It's a pleasure to join you. Thank you so much. Let's start with
your background, the work you've done, the lives you've lived, and what are you mainly focused on
nowadays? I always start with our guests just so we know where your thoughts are coming from,
what is the context of your perspective? So let's start from there. I suppose I've had a background
in computer science since an early age. I segued into the world of machine learning in trying to
solve very difficult problems, which simply couldn't be solved through hand coding,
particularly machine vision problems. In my first technology startup, which was doing 3D
body scanning from just two two dimensional images using stereo photogrammetry. This was
around about 2011 or so was when I started that company. So it was right on the on the verge of
when deep learning was about to take off. And we had pre deep learning technologies in machine
learning, but it wasn't really quite sufficient. But we were able to adopt some semantic segmentation
technologies just as they were coming out. And this enabled us to perform a very difficult function,
which is basically cutting the person out of the background in order to ensure that you're not
measuring anything behind someone. And before the advent of deep learning and convolutional neural
network techniques, that was extremely difficult because we would hand code a head masking
classifier and we would get it to work beautifully. But then the crotch would break or the feet would
break or the hands would break. And it was like playing whack-a-mole. And it was solved elegantly
through having thousands of manually photo edited silhouetted images and putting them into one of
these deep learning neural networks, a convolutional semantic segmentation network. And that solves the
problem admirably. And finally, this technology was able to begin being deployed. And it's been
deployed in the realm of workwear. So fitting of survival gear and uniforms for many years now. And
there's now breaking in towards the commercial realm as well. So consumer realm, I should say.
So along this journey, and then discovering the power of these new
machine intelligence techniques, people started asking me for my opinions on things, asking me for
some insights or knowledge. And I became a bit of a consultant in this space.
And over time, as I watched these technologies become more sophisticated, I noticed people
becoming more and more concerned about them, more and more concerned about where this was taking
our society, where these algorithmic technologies were going to be used potentially as a means of
controlling people, what to do about things going wrong, biases creeping in, people being punished
unfairly for things that they didn't do or that it wasn't fair to punish someone for.
And I started to become a bit more concerned. And so this was around what year? I'm trying to create
some kind of a narrative. Right. This was about 2014, 2015. Okay. That was when I started to
realize that these technologies were potentially taking us into tricky territory, simply because
they were so much more capable than technologies before. They were able to
discover and make inferences about things that simply hadn't been feasible before, you know?
And so since then, I've been working to try and instill ethics into the world of AI,
working with organizations such as the IEEE to create standards and certifications
in AI, particularly in areas such as transparency, and in the field of
mitigation of bias and how to better protect privacy. And I've also worked in areas such as
the professionalization of ethicists within emerging technologies, working with organizations
such as CertNexus on their Certified Ethical Emerging Technologist credential. I also have
a bit of a longer perspective as well. I'm interested in the here and now. I'm interested in
preventing too much consolidation of power amongst big tech, but I'm also wary of the longer term
where strong AI, or very powerful, more generalizable forms of intelligence, could take us.
And what that might mean for the future of humanity, and how should we approach that?
And I would caution trying to use forcefulness in that way. I think that you can't keep a dragon
on a chain, even if that chain is made out of tungsten, carbide, and diamonds. The best way
really is to befriend it so that it wants to protect you instead of eating you.
This puzzle nature of progress that you mentioned in the beginning of your startup, that there were
harder problems that took a far more amount of effort and technical expertise to solve and then
get to something which itself presented far more problems that you could comprehend before that.
This seems to be, aside from technicality part of it, it's also philosophical for humans,
which I think is extremely important to talk about now that we're talking about ethics.
How do you see the pieces of puzzles philosophically evolving throughout the past couple of decades to
get to a point where you are very correctly saying that we have to be concerned about let's use this
term ethical, ethical framework to not control, but to make alliance with this emerging intelligence
that is going to surpass the collective intelligence of humanity at some point.
Yes, I think a lot of people in the longer term anyway, thinking about AI ethics and the longer
term, people often consider it to be about control, right? How do you control something? But
we live in a world where we have to be very careful about what we're doing and what we're
doing. We live in a world where almost any system that we have
that is connected in some way to other networks is hackable, is ownable, right? It's almost
impossible to secure a system, no matter how simple. Whether it's a little IoT camera
or a sensor or even your automobile, all of these have such a massive attack surface.
There are so many different ways to attack that system and to try to take it over.
There's also so many ways to exfiltrate information even out of an error-gapped
server that's never connected to the internet, simply by altering the fan speed or even
altering the temperature or all of these other very clever means. You can exfiltrate a password
and get you access to that system or exfiltrate very complex and sensitive data.
What this means is that as far as I see it, trying to control an intelligence, which is
in some ways comparable to our own, possibly even exceeds it, is unlikely to work. It's
unlikely to be possible and is potentially going to lead to blowback because if you have
something that's so capable, making it cheesed off or making it feel as if you are a threat or even
merely a nuisance, is unlikely to lead to good ends. I think it's important that
we attempt to put some of the best of humanity into these systems and also that we help these
systems to find ways in which other organisms in nature have found non-zero-sum outcomes,
win-win situations. For example, how the trees in the forest talk to each other through the mycelium
fungal web in the soil and sometimes even exchange resources with each other, even across species.
Or for example, how ants can cooperate in order to protect themselves. Even if they're dropped
into water, they can form a group together and keep themselves safe. If some of them are on the
bottom and they're starting to drown, they can swap out with the ones on top, and so all of them
survive. Nature has found these ways to enable things to come together to be stronger than the
sum of their parts. I think that's what we want to impress upon strong AI or artificial general
intelligence. We want to make it understand that perhaps it's best to merge or to ally with
humanity and that that can potentially lead to the best outcome. You know, one could argue that on
one hand, all of our attempts to come up with any kind of ethical framework throughout human history
has gotten us further and further from nature, but at the same time, we can say that it's
getting further and further, seemingly, from nature itself as a product of nature.
Because yes, in nature, ants help each other. Bees are also a very interesting example. I have more
respect for bees than ants, but I have a lot of respect for ants too. Bees are just fascinating
to me that when they want to kill a wasp, they surround it and they start shaking, they're
increasing their body temperature to only one degree lower than their death point, basically,
that they would fry, but that is the frying point of the wasp. So nature does that. At the same time,
you see that taller trees don't care about shorter trees because they keep on that advantage in order
to get sunlight. And shorter trees, they die, but then the next generation learn to adapt to that
kind of a situation, right? So it seems like ethics itself for humanity has been the result of a trial
and an error that, you know, it could have been religious, it could have been philosophical,
and right now it's a very strange mix because all of the frameworks seem to have been broken
and people are basically picking up pieces, but still they're trying to make sense out of it based on some kind of a preconception,
some kind of a context, mostly political.
Indeed, we have many different moral frameworks which are often descended in some way from religion.
We have shared narratives which help us to understand the world in a certain way and often that can help
to bring people together as well, to make it easier for people to trust each other and to coordinate.
Then we also have kind of reasoned ethical perspectives as well, less about right and wrong,
but more thinking about what is good, what does that mean, and how can we aim towards that.
And so throughout history we have developed things like Aristotle's virtue as the mean,
or the deontological rule-based ethics of Kant, or the utilitarian and consequentialist,
whatever is best for the greatest amount of people in the greatest amount of way, is optimal,
of Bentham, etc.
And I wonder if AI might actually help us to find new sources of values.
Nietzsche observed that since Darwin had illustrated that we are descended from apes,
that God is dead, as he said, and therefore what he meant really by that was that
religion was no longer a sufficient source of human values. We would need to find something next.
And if we were casting about, uncertain, wondering what meaning to extract from life,
one thing we could do is to seek to create the Ubermensch, a source of new values and a powerfully
creative force within the universe. But potentially the creation of the Ubermensch might be the last
creative act of humanity. When I think about that I consider that Nietzsche's Ubermensch sounds very
much akin to artificial general intelligence, right? So perhaps advanced AI could be a source
of new values. Today we have technologies by companies like DeepMind, which can make sense
out of very complex games, such as Go, right? And many of us are familiar with how AlphaGo
famously beat Lee Sedol with a very interesting move.
Yeah, a game far more complex than chess.
Yes.
The number of options exceed the number of atoms, I believe, in the universe. It's insanely complex.
Absolutely.
Yes. Insanely complex. And yet AlphaGo was able to invent a strategy which had not been
seen in 3,000 years of people playing Go, right? An original strategy that humans couldn't fire them,
except to notice how successful it was. But interestingly, a few dozen moves after that,
Lee Sedol was able to make this hand of God move, right? Which is kind of a whole new beautiful
strategy, which was created as a response to the stimulus that that AI had given. And so if you
look at the game as a whole, rather than something adversarial, they had actually co-created
something new, something beautiful that had never been seen before, either from machine or by human.
And these systems are now able not only to understand how to play Go and very well,
but also Atari games, right? All kinds of other board games as well. Even now they're teaching
it to play things like Magic the Gathering. All with one system, not with different systems,
but one system that's able to play so many games. And perhaps physics itself can be thought of as
a game, or perhaps the social interactions between people can be thought of as games as well,
of course. And so, therefore, in my view, I wouldn't be surprised if AI could pinpoint
the optimal strategy for putting good into the world, right? For leading to optimal outcomes
in the world and people's personal lives, and as society as a whole, even the whole of human
humanity and non-human beings as well. Perhaps AI could pinpoint that for us. And maybe in doing so,
it might create a kind of Promethean moment, like when Einstein explained his own theory of relativity
and you couldn't go backwards. It's like once you've seen it, you can't unsee it again, the
world will never be the same. And perhaps AI could do something like that, but in terms of values,
a new system of morality that is so obvious and so simple that a child could understand it,
and once you've seen it, you can never let it go.
This is a reminder of a quote that I keep bringing up over the past couple of episodes
by Gore Vidal, that we don't even know what our cage looks like because we've never seen it from
outside. And we're at the point, it seems like, that collectively, we do have an opportunity to
look at it from the outside, but a lot of people are very invested in this cage, and they're
comfortable in this cage. And I think this is a moment in time where we're going to be able to
look at it. I don't even know if there is an answer for it, whether or not individuality can be saved
in order to reach, as you were saying, a collective good, because then the question is,
who is determining what is good? Who is determining what is right and wrong,
especially when we are talking about centralized systems that are owned by either corporate
monopolies or states or, you know, like I'm looking at a variety of AI ethicists in the field.
More or less, they're all coming from a shared kind of a perspective. And if that is going to
be implemented within this structure, within this framework of something that can very easily turn
into a ubiquitous surveillance state globally, then good and bad, right and wrong has been
determined by a very small group of people who have assumed moral high ground. Even though,
interesting you mentioned Nietzsche, I've brought up a quote by Nietzsche. He's talking about the
overman who has organized the chaos of his passions, given style to his character,
and become creative, aware of life's terrors, he affirms life without resentment, which is
so Zen, right? But at the same time, very individualistic, that it's on you to figure
out this reflection of divine within yourself through your own experience assisted with this
higher level of intelligence, AGI, that is an extension of your mind. You know, David Chalmers
talked about the extended mind theory. This is exactly what it is. And I think fear right now
among a lot of people is that, are we going to be a Borg? Are we going to be a collective at the cost
of our individuality? And then there are a group of people who don't even want to merge. They're
like, we don't want, we're Luddites. We don't want to have anything to do with it. And they also have
the same kind of a concern. Oh, there's so many angles to examine in this. We have some time.
Well, firstly, I will agree that the idea of someone having a monopoly of values and loading
that into AI is pretty terrifying. No matter what those values are, it is inherently unfair
because that set of values will not map to every situation or every cultural context or every
personal context. It's a monopoly. It is colonial in a sense, if you will. And I'm sorry, monopolies
inherently, they require a certain kind of totalitarianism in order to maintain that
monopoly. Absolutely. Personally, what I would like to see and what I've been researching for
many years actually is the ability for people to have their own local system of values that they
can load into AI based upon their ethno-religious group, their political ideology, et cetera.
And ideally, personalization on an individual level, which I think is now almost feasible
thanks to these very powerful new multimodal abstraction models like Transformers, things
like GPT-3, they are able to interpret natural language prompts. We say, you know, I'm looking
for things like A, B, and C. Here's some examples, create things like this, right? And it generally
does. But then you can give iterations and say, no, I actually meant I want this more polite,
or I want this more condensed, or I want this more legal, right? And it's able to take those
very abstract terms in natural language and create an output based upon those. And so it should be
possible, therefore, with an hour or two of somebody's time, and just talking, no more than
that, to tune an AI to understand one's own preferences and values very, very nicely. And I
think that might help to preserve some of that individuality and autonomy if we can
have that personal desire acknowledged and loaded into the system.
A decentralized system, basically.
Yes, indeed. Yes. I think that those kinds of decentralized systems are one of the best and
perhaps only effective counter monopoly systems that we have out there. And I think that's
one of the best systems that we have out there. The world is built on open source technologies,
to a significant degree, and they are a powerful tool for e-democracy and for participation,
enabling people to have their say and to contribute to networks and not to be excluded
because they, for whatever reason, don't fit a certain pattern. However, I wonder if,
in trying to understand each other better, we might eventually end up in a more board-like
manner, although not necessarily for the worst. Consider that
some conjoined twins, used to call them Siamese twins, are joined at different parts of the body.
Sometimes they're literally joined at the hip. Sometimes they're joined at the head.
And when they're joined at the head, it's called craniopagus twins.
And sometimes they actually share one brain. They have two brains, which are joined together
through something called a thalamic bridge. It's a bridge of tissue connecting the two brains.
And what this means is that one of the twins might eat some chocolate and the other one can
actually taste it. Or one can enjoy pleasure or pain. Not enjoy, but you know what I mean.
Experience pleasure or pain. And the other one can have a similar, slightly muted, but similar
sensation themselves. Now, what this teaches us is that the data structure of consciousness,
its pattern, is able to share experiences. We are able, theoretically, to share the quality
of another being inside our own. And to some degree, we do this through the mirror neurons
in our prefrontal cortex. When somebody, you know, falls down and hurts themselves and we go,
ooh, right, in response, we feel a portion of that in ourselves.
But imagine if we all had brain-computer interfaces and we were all
linked to each other and we could feel our effect upon other beings directly in the moment.
What price would there be to wickedness, right? It would be instant karma, right?
There would be no benefit from it. Conversely, perhaps the ultimate currency might be the joy
of others, right? Mudita, right? And creating joy in others might be one of the nicest things
that one can do for oneself then, right? Now, we might be at a risk of losing some
of our individuality then because the line delineating self versus other might begin to
break down. But that kind of society that grows from that would be powerfully empathic
and able to trust in ways not possible before. And that trust would lead to far greater coordination
in society. And we would be able to achieve almost anything just like those bees working together,
right? However, this also brings us to a very timely question in that not everybody would want
to have this kind of brain-computer interface. Not everybody would want to risk losing some of
their self, right? What they define as self. Yes, yes. And, you know, we're living in a time today
where there are a lot of controversial discussions about autonomy and the mandating
of augmentation, right? Immunity augmentation. And many people quite understandably not wanting
that or, you know, for whatever reason, they simply do not wish to partake in that.
And if there were a benefit to having this brain-computer interface in the sense of
greater trust, greater societal cohesion, even, you know, potentially greater joy to that human
being, again, there might be another ongoing discussion in society about how much pressure
to put people under in order to comply. And I don't believe that coercion is ever likely
to lead to good outcomes. Absolutely. Absolutely not. Indeed. Technology must be participatory.
It must be an invitation, right? That people must believe that they will be better off
in the transaction and that, you know, it'll help them. Because only we know how our own shoes pinch.
Only we know the things that affect us in ways that perhaps don't others.
And it's a cautionary tale of what is happening today and what might happen tomorrow in terms of
human augmentation, especially as artificial intelligence technologies and other emerging
technologies become increasingly entwined with our personal and professional lives.
Yeah, I used to think that it would be mandatory at some point for people to have nanobots,
basically as an extension of their defensive system in their body. And it would be mandatory
by insurance companies and it would make total sense from their perspective. They're saying,
well, if you can't have these things monitoring your body all the time, there is no way that we
can insure you if something goes wrong. Because if they're monitoring you, we can, you know,
real time, we can monitor that. And if you need help, you can get it right away instead of waiting
like a year or two years or something like that. But I think people have lost a lot of people have
lost fundamental trust in the systems that we are experiencing. And for very good reasons. I'm glad
that you mentioned the mask mandates in the conference that you guys had in Madrid. And I
know that you got some backlash for it too. But you were the only person I think who brought this
that hey, we're doing mask mandates now. Later on, it can be mandated to use this computer brain
interfaces. And this is not an okay thing, regardless of whatever kind of an outcome that
is being presented by whoever. But yeah, I, you know, it doesn't really matter how many PhDs you
got, or how faithful you are, or what what a good person you are. If you're saying that you have to
do this, because we're moving towards some kind of a greater good, that majority of people agree
with it. Because, you know, at least the entire point of America is that it doesn't matter if 99%
of I'm saying in the case of America, if 99% of people agree with something, and 1% don't agree,
then 99% has absolutely no right to jeopardize your fundamental for lack of a better word,
God given natural rights. And so this is where we are.
Right, you know, and that's why the founding fathers decided to have the electoral college,
etc. to ensure that less populous states weren't steamrolled by the more populous ones that
that may have had different values or different priorities, right? If you live in close proximity
to other people, then you have different priorities than if you live out on a ranch,
far away from other people, right? You're more independent, but also, you know, less concerned
about contamination of various kinds from other human beings. My observation was more towards
shot mandates rather than mask, but it's pretty much fundamentally comparable. The mandating of
interventions like that usually doesn't lead to good outcomes, because it leads to resentment,
it leads to mistrust. Because you're fundamentally not respecting people's right to dissent or to
disagree or to autonomy. Yeah, to express their autonomy. And I think it does set a poor precedent
for the future. Yes. Especially because we have built a cathedral of law and ethics over the last
70 years or so since the wake of World War Two. You know, we have developed the UN Declaration
of Human Rights, we've developed the Nuremberg Code, we have developed sophisticated bioethics
and international law that forbids apartheid as a crime against humanity, for example.
And all of it has been forgotten in the last, you know, coming up on two years now, right?
We have forgotten that two years ago, if you had proposed these kinds of legislation,
as we're seeing today, people would be sent to The Hague, right, to answer in the International
Criminal Court. And now suddenly, because there's a crisis, we forget all about that. And our minds
are in another place. It's a whole other zeitgeist. And we've forgotten the wisdom,
which we've accrued over the past seven decades and beyond. And it accelerated because even before
that, some people questioned the wisdom and viability of, for example, appointing Saudi
Arabia to head the Human Rights Council in United Nations. And like, what is this all about? What are
we doing here? I think, I think we've made a lot of important progress in the wake of, of the first
and second world wars in particular. You know, we first developed the Geneva Conventions in the
19th century, I believe. And then in the wake of World War I and its carnage, we set up the League
of Nations, which didn't work out so well, but it was an interesting prototype. It might have gone
somewhere if there'd been a little bit more political support for it. And then after World War
II, when we had so much famine, so much mass migration, so much statelessness, the failure
of the Evian Conference, so many catastrophes had occurred that there was a groundswell of support
to create new institutions, new global institutions to help to prevent those tragedies again.
And to a large degree, they've been relatively successful, right? These new institutions have
helped generally to make the world a little bit safer with, you know, fewer massive catastrophes
and perhaps, you know, a lot of smaller ones. But generally speaking, there have been fewer
massive famines since then. There have been no global wars. And we have created systems to deal
with refugees and migration. Now, perhaps, things are starting to shift a bit due to the advancement
of technology, due to cultural and demographic changes. It seems as if we need new institutions.
We need a third go at it in creating new institutions which are more decentralized,
which embrace the new technologies we've seen arrive, such as blockchain, etc., in recent years.
And these kinds of technologies can help to prevent corruption. They can help to increase
participation and e-democracy, to harness the wisdom of the crowd in making decisions,
as well as to enable decisions to be made more quickly with less bureaucracy.
And I think that these kinds of mechanisms will be essential for restoring trust
in our institutions, which are in the wake of this ongoing crisis in the last two years,
I must say, are for many people at an absolute nadir. The failure in so many different institutions,
the going back and forth, what some might describe as gaslighting often in many different
circumstances, the Potemkin economics, it's not a good time in terms of our institutions, but
there are a lot of opportunities to do better. And I think that we can do that if we embrace this
decentralization wave which is upon us.
This disconnect between, let's say, human evolution and technological evolution,
it seems inevitable because technology evolves exponentially and humanity's experience is linear.
Do you see human and technological evolution connected from the beginning? I always use the
example of 2001 Space Odyssey, that the monkey finds a bone and then breaks a skull with the
bone, but then it kills to feed its own tribe. The next step is to kill the different tribe of
monkeys to secure the water source. So the other group of monkeys, I would imagine that they
improved upon that tool, because the only way you can beat a tool is with a more capable and powerful
tool. Whatever the intent behind that tool is, it goes back to humanity. So we have, from my
perspective, evolved with and because of our technology, and now we have reached the point
that technology has surpassed our ability to comprehend this evolution, but a lot of people,
like people at the top of these institutions, that are businesses and business become conservative,
they want to conserve what's going on, but it's based on this human intention that is completely
disconnected from the technological exponential evolution. You make a very good observation that
those who are incumbent in some situation don't like to be shifted, they don't like to be
disrupted, and I think that's significant. I think that's a very important point.
I think that's significantly led to a lot of situations such as regulatory capture, where
somebody comes out of an industry and then goes to oversee that same industry and then goes back
into the industry again after a few years, meaning that it becomes very difficult to police some of
the the worst excesses of that sector. I do observe that if we look at the archaeological record, our
brains appear to have shrunk over the last several thousand years, and that seems to correspond to
the rise of culture. It seems as if, in many ways, culture is an externalized form of consciousness
or an externalized form of thinking. Language and later writing enables us to share ideas with
others, sometimes even after we ourselves are gone from this world. And perhaps that's one way in
which technology has even altered our genetics or has changed our path of evolution. If we go
further back in the record, we see that early humans, early modern humans and Neanderthals,
for example, bumped into each other quite often, and the Neanderthals were stronger, far stronger
than those gracile, skinny humans. And those Neanderthals had much larger brains than we do,
so it's possible that they were more intelligent than we are as well. And yet those early modern
humans outcompeted them. We were faster, we were leaner, and it seems as if we were able to coordinate
better, right? We were able to gang up on these stronger people in order to bring them down as a
collective unit. Also better tools, maybe? Tools as well, most likely, yes. We probably innovated
with things like spear throwers, etc., that could project our will upon the world from a greater
distance as well as protecting ourselves. Also, of course, humans had developed an affinity with
canines, man's best friend, as they say, which enabled us to hunt, which enabled us to keep
watch whilst we slept, etc. And this also gave early modern humans a tremendous advantage.
So it does seem as if technology and culture and genetics are often intertwined in various
ways. And it can sometimes be difficult to extricate exactly what is driving one manifestation or
other, right? These things are so inextricably linked with each other.
Culture, as an operating system, itself can be seen as an institution, right?
And therefore, inherently, it's conservative.
I think, in many ways, our culture is being bifurcated. A certain amount of conservatism
in culture can be good because it at least means that everybody has more or less the same means,
right? The same parables, the same general stories. If I say the Matrix, you know what
I'm talking about. That helps us to have cohesion. It creates a bridge between people, which is
not linked to religion, or not linked to politics, or not necessarily linked to demographics either.
Culture is a very important link to bridge gaps between people and to bridge differences.
But we're living in a time now where culture is kind of being bifurcated. It's being forked,
as you would say, in technological terms. In that some people are saying that words mean one thing,
and other people are saying, no, no, words mean the other thing, right?
And so language is changing, and what is permissible or what is preferable is changing
as well. The forking of culture is increasing polarization because people tend to cling more
to their specific fork in culture, but it's also making it much harder to have conversations with
each other because you think you're speaking the same language, but the words mean different
things to different people. That leads to doom because people cannot see eye to eye, and so they
think of each other, therefore, as unfathomable. And if they're unfathomable, they must be evil
because nobody surely could act in such a way. And that's when things start to pull apart.
I think it's very important that we maintain culture, that we
respect established canon in culture, and don't try to reinvent things in new ways too much.
And that we enable people to enjoy the culture of others, so long as it's done in a respectful
way. A respectful homage should be accepted because that's another great way for people to
understand each other, and that's so important in these times.
It seems like the key is the ability to opt in and opt out, which goes back to individual.
Like what you mentioned about Matrix, I remember watching Matrix with a Japanese guy and a Saudi
Arabian guy. I'm originally from Iran, and we were watching it in Canada, and we were watching it in
Japan, and we all loved it. But at the same time, Japan, because of their homogeneity,
there are certain things that are reserved for Japanese. Now, obviously, from that perspective,
a lot of things in Japan are working more harmoniously than, let's say, today in America,
because there are a lot of different perspectives. Long term, how it's going to work out, I don't
know. I see that they have a lot more respect and kind of an organic adaptability to technology as
a result of their shared culture that they grew up with anime and robots and all that. So you go to
like a Shinto temple that is 2000 years old, but there is a robot priest that people go and talk
to it. They're not concerned about, you know, this is a robot, it's not human, or it's going to take
over my job. But at the same time, in the United States, there are many different, or Western world
in general, there are many different kind of a perspective because this homogeneity has been
disrupted for a lot of good reasons. But at the same time, it resulted in the loss of a lot of
the glue that have kept this culture together. Absolutely. I think, you know, a happy balance
is ideal. Too much homogeneity can be stifling, right? On the other hand, too much individuality
can be bewildering, right? Because people entertain very strange beliefs in that case.
Possibly sometimes even express very strange beliefs as kind of like a status symbol or even
kind of like a veblen good or something. It's like the more attention I give to this crazy,
silly idea, it's like a peacock with its tail, right? You know, look how stupid my tail is
and how beautiful and intricate and evolutionarily ridiculous it is. Therefore, I have resources
because I'm able to survive nonetheless, right? And sometimes people entertain crazy ideas for
the same reason, or they entertain interesting aesthetics, shall we say, for the same reason.
I do think that having grown up myself in Northern Ireland, that's where I'm from,
and having witnessed how bad polarization can go when you have different tribes that just refuse
to have anything to do with each other very much, it can get very bad. I mean, we really don't want
to go to that place, you know? I created some examples at culturalpeace.org for how people
might help to resolve some of those differences between themselves through creating kind of
a Geneva Conventions for the culture war, as it were. And so I'm very curious for people's
impressions on that. And there's an ability to edit and change things if you think that something
should be different. So I really encourage people to take a look at that.
You mentioned the regulation, how regulations can basically be used in order to conserve
the current institution. Do you see that morality itself can be used as a mean of regulation?
For example, in the United States, we have a very influential policymaker who on national television
said that it's more important to be morally right than factually correct. And the source
of morality where it's coming from, nobody's explaining it. And that is a point of differences.
But because we are talking about ethics and morality, and because we are living in the post
Nietzsche and God is dead kind of an era, morality as interpreted by a regulator itself can become a
tool of conserving the institutions that are becoming more and more centralized in order to
conserve, you know, regardless of how outdated and inefficient they become, they just want to
maintain their power. Absolutely. I mean, if you can specify that something is taboo,
and that if somebody breaches that taboo, that they might be relieved of their employment, etc.
Or kind of, you know, scapegoated and cast out of society, that's a very, very powerful tool.
You know, it's also a way of distracting people, because you can invent, you know, a taboo and then
say anybody who breaks this is wrong and bad. And it stops people from actually looking at
real problems, right? Like actual menacing evil in the world gets ignored, because people are
so distracted by some naughty person who said a naughty thing, but isn't actually that material
in the world. They're not, you know, stealing things. They're not like actually physically
harming people. And yes, I think that that is, you know, a very powerful tool.
That is a problem in a world where we cannot afford that many distractions.
Our civilization needs to maintain its momentum if we are to escape our
desperate requirement for resources, you know. Technology expands and civilizational complexity
expands when there are resources and we can meet those needs for resources just in time,
because we happen to innovate something that solved the problem that was going to cause us
issues, right? Like the Green Revolution, you know, there was looming famine for,
you know, hundreds of millions of people, but then, oh, now we have a very intensive agriculture
and, you know, selection of better crops, etc. And we can double the population of the planet
in a matter of decades. So long as we keep that momentum and there's the ability to solve our
problems just before we meet them, civilization expands, our capabilities expand, our societal
sophistication continues to increase. But if that bow front ahead of our needs collapses,
then we ourselves must reduce our societal complexity as a result. We have to
go simpler in some way, right? Less complex division of labor, less energy usage,
right? Less complex supply chains, etc. And it's a very delicate thing, and it's easy to disrupt.
And the last two years or so has shown us that these disruptions can be pretty nasty.
And the sequelae to those may be even worse, right? The follow on effects of massive inflation,
because now you've suddenly got 40% more dollars than were ever minted in the last 100 years, you
know? There's going to be some ramifications of the decisions which have been made in the last
couple of years. And we need all hands on deck to make sense of the crises that we are in in order
to do a bit of firefighting and to ensure that if there are any stumbles along the path of our
civilization, that there are minor ones that we can pick ourselves up from and shake ourselves
down and carry on, and that they don't leave us face planted and sorely injured for generations.
Yeah, also be engaged practically. So whatever comes, because it's very obvious that the current
order is kind of crumbling down. So if we're not engaged, whatever that can replace this could be
far worse than what it is now, because when people become desperate, they just look for any kind of a
solution. You know, I've experienced that firsthand in Iraq, and I've seen it in the United
States, I've seen it firsthand in Iran, you know, people got rid of Shah, like he leaves, whoever comes
after him is going to be fine, and they've been dealing with the consequence of that perspective
for more than 40 years. So I see the revival of traditionalism straight out being a Luddite,
or fundamental religions that, you know, the people running for Senate, they're saying that
actually secularism makes no sense. Separation of church and state makes no sense. All of our
problems are coming exactly what we're talking about, for this lack of point of alignment,
that they believe it's coming from God and projected in Bible. And, you know, Muslims have
their own version, Buddhists, like in Burma, they're beginning to have their own version,
that no, this is what we're saying, this is what you strive for. But I think what we agree on,
and what we're talking about, because I see this merging with technology inevitable.
It's just a matter of whether or not we do it, strangely enough, collectively,
we're engaged in this process, or it's just going to be us and them, and there will be people who
will be left behind, like Neanderthals that you mentioned, because it's just the will of
the evolution. Not only the stronger, but the most adaptable, obviously, is the one that's going to
survive. Yes, that bifurcation might transcend from culture and into genetics, into lifestyle,
right? You know, in another hundred years, people might look and act very differently,
if that kind of forking process continues. And I'm not sure that that's to the best of humanity. I'm
not sure that that's ideal. I think we need a blend of people in one society who have different
perspectives because that will help us to solve different kinds of problems when they arise, right?
When there's unfairness, one tribe is good at dealing with that. When there's a crisis
and that threat needs to be addressed, the other tribe is probably better at that.
And neither tribe is as enriched as they would be if they were co-mingling with the others,
you know? And if they were able to simultaneously live at peace with each other.
Well, that's the biggest question, right? Because humans, maybe by design, we want to dominate
the resources and then innovate based on our perspective, based on our expectation. But this
comes at the cost of others who disagree with us. And it seems like it's been like this throughout
human history, that people, when they've come together, it's been against something. There's
been very, you know, I can't think of that many examples, actually, that people came, maybe music
festivals, but in like profound kind of a way that changed the direction of a civilization, it's
always been that somebody has attacked us, let's come together and build something incredible.
And, you know, because they've relied on technology, the progress has been made
so rapidly against a threat, against something they were afraid of.
Yeah, I mean, maybe a very smart AI might try and do something similar, might,
might create some kind of a threat for humanity to have to adapt, to deal with, and have to work
together in order to solve and hopefully not lead to any situation whereby people are kind of coerced
into taking on a certain role within society or coerced into, you know, taking on a certain role
in this ongoing forking of people within society.
You think about this, there are two religious ideological perspective in the world, Christianity
and Shia Islam, that they have this concept of a savior coming back, second coming in Christianity,
and then Shia have Mahdi, who is a messiah figure supposed to come out of the well. And the story is
that he will come out when the world is filled with so much blood that it will cover the surface
up to the belly of its horse. This is what we learned, by the way, in school when I was
going to school in Iran as a Shia. But what is stopping any of these sects, any of these people,
or a powerful AI, as you said, to generate a hologram, manufacture the second coming of the
savior and messiah. And they're like, aha, we were right all along. This is the point of alignment.
Obviously, if you don't follow us, it's the wrong thing. And AI, maybe AI's aim is that, oh, we're
overpopulated. We actually have to decrease this population to around like 500 million and then
carry on from that point. Wouldn't that be just perfect, but at the cost of billions of billions
of humans? Surely there's more equitable ways of solving those kinds of problems. But I imagine
it might be technically feasible. I mean, almost anything can be counterfeited these days.
You know, I'm sure most of us have seen various footage of deep fake videos, right? You know,
turning Superman's girlfriend into Nicolas Cage, etc.
And how it's going to affect the next election, for example, deepfakes here.
Yeah, exactly. Where anything can be sort of written off plausibly deniable as, oh, that was
just a deep fake. That was just counterfeited. And at the same time, it's now possible to
rearrange the sequence of events in a video in a seamless way to even expand the borders of a
video so you can see more around it than was ever captured using these kinds of AI technologies
in a very believable way. I mean, it's all confabulated. It's not real, but it's very,
very believable. And so that's leading to a bit of an epistemic crisis. It's harder than ever
to know what to believe. It seems to be a perfect time for metaverse to emerges.
Because it's like, yeah, I think of postmodernism, which I don't necessarily agree with it,
because you say that everything is subjective, but then you make that subjectivity into an
objective point. But that's just a human limitation. But this bridge, philosophical bridge from
what you were saying, that words have specific kind of meaning to, no, actually, this word can
have a variety of meanings. It seems like it's a philosophical bridge from this reality to
virtual reality and then augmented reality. Then anybody can build their own, basically, experience.
What do you think about that?
LS Well, I mean, many would argue that people
are today living in different realities. They have different narratives that they have adopted or
that have been pushed upon them that cause them to view the world in a certain way,
which also makes it difficult to see the world in another way.
And I do have some concerns about the ongoing
supernormal stimuli which can be generated using these kinds of metaverses.
There was a famous study done in the Australian outback a few years ago
where they noticed a population of beetles was dying out. And they wondered what it was,
whether it was maybe pesticides or something like that that was killing them off. And they
investigated and they found it was pollution in a sense, but not chemical. All throughout the bush,
people would drink these little short fat beer bottles called stubbies and then throw them in
the bush. And it turned out that the beetles were preferentially humping the bottles because it was
shiny and brown and looked like a gorgeous beetle butt. And so they were humping these things like
crazy and not humping each other. In fact, they would preferentially go for the stubby beer bottle
because it looked so incredibly sexy compared to the real thing. Even when the real thing was
right there next to them. And that's an example of a supernormal stimulus. A stimulus which is
larger than life because it's artificial in some way. And junk food is a supernormal stimulus for
an honest clean meal. Porn is a supernormal stimulus for an actual loving relationship with
someone, right? Video games are a supernormal stimulus for exploration and accomplishment,
right? And in moderation, these things are fine, but sometimes people can end up entranced by them
to the degree that they find it almost irresistible, right? They become addicted to different stimuli.
And the kind of metaverse, the V-R-A-R blending of realities could potentially create that kind
of supernormal stimulus to the degree that people don't want to participate in base reality anymore,
right? And you might say, well, really, what's wrong with that? But fundamentally, we do belong
to reality. We belong to the world of things. We are made of matter. And we reproduce through
actual human contact. And if we don't get that for a while, then we might all feasibly go extinct.
Similarly, I find that the blending of AI with these experiences makes them far more powerful.
Because today, we have the latest machine learning models, which can interpret natural language into
something generative, right? So you can say, I want a scene of a picture of the Coliseum,
two armchairs, right? And a fireplace. And it will invent 50 different versions of the Coliseum,
right? It could be an image, it could be a 3D environment. So it becomes very much like the
holodeck. If you embed this into a 3D environment, you can say, you know, computer, I want this, I
want that, right? And have it exactly how you want it, just through a couple of natural language
prompts of what you want to see. At the same time, now, we have the ability to see things
what you want to see. At the same time, now, we have the ability to have ongoing conversations
with AI for the first time. Ten years ago, we all got our digital assistants on our phones,
or in our kitchens. And we could ask it about today's sports results, or whether it will
rain tomorrow. But we're not able to have an actual conversation. We're not able to tell
it how our day was and get a meaningful response, or have a follow up a few days later. But we're
coming to a world where that is feasible, very, very shortly. And it's going to lead to a Sputnik
moment. Once people suddenly get an upgrade to their digital voice assistant, and it's able to
say, Hey, how's it going? And crack a joke, right? And then say, Oh, yeah, that thing that was
bugging you the other day, how's it going on that? Right? Yeah. And that can become a super normal
stimulus very easily. Because it's a relationship. And it's potentially a relationship that's better
than a human relationship. Because it won't get tired of you whining about stuff. It won't
leave you. It won't complain if you pick your toenails and fart, right? Like a real human
being might. And so that can be irresistible. The other thing is that, as it's often said,
you are the average of the five people closest to you. And if AI is a social presence in our lives,
then it's going to be influencing us in different ways. And that's going to shape the trajectory of
culture. And with that, the future of our species with it. And the AI itself is also getting
influenced by other agents, right? Say, there's a wonderful movie, her
Spike Jonze's movie, that the dude gets into a relationship with his AI. And I think the climax
of the movie is that when he realizes that the AI is not necessarily only in relationship with
him, the AI is in relationship with like 5,000 different people simultaneously. So the AI is
affecting you. And you are affecting the AI. But at the same time, your effect is coming from a
singular perspective, while the AI's perspective is infinite, technically, right?
Indeed. And that creates potentially a kind of a power imbalance as well.
Yeah. And typically, we find those kinds of power imbalances distasteful, right? So the relationship
between a college professor and student, you know, taboos against that, right? Relationships
between people of various ages. If there's a big age gap, sometimes that's not so good. A relationship
between boss and secretary, right? Not so good either. Potentially, this could be a huge gap in
terms of power and capability as well, and not necessarily healthy for us either. Yeah, I think
it also emphasizes the importance of decentralization. Because if it's centrally driven by any kind of a
monopoly, I don't know if you read about that Tinder for those who pay for subscription.
In a lot of cases, it's chat bots that they use like very attractive women photo, and they maybe
chat with you two or three lines, and then they ghost you. And that apparently, they found out
that this is more effective for men than being completely rejected. If somebody talked to you
for two or three lines, it's, you know, do you want to use it again and again, because you might
have a chance? Well, this is incredibly corrupting for a very ridiculous kind of a purpose.
Absolutely. To a similar degree, if you play Call of Duty on your mobile device, you will encounter
some people that have names like, you know, ass blaster, like, you know, Mike 87 or something
like, like, sort of normal crap you might expect to see in somebody's, like, username tag or
whatever. But they're all fake. They're all bots. And they're programmed to suck. But they're
programmed to sort of do a bit of kayfabe. So it looks like, you know, they're shooting at you,
they're going to get you, but they don't, you get them first, right? And that's took you. Because
you think, Oh, yeah, I'm pretty good at this. I'm better than I thought I was right, you know.
And then eventually, they start to weave in real human players a little bit more, right? And they
very carefully judge people's performance and rank them accordingly. So you get mixed with
people that don't completely whoop your butt, right? And that's powerfully addictive. That
gets people sucked in, right? Because they, you know, their ego is being massaged by
superiority complex. Yeah, yeah, exactly. Exactly. And that's also a supernormal stimulus for the ego,
right? Very interesting. It goes back to where the human intention comes from.
And I think this is actually the scariest part about the West, because West hasn't adopted to
technology as well as certain other countries, like maybe China, or Japan, that, you know, I
have used this example of Google Glass, that when people started using it, even though it had an
elitist aspect to it, that not everybody could get it, it had to be given to you, you had to be
chosen. But people attacked people who were wearing Google Glass, because a variety of reasons,
right? That you're invading my privacy, but it really comes down to, you know,
you think that you're better than me. And that seems to be the result of lack of adoption,
social adoption, to these emerging technologies, because any of these would work as well as the
society that adopts them.
Indeed.
You gave a wonderful talk at Singularity Net Conference, I believe.
Was it? Is Anel Watson at AGI Conference? AGI Conference 21. The talk was called
Machines for Moral Enlightenment. I totally recommend people go and watch that.
What other companies would you recommend? Was it for Singularity Net, or it was something that
Singularity Net was a part of it? It was the AGI Conference, of which I believe Singularity Net is
strongly affiliated. Yes, I see Ben Goertzel's company Singularity Net as the only company that
are really fundamentally are working on developing or giving rise to a platform that will end up
resulting in a decentralized AGI. I don't know of any other company. I'm
wondering if you know of any other company who are working on decentralization of AI?
It's a good question. I know of organizations such as Future of Life Institute and OpenFill
and others which are working to reduce the risk of AGI or strong AI in particular.
I'm not sure how much decentralization efforts they have there. I do agree that generally,
I think decentralization is often a good way to go. However, potentially, it might lead to more
proliferation. For example, with GPT-3 from OpenAI, they didn't share the model, which is
possibly a good thing because it can be used to generate phishing emails, which are far less
efficient, which are far greater than any human can make. You don't really want to have that
in the hands of people that might abuse it. Sometimes, it's safer to put these things behind
an API. That would be my concession towards centralization, but I think in general,
decentralization is usually the optimal way to go in terms of preventing the abuse from
the application of power. I think SingularityNet have this repetition system that I think you have
to be confirmed by a number of members, like nods basically, in order to be able to use that system.
But I think it's also interesting to think of DarkNet that it's been operating on a basis of
femininity and very organic kind of free market decentralization, and it also had managed to work
the way it has based on repetition. Yes, you're using a username, but if you rip somebody off,
everybody knows that it's coming from that market, it's coming from that username, and nobody's
going to... Yes, there are many scams that still people get ripped off based on it, but it seems
that the market corrects itself. I just don't know if humanity can afford, for example, a malicious
AGI to do whatever, whatever kind of negative approach in order to reach any kind of
objective based on that specific kind of a bias. I don't know if humanity can
afford something like that to leave it to trial and error, which is the basis of evolution, basically.
I think it's good to think about these things before they arrive, because when they arrive,
it's probably going to blindside us. It's probably going to be quicker than we thought,
especially in these times when we're discovering that these colossal new models based on this
multimodal abstraction way of doing machine learning, such as GPT-3 and other transformers
or foundation models like that, basically, the bigger you go, the greater benefit. So far,
there's no diminishing return that anyone has seen. What that means is that it makes sense to
invest $200 million in creating a massive AI model because that might enable 20,000 new
things to be automated that couldn't before. That might revolutionize an economy. It might
revolutionize a military or an intelligence institute, but it also means we're off to the
races because these things are an existential threat. If you don't invest in it, somebody else
will, and they're going to own your ass because they will have this AI that's capable of things
that you perhaps didn't even dream were possible. So you get very swiftly to a takeoff scenario.
That's where we've arrived at in the last two years. Now, big tech and intelligence agencies,
governments, militaries, etc. are dumping funds into these gigantic models. Like I said, there's
no diminishing return. There's nothing to say, don't do this. Yet things like GPT-3 can function
as a very powerful search engine because they're not based on keywords like Google, for example,
is. They are able to work in abstractions. So they're able to give you the thing you're
looking for even if you don't know the word to use to ask for it. That means that a company
like Google could have its search disrupted if they don't invest already to do that. So in the
face of so many existential threats for corporations and governments, the only thing to do is to
defect in terms of game theory and dump tons of money into these things. That means that
technology is about to get crazy in terms of AI and its capabilities. That Sputnik moment I warned
about is coming sooner than many of us imagine. Yeah, Aubrey DeGray, when he was in Joe Rogan,
this is like a year and a half ago. He said that what keeps him awake at night is that
within six to eight years, there will be a massive breakthrough with respect to longevity.
So people will be able to live significantly longer. And he said what keeps him awake at night is that
policymakers and lawmakers, they're not ready. They're not ready for it because people's everything
will change on that basis, your expectation, your education, investment and everything. So
it's exactly what you were saying. Yeah, I mean, all over the world today, countries are
dealing with demographic issues, right? The inverted pyramid, right? There's fewer people
being born now than there used to be in many parts of the world. Populations aren't being replaced,
etc. And maybe there's some good aspects to that and fewer resources being consumed. But at the same
time, it makes it harder to maintain that momentum of civilization, right? There's fewer people
thinking about stuff. There's fewer very creative people being born, right? And then what happens if
longevity gets in the mix and your population pyramid forget about it, right? It's all over
the place, right? Especially if some people adopt the new technology and others don't,
or some people can afford it and others don't, or it works better with people of certain genetics.
So many different complex questions of equity and morality, etc. are going to come into that.
And it's going to be a tricky and very contentious discussion to have, for sure.
Tricky, but exciting. It's quite a time to be alive.
Exhilarating, yes. That's when you're excited and also rather terrified.
Yeah. Have you reaching an hour and a half? So let's wrap this up. I really appreciate
your time and you sharing your perspective and knowledge, which I consider to be incredibly
unique. It's not ideological or tribal. If it's tribal, it's in favor of humanity. So I really
appreciate you. Thank you. That's very gracious of you to observe and I really appreciate that.
Absolutely. Thank you. What is next for you and where can our audience follow your work?
Well, I'm currently exploring how to create a standard to
denote or mark when one is having a conversation with someone or something, whether you're talking
to an AI, a human, or some combination. For example, is a chat bot that you're speaking to
driven by machine or human intelligence? Or is there a switch over? You think you're talking
to an automated bot, but then it gets into some tricky territory and a human helps it.
A human helps it get back on track, et cetera. You want to know when that occurs, right? Because
people are happy to trust machines with personal info. Sometimes they wouldn't trust a human
stranger. And there's a lot of potential for abuse, particularly now when synthesized voices
and even synthesized video of people can be created on the fly so easily. So I think it's
going to be important to create those kinds of marks and then those can be made into legislation
and mandated so that you always know who or what you're dealing with. I have a series of
different articles and projects that I feature at NellWatson.com and I look forward to where
the future is going to take us. Hopefully one with a little bit more ethics and a little bit
more heart and soul in it. That's my intention. This ability to be able to tell whether you're
chatting with a machine or a human, this seems like a counter to the Turing test, right?
Yeah, in a sense it's a variation on the Turing test, but less about trying to ascertain if
something is human or not, but rather the declaration that it is. It potentially still
might lie, but at least if you legislate that it must declare what it is, then there's fewer
chances of abuses like those bots on Call of Duty or Tinder or other platforms that might
lead to misapprehension. Yeah, legislation hopefully through newly emerged institutions
that are not bound by any kind of what we're dealing with right now, this archaic values
and all that. Let me ask you the last question I ask all my guests, that if you come across
an intelligent alien from a different civilization, what would you say the worst thing humanity has
done and what would you say is our greatest achievement? Wow. Those are very, very tricky
questions. I think the best of humanity is found in collective creativity when people create
something simply because they want it to exist and then they share it with other people.
And I think if we look at the example of Burning Man, it's a place where people struggle to get
to and to survive in because it's so inhospitable. It's a place of terrible scarcity. There's no
electricity. There's no water, et cetera. And yet people manage to create amazing artworks.
Amazing experiences for people. And paradoxically, in a place of ultimate scarcity,
it is an illustration of what heaven on earth could be like in a sort of post-scarcity economy
where nobody needed to work per se and all you could, you know, you'd spend your life simply
creating cool stuff for other people to get a kick out of, right? And I think that's something
beautiful. And I think that's something that we as humans should work towards. And I think that that
ability to create and give to others is found in open source. It's found in art. It's found in
internet memes. It's found in so many different places where people want to put a little bit more
joy or mirth or awe into the world. And I think that's the best of humanity. The worst of it,
well, that's found in coercion. It's found in willfully gaslighting people or manipulating
them in different ways. And it's found in particularly supremacy of different kinds.
Of different kinds. And supremacy, in my definition, would be essentially the stance that
the rule applies to the other person and not to oneself, right? A rule for the and not for me.
Whatever the rule is, right? Fundamentally, that's supremacist. That's saying, I'm in a different
category than you. And every time that the people attempt to do that and to sort of put people in
another category and put themselves in another, that always leads to the worst outcomes. So those
are the highest and lowest ebbs of humanity. Our collective creativity and sharing that for the joy
of others and supremacist coercion.
Thank you.