I just wonder once we're able to decode our emotions and quantify them, how can we apply
them in a way that augments our intelligence and gives us these superpowers across the
board?
Hello, and welcome to the 78th episode of Neohuman Podcasts.
I'm Agabahari, an ecologist on Twitter and Instagram, and you can follow the show on
LiveInLimbo.com, iTunes, YouTube, BitChute, and soon on Spotify.
And today with me, I have Rana El-Kalyoubi.
Welcome to Neohuman Podcasts, Rana.
Thank you for having me.
It's a pleasure.
Let's start with your background, the work you've done, the lives you've lived, and
what are you mainly focused on now these days?
Well, I am co-founder and CEO of an MIT startup called Affectiva, and we are on a mission
to humanize technology by building artificial emotional intelligence, so I can say a little
bit more about that.
But also, I just launched my book, Girl Decoded, and it's a memoir, so it's an intertwining
of my personal story and the story of the technology I've built.
Are you originally from Egypt?
That's right.
I was born in Egypt.
I'm Egyptian, now Egyptian-American, but then I also grew up in Kuwait and Abu Dhabi.
How old were you when you left the region?
I was born in Cairo, and then we were in Kuwait until the first Gulf War, so I was about 10
when we had to evacuate our home there.
And then I was in Abu Dhabi until I finished high school, studied computer science at the
American University in Cairo, and then moved to Cambridge University at about 19 years
old.
And I've been back and forth a lot since then.
Yeah, the reason I ask because it's very important, I think, to have the perspective about those
kind of societies with respect to technology and artificial intelligence and governance
and all of that.
And I want to talk to you about all of that in the next, hopefully, an hour, maybe a little
more.
But let's start with your book.
The book is called Geralt Dakota, The Scientist's Quest to Reclaim Our Humanity by Bringing
Emotional Intelligence to Technology.
What made you write a book, and what the book is all about, and what are you trying to express
mainly to the audience?
I would say I initially wanted to write the book because I wanted to really tell the world
about emotion AI and what are the applications of it and what are the ethical and moral implications.
And as I started writing the book, I also realized that my own path to coming to this
is really unique, and I had to overcome a lot of cultural and societal norms and find
my own voice.
So I really wanted to be a story about humanity and just kind of an inspirational story for
everybody out there that's trying to figure out their own career and kind of sense of
purpose.
What made you interested in artificial intelligence?
You know, it was really kind of this realization that technology changes the way we connect
as humans.
So it's a very human story.
It's not about the technology.
It's really about how we connect and communicate.
And when I first got to Cambridge University for my PhD, I realized I was spending so much
time on my device like all of us do, yet this machine had absolutely no clue how I was feeling.
And even worse, it was the main device I used to communicate with my family back home because
international calls were and still are very expensive.
And I realized that a lot of the richness of, you know, I come from the Middle East, so
we're very emotive and very expressive.
And I felt like all of the richness of this nonverbal communication kind of disappeared
in cyberspace.
And that got me, I started asking a question like, what if machines could understand human
emotions just like we do?
And that was 20 years ago.
So I've been on this journey for the past 20 years trying to build that.
I was looking forward to talk to you because I've talked to a number of people in the field
of AI, but every single one of them have been with respect to thinking side of our brain
and thinking side of, you know, the society.
The emotional AI, it was the first time that I heard about it.
And it's actually pretty consistent because IQ, I knew about since it was maybe four,
three, five, something like that.
But EQ, I learned about, which is emotional intelligence in my 20s.
So what is the definition of emotional AI and what are the implications of it?
Yeah, let's start with humans, you're absolutely right.
So if you look at the research in the past, like 60, 70 years, our IQ matters, your cognitive
intelligence matters, but actually your emotional intelligence matters just as much in day to
day life.
So people who have higher EQs, which is your emotional quotient, your ability to read and
understand and adapt to other people's emotions, they tend to be more likable.
They're more persuasive.
They're better managers.
They have more successful professional and personal lives.
And I believe that that's true for technology as well, especially technology that is mainstream
and interacts with us on a daily basis.
So you're right.
A lot of the focus on AI is about automation and being more efficient and more productive.
Okay.
But what about it being more humane and helping us be more human and more empathetic and more
connected with each other, which are very important parts of life as well.
And so that's been my focus to try and bring that EQ element into AI.
There's also the elements of automation with respect to emotional AI as well, right?
Let me just read for, because some people watch this, some people will listen to it.
This is a description of emotion measurement technology that is a technology that your
company pursues and says, effective as technology enables software application to use a webcam
to track a user's smirks, smiles, frowns, and furrows, which measures a user's level
of surprise, amusement, or confusion.
The technology also allows a person's heart rate to be measured from a webcam without
the person wearing a sensor.
So a lot of positive application, but I'm sure a lot of people are freaked out about
it too, because we are dealing with text-based and image-based and video-based kind of social
media and content creation at this point, and everybody's losing their mind at how
these data is being collected, who owns it, and all the biases that exist about interpreting
those data.
So I would imagine how is this going to affect every day kind of a person if you can look
at it from purely a user base, because this is a technology that you guys, I believe,
are licensing to different companies?
Kind of.
I can talk about the applications.
Okay.
Let's start with that.
And then I want to talk about in the societal scale, because it's not only going to be
a webcam, it's going to be, if there is a surveillance camera on the street, this will
be a technology that will be used there for good reasons and also negative reasons, because
it's a tool.
Right?
It depends on human intention how they want to use it.
Right.
Yes.
And I feel very passionately about that.
And we as a company have drawn a very clear line on where we want to see this technology
being used and where we will just not license the technology or build products for industries.
So I want to start with the positives first, because I really do think, I mean, I'm biased
because I'm passionate about this, but I really do think there are real transformative use
cases for this technology.
As a company, we're very focused on the automotive industry, where, you know, if you have a sensor
in the vehicle that can detect signs of distraction or signs of drowsiness, levels of drowsiness,
if you are moderately drowsy or severely drowsy or even asleep, we've seen examples of people
like literally driving while they're asleep.
Well, the car can take action.
The car can alert you.
It can even take more aggressive action, like, you know, if it's a Tesla, for example, and
it has semi-autonomous capabilities, it can say, well, you know what, I'm going to be
a better driver than you are right now because you're so tired.
I'm taking over control.
So I think this kind of human machine partnership, especially in the context of automotive, can
really increase the safety of our roads.
Another example is we now have child seat detectors and we can detect if there are children
left behind in the car.
This doesn't happen a lot, but when it happens, it's obviously horrific for the parents because
often these children just die of heat in the vehicle.
So that's another example where technology can act as the ears and eyes inside the car.
So that's one use case.
Another amazing use case.
So animals when they're being left in the car.
Absolutely.
That's another one too, exactly.
Another one, which I'm very passionate about is the whole area of health and especially
mental health.
We did a lot of work in autism.
It was the first project.
It was actually the project that brought me over to the United States.
So we were building like a Google Glass like device that can give real time feedback to
kids on the autism spectrum about like nonverbal signals and making face and eye contact.
We also have people who are looking into like early signs of Parkinson's.
You can use this to detect stress, anxiety, depression.
So there's really a lot of potential.
I'm not saying we're there yet.
There needs to be a lot more work to be done.
But it can, I mean, we're in front of our machines all the time.
So that could be an opportunity to really understand your baseline.
And if we start seeing a deviation from that, we can flag that to you or a family member
or a clinician.
So that's another area where it can be really transformative.
So what you said with respect to cars, it sounds like that it can be used as a bridge
to full autonomy.
Because by the time that cars can drive themselves, whatever state the driver is in, it doesn't
really matter because the car is in charge.
But we are, I don't know how far we are away from that.
But again, the issue of privacy, which I think we have to really move on beyond the conventional
definition of privacy, that it's non-existent at this point.
Because a lot of data is being collected.
But it's just a matter of who's collecting them.
How are they using them?
And also very important, I think, is that why aren't users getting paid for the data
that they're generating?
I hear you.
I'm absolutely on the same page with you.
So when we first started the company, my co-founder, who's an MIT professor, Rosalind Picard, and
I kind of sat around her kitchen table and we were like, OK, there are so many applications
of this technology.
What are we going to say yes to and what are we going to say no to?
And we decided on a set of core values to help us make these decisions.
So one is respecting that this is very personal data.
And so everything we do, we do on a consent and opt-in basis.
So any application where people don't know that they're being recorded or they're being
kind of tracked, then we basically decline that.
And that has implications on surveillance, for example.
We never do anything in the surveillance or security or lie detection space, because usually
people or consumers don't really know.
They might know that the cameras are there, but they don't really know how it's being
used.
The second is this transparency around usage.
I mean, even now with all of our devices, you get these long, like, five-page agreements
and you just click, I agree, because nobody reads them because they're too complicated
and they're not transparent.
And we're big advocates of just a very clear, plain English consenting form.
We're going to turn on the camera.
Here's how we're going to use the data.
Here's what you're getting in return for it.
I think we need more tech companies to kind of adopt that approach.
And then the third is what we're calling power asymmetry.
If you look around, a small number of companies and governments have access to the majority
of the data.
There's this power asymmetry.
And I think we need to rebalance that to your point.
Like, if I'm going to give up such personal data, like, what am I getting in return for
it?
And I think it could be monetary.
It could be other types of value, but we need to rebalance the power here.
Yeah, the reason I'm talking about the monetary aspect of it is because we're talking a lot
right now about how a lot of jobs are not going to come back, like 40% of jobs, supposedly.
And people are talking about universal basic income and how we can...
And I'm like, we are becoming our own careers just by generating data because these companies
are collecting data.
We're becoming trillionaires.
And users, not only they don't own their data, they're not getting anything in return.
So you might once in a while get like 1200 bucks check in the mail, which is just laughable
and think about, hey, how am I going to...
And it just seems like this process of automation and digitization, it's not going to stop with
where are we right now?
Because at some point, we're talking about emotional AI right now.
But what will happen when we have, at some point, nanobots monitoring inside of our body
for all the good reasons, right?
But we becoming this data generators, I don't want to misuse the term, but it really can
suggest that at some point, if there will be very few people at the top with these massive
corporations and companies, you will be slave data generators who are creating a lot of
opportunities and a lot of wealth for very few people and you get nothing in return.
So it's a big concern aside from the privacy aspect of it.
Yes, I agree with that.
And there has to be a different data model, a monetization and model here, business model.
One of the reasons I wrote the book is I really wanted the consumer, the average consumer
to be part of this conversation.
And what you find is because AI is such a black box and a lot of people have a lot of
misconceptions around what it is, how does it work, then the average consumer is not
part of this dialogue.
And I think as this evolves in terms of ethics and business models and who owns the data,
all of these dialogues, I think we need everybody around the table to ensure that it works for
all of us.
What are your thoughts on decentralization of data using blockchain?
I think that that is very interesting.
I haven't seen it done in our space, so there's probably actually some potential for innovation
there.
Yeah, but I do think that that is interesting.
Yeah, because the concept of trust itself, it seems like it's not really reliable to
say, well, we don't trust this CEO, let's replace him with another CEO.
It's just that transparency and the community owning the data that is being shared on a
decentralized basis seems like a more viable kind of an approach rather than relying on
any specific kind of individual.
Yeah, absolutely.
So the book is called Girl Decoded, a scientist quest to reclaim our humanity by bringing
emotional intelligence to a technology.
What are some of the elements of humanizing machines and technology from your perspective
that needs to be taken in a very solid kind of a steps moving into this crazy decade that
is ahead of us?
I think there's a few things.
So first of all, it's this kind of going back to this idea that we need to marry IQ and
EQ in all of our technology platforms and take a very human centered approach to designing
this.
So to designing, building and deploying it.
For me, when we sit around the table and design, what is the next version of a conversational
agent going to look like?
It can't just be about the transactional function of that device.
It has to also include the human elements and I think that's really important.
And then I really, if you kind of dissect how people communicate, only 10% of the way
we communicate is in the choice of words we use, 90% is nonverbal and it's split kind
of equally between your facial expressions, your hand gestures and your vocal intonations.
So I think, and especially now that we are connecting with this pandemic, a lot of our
communication is becoming virtual, whether in the way we conduct business or in the way
kids are learning or even patient doctors are connecting.
I think we're going to see a layer of innovation that incorporates emotion AI to quantify these
nonverbal signals and then you can draw all sorts of really interesting insights.
One example, actually two examples if you don't mind, because I feel very passionate
about those.
I've had to pivot away from what you would expect a book tour to look like and I've been
doing these virtual book events and these typically involve, I'm giving a Zoom or a
live stream to hundreds of people and I can't see any of them.
And it's so hard because you can't really rip off their energy the way you would in
a live auditorium.
But I imagine if emotion AI was integrated, you could get real time feedback.
I could just aggregate everybody's emotional engagement and I could see if they find, you
know what I say, interesting, are they engaged, are they totally confused, are they bored
to death?
So I think that's one area that's really powerful.
And then how we connect with our teams, right?
Like I have a global team and now that we're all kind of dispersed and working from home,
I just keep wondering like, is the team engaged, you know, are they committed, are they stressed?
And I just want to know because then I can be proactive as a leader, so I miss that.
That's fascinating.
I'm just thinking as a speaker, you can wear a glass and become a forensic psychologist,
a public speaking guru and it gives you real time data that you can tweak yourself according
to that.
And then the question would be what would be the difference between human response and
this information and data that is being collected and presented to humans by machines, right?
Because that's one of the arguments that Elon Musk is making for Neuralink that our biggest
disconnect with the machines is the rate of input.
That's so interesting.
That's a very big consideration.
For example, we generate, like our technology generates about like, you know, at 30 frames
a second, about 50 or 60 variables, right, and that's overwhelming, right?
So a big part of what we do is distilling all of that information to the top highlights,
like what is the key nuggets of data and it's actually non-trivial to your point.
It's really, it is really a hard part of the problem and how do you visualize it?
Do you want to show me a real time graph?
And who prioritizes it?
Is it going to be like a dumber AI or is there going to be like a third party human?
Yeah, that too, like, you know, in our automotive work, that actually comes up a lot, right?
Like when we're working with car companies or even social robotic companies and we give
them this data feed, they're like, whoa, what do we do with this?
Like, tell us what values to look at.
And you know, there's various ways you can do this with thresholding and whatnot, but
also reinforcement learning is another approach that automate some of that feedback loop around
what data matters the most.
So it's an unsolved problem, but it's a really fascinating one.
Yeah.
This problem of bias is a very important one because it leaks into ethics and morality
as well.
And then what kind of ethics and morality because the kind of ethics and morality that
we are dealing with here in the United States, even here, it's not unified, right?
You can go from community to community, they have their own priorities, but it's drastically
different when we go to Egypt, where you're from, or Iran, where I'm from.
And I just don't know, is there any?
Hang on.
Do you mind?
No, no, no.
Absolutely.
Can you open the lights?
Like, we have a sudden thunderstorm here, so like, like, it's just bizarre.
Yeah.
So I can't record right now because it's boring, and you can hear it in the center.
Can you hear the pouring in our recording?
No, not really.
No.
Okay.
So we're good.
Perfect.
Bye.
Sorry about that.
Yeah.
Here, weather is kind of weird, too.
We're in South Florida.
It's just a strange year.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
Like, right.
Just a thunderstorm and the big skew of things.
It's fine.
So I apologize for interrupting.
No, it's all good.
Yeah.
Have you, have you come across any kind of this, I don't know where your technology
is being used as mainly United States or globally, but have you come across this difference between
priorities with respect to ethics and morality based on social values and cultural values?
Yes, we have.
So our technology is deployed in 90 countries around the world, and I also, I'm involved
with the World Economic Forum, so I'm a young global leader and I sat on the Global Future
Council for Robotics and AI for a number of years, was a very international council.
And I was just fascinated by how different countries have different values around ethics
and AI and privacy and all of these considerations.
So for example, our biggest competitor is a Chinese company and they have access to
a ton of data and a ton of funding and they're very aligned with their government.
And a lot of this is about access to data, as you know, right, especially in this AI
and technology space.
So and I, you know, I think it's really interesting.
We have very strong core values and we've decided to take a particular path and be advocates
for what we believe is ethical AI, but I recognize that it's not universal.
What we have found, though, is that like-minded businesses select us, right, because they
too care about ethics and they want to be seen as the kind of the ethics friendly company
to partner with.
That's been really true for car companies in particular.
So I don't know, I'm hopeful that, again, one reason why we need consumers to really
be educated about this is then consumers can have a strong voice and say, you know, I'm
going to buy technology from this company because they're ethical, but not this other
company because they don't meet kind of the ethics standards.
Yeah, also keeping big tech companies responsible for working with systems that are not necessarily
ethical, right?
Because it's interesting, you mentioned the Chinese company because now it's a huge contrast
between Western approach and the Chinese approach and then how the business interests sometimes
can jeopardize the ethical and the Western value kind of an approach and how we're going
to move forward.
As you said, you know, companies with more access to data will have a far greater chance
of dominating because that's, you know, why wouldn't you if you have a good technology,
why wouldn't you want to dominate?
So it seems like...
One other thing that you also brought up that is really important is bias, especially in
our space.
And you may have seen that in the news over the past 18 months or so.
Some facial recognition systems have been kind of criticized for discriminating or not
being accurate or being biased against certain subpopulations, including women of color,
right?
And the reason this is the case, if you look closely at it, is because the training data
is very homogeneous.
It's usually middle-aged white guys, right?
Why is that?
Well because that data seems to be the most readily accessible.
I mean, we at Affectiva, I have this kind of example anecdote where we work with a lot
of the car companies around the world and this one particular global brand, it's a global
automaker, luxury automaker based in Europe and they wanted us to test the accuracy of
our algorithm.
So they sent us a data set and we looked at the data set and it was literally like, you
know, East European, middle-aged, blue-eyed, blonde guys, right?
And we could have totally tested this data set, probably done great, and sent it back
to the car company and moved on.
But we had an internal meeting and we said, that's just not right.
This is a global car company.
It's almost our social and moral responsibility to flag that to them and educate them, right?
And so we sent back a report, we said, okay, you know, we really recommend that we go back
out and collect a more diverse data set with different ethnicities, different genders,
different age range ranges, even, you know, people wearing glasses or having beards like
you do, right?
Like there were very few people who looked like you in that data set.
And that's really important.
So we did that and I think that built a lot of credibility with that car company.
But it just made me realize that, and it was unintended, right?
It's not like they did that on purpose.
They just didn't think that the diversity of the data is important and it's so key.
And that's where the diversity of the team becomes even like really critical.
Because we're such a diverse team, we were able to say, hang on a second, nobody looks
like me in this data set, right?
That's not cool.
So I think bias is, to me actually, it's the number one biggest area for concern I have
around these technologies.
Because if we're not careful, we can just perpetuate all of the biases that exist in
society and just kind of replicate them at scale.
But bias can also be reversed, right?
In a sense that, hey, we want to focus on diversity, therefore we don't care how good
you are as a white team or a white CEO, we just want to replace you with like a brown
person or a black person, right?
Because that's also a problem.
It's a very human thing that we say, hey, we want to fix some problem and let's just
destroy all the structure that we already have.
We don't even care how well it's working.
So yeah, I mean, I think humans are very biased and we're not necessarily always objective.
And I think technology can bring a little bit more objectivity into this.
I mean, hiring is another area where humans are really biased and technology can help
reduce that bias, but we have to be careful about how we use it.
What you mentioned about facial recognition, the news came out last night that Amazon bans
police use of facial recognition technology for one year.
And I noticed in this article that on Monday, IBM said it was getting out of the facial
recognition business altogether.
So it's a very big deal what is happening with respect to facial recognition.
And I also want to mention to our audience, this is actually from MIT technology review,
that China has started a grand experiment in AI education.
It could reshape how the world learns.
And it's also very interesting with what you're doing, how the Chinese classrooms, they're
using machines and headbands and different kind of sensors to measure basically how focused
you are as a student, how, you know, with facial expressions and all of that.
So have you guys worked in any capacity and education area as well?
We have not.
It's not been an area of focus, but it's one that I'm actually really passionate about.
And I know that's where how you design the system and how you think about the user experience
becomes really important.
I don't know how the Chinese I don't know exactly how this Chinese company.
Let me read this very small segment.
These days, many students at Jin Hua Zhoushun Primary School in eastern China begin their
lessons not by opening textbooks, but by putting on headbands.
The headbands developed by startup BrainCo incorporated of Somerville, Massachusetts,
where you are, use three electrodes, one on the forehead and two behind the ears to detect
electrical activity in the brain sending the data to a teacher's computer, software generates
real time alerts about students attention levels and gives an analysis at the end of
each class.
Obviously, it's not going to be limited to only this kind of data and this kind of an
approach, but it gives us an idea that basically the A in AI, which I've been arguing for this
for a long time, instead of thinking of it as artificial intelligence, it is being seen
as augmented intelligence that you have a very powerful and reliable assistant that
does something that you can't even imagine like what you said, the amount of information
that your system generates 50 or 60 every second is just unimaginable for any human
to be able to do that.
But it has direct and real life consequences and positive consequences for students who
can learn better.
And it just seems like a really cool thing.
But at the same time, it comes with all the negative things because it's a tool.
It's a double-edged sword that you can use it in any kind of a direction.
Right.
And you can use exactly it.
And it's the way you design it.
If the teacher is going to use this data to reprimand students and really punish students
for not paying attention, then I'm not sure.
However, if the teacher is going to use the exact same data to identify that Joe, or that's
not a Chinese name, but a particular kid is really not engaged in this class and he or
she the teacher can really focus on that student to personalize the learning experience, I'm
all for that.
Right.
And especially again, I mean, I've been watching both my kids learn online over the last few
months.
It's terrible because class, the teacher can really gauge the level of interest and engagement
and it can, you know, she or he can adapt the learning experience online.
It's so hard to do that.
If you are, you know, if you're in a zoom classroom, it's really hard to assess level
of engagement.
Even worse, if you're doing asynchronous learning where you are just watching some video content
and learning math online, well, imagine if that learning experience, there was a little
chat bot that was monitoring your level of engagement and could notice for instance that
my 11 year old son was really fidgeting or losing interest or super confused or frustrated,
then it could interject the way an amazing teacher would.
So I think there's really incredible opportunities to democratize access to online learning in
particular.
You know, I grew up in the Middle East.
I was lucky that I had like access to amazing schools, but most people there don't have
that.
I mean, not just there, all around the world.
And I think technology can really, if you've got intelligent, like emotionally intelligent
learning systems, I think that could really be powerful in terms of engaging students
and increasing learning outcomes.
Yeah.
And on the personal basis, like one on one basis, right?
Because like what you were saying, I also went to school in Iran and my elementary school,
we were like 50 people in one class, right?
Right.
They just dumped something that they decided that, hey, this will work kind of a general
people because of the jobs that we need and screw the individual capabilities and abilities
and interests of these kids.
And here, even though it's like night and day, but it's not really that different because
you still rely on the perspective and the experience and again, bias of that individual
teacher who has to take care of maybe 20 students.
And she's like, well, this is how I've been doing it for the past 40 years.
Why do I need to change it?
Right, exactly.
And we have an opportunity with technology to augment.
I'm not saying we're going to replace teachers, but to your point about augmentation, augment
teachers with new data and with new tools that could help with this personalization.
I think that could be really powerful, but yeah, it has to be designed in the right way.
It's not about, you know, big brother, like, right?
Like we're now like going to survey all these kids and punish them.
Like if it's that, then I'm totally against it.
Which could totally be that, right?
We got to talk about it because it can be awesome or it can be what you mentioned with
respect to my beard and what we talked about about prioritizing this ocean of data to highlights.
Well, you know, if there is somebody who's not careful, they can look at me and like,
hey, we have in our data that's been prioritized by us that terrorists usually have this kind
of a beard.
So maybe this guy is a terrorist.
We're just going to put it here.
And you know, it's out of my control.
It's crude, right?
Yeah.
Seriously.
I know.
Like it's serious.
Well, I got it.
It is actually.
Yes.
Yeah.
One of the topics that we talked about is any technology works as well as a society
that adopts that technology.
How do you see this process of adopting to technology done here in the Western society
and in a society like in Egypt or in the Middle East?
I think this is where advocating for the thoughtful kind of what we call thoughtful regulation
of this technology becomes really key.
I do think there's a role for regulation here.
I don't think it should just be kept up to the individual companies or individual founders
like me.
I'm part of an organization called the Partnership on AI Consortium.
It was started by all the tech giants and now as well as Amnesty International and ACLU.
And now they have companies like Affectiva part of it too.
And the idea is we come together and we're trying to kind of build what is fair, accountable
and transparent and ethical AI and develop these best practices and work with other organizations
to implement them including legislation as well.
So I really think there needs to be a lot more conversation and a lot more work to be
done.
Now regarding how it's used in say the US versus a country like Egypt, yeah these are
very I mean there's cross-cultural differences in terms of what's acceptable and what's
not acceptable.
Again we've deployed our technology in 90 countries around the world.
We always ask for opt-in and we found that some countries the opt-in rates are really
high and in some other countries the opt-in rates are really low like Germany is our lowest
opt-in rate.
Really?
Wow.
Yeah.
Where is the highest?
I honestly don't know.
I don't know where the highest is.
Yeah I'm not sure but like they're kind of all hovering kind of around 80-90% and Germany
is at about 60%.
So there's a lot more mistrust of I don't know if it's mistrust of tech companies.
I don't know if it's you know not wanting to turn the camera on.
I don't know but I thought that was really interesting.
We had a really interesting experience with Google Glass when it came out and the way
that it came out we've been talking about that too that you couldn't even buy it.
It had to be given to you if you were selected and people didn't react to it that well you
know some of the people who were wearing Google Glass they were being attacked by people which
part of it is because of privacy but the other part is hey you're not human anymore.
You think you're better than us basically.
So that's what I mean by social adoption because for example when you look at Japan
the social adoption of technology there has been done very organically.
You go to a temple there is a robot priest that you can go and talk to and it's like
well that's how it is but there's a disconnect here right.
Some of it comes I guess from religious aspect of things that you know if you're a Christian
you say hey if you use a chip for example in your brain that's Markov the beast and
whatever I'm not saying right or wrong or whatever I think people should believe in
whatever they want to believe but there will be a point that obviously you're going to
be an empowered human being if you're using these kind of technologies and people who
are not using them will be falling behind.
This is just you know this is the bottom line.
Yeah yeah correct.
Actually on this Google Glass example we're now partnered with a company called Brain
Power and they use Google Glass and our technology as an augmentation tool for kids on the autism
spectrum.
So they've deployed about 400 of these around the US in US schools and homes and we're already
seeing that a lot of these kids you know they're improving in terms of eye and like reading
nonverbal communication.
The question is you know what happens when you take away the glasses does the learning
persist.
So again it's an example of a tool where you know if it's deployed in the right way it
can be really helpful but you do have to consider all of these social factors.
I mean when I started doing research in this area like 20 years ago when we you know remember
the days when we had like big rounded blurry webcams there was zero acceptance of cameras
right like they weren't ubiquitous we didn't really have a use case for them and now cameras
are everywhere like they're they're just part and parcel of our societal fabric.
You know the selfie movement right.
And I think that all this social acceptance has to be part of the equation you're absolutely
right and again very different across cultures.
Yeah just educating the people I guess to talk to them about it right because people
are resistant at first but when they feel like they're being left behind they rush
to stores to buy whatever it is that they want to buy but they use it but they end up
using it without really knowing why they're using it for.
You are a very impressive human being because you're in your early 40s if I'm not mistaken
and you're coming from a society that is very close with respect to women the entire Middle
East really and you're one of the very few people I would say relatively speaking who
is the leader of this new wave of artificial intelligence being built.
How would other girls and women can follow your footsteps and also I'm interested to
know how many other women relatively speaking are in the position where you are in the field
of artificial intelligence right now.
Yes I'll start by answering that question.
There's very few the answer is very few and we need a lot more so the intersection of
kind of women led AI company you know women and AI company and entrepreneur it's like
really tiny the Venn diagram is really tiny.
So I think we definitely need more women in leadership across the board but especially
in AI.
Now add to that the complexity that I am from the Middle East I have been again so lucky
that my parents supported my and my two sisters education I really owe everything to that
and I try to pay it forward with my kids for example I really do believe in the power of
education it's transformative but I also think that there are you know I grew up in a family
that supported my education but still had very strict gender roles and I had to I had
to really navigate that right like there was a lot of tensions throughout my career between
my role as you know my professional role and my aspirations and then my role as a mother
and a wife I'm now a divorcee so that didn't work out right.
So I had to really struggle with that.
My advice to young not just young but my advice to women out there who are trying to figure
that out is just really kind of I don't know for me it was really about learning to believe
in myself I have so much inner doubt it's not even funny right like I'm always doubting
myself and it's because of these deep cultural things that are ingrained in my brain that
basically say oh you know you can't be a CEO oh no no no no you can't go out and raise
money like that it's not gonna work right like all the time this voice in my head is
just putting me down you can't write a book nobody's gonna read it right well guess what
people are actually reading the book right so I just have I've had to learn to negotiate
with that inner voice in my head and it has stopped me a few times in my career for sure.
Yeah facing your fear is a very good step Joseph Campbell has a quote saying the cave
you're most afraid of has a treasure that you seek that I like that I'm gonna write
that yeah it's really good well please look it up but I'm pretty sure that it's Joseph
Campbell about the cave and the treasure and I keep saying it to my friends that whatever
do you afraid of the most that's the indicator that that's exactly what you're supposed
to be doing you know because the voice in here that's not necessarily your friend there's
actually one of my one of the books I really like is called run to the roar it's a it's
by a professional coach swash coach called Paul Asante and he talks about how you really
need to just face your like if there's something you're afraid of take it on and I kind of
like that yeah and also that kind of a fear that like you understand that because you're
also from that region that we are born into the pool of stuff that has been already determined
and decided for us and you know I I always say I was one second old I was labeled as
a Shia Muslim straight male Iranian and good luck changing any of them right every the
entire society and civilization will come after you if you decide to change any of them
but when you go through with it you realize that hey I'm I'm on my own I have my you
know my priorities a decision that I can make so it's also very interesting to me how machine
emotions and emotional analysis empowered by technology is going to separate things
that we are carrying emotionally but are not useful or productive for us yeah that is that's
an interesting way to think about it because I don't know my view is that it's not just
my view but we know that emotions cut across every aspect of our lives right like the way
we make decisions our health our memories which is an area I'm really fascinated by
and I just wonder once we're able to decode our emotions and quantify them how can we
apply them in a way that augments our intelligence and and gives us these superpowers right across
the board and I don't know like this is it's very new territory right like we still need
to figure that out yeah yeah I don't know it's really interesting I never thought about
it before saying it but this is interesting you know really interesting yeah yeah never
heard it framed that way do you know what I mean like I'm think about this one of reasons
I don't write down questions and I lose a lot of guests because of that because they're
like well send us some of the questions you want to ask because they want to be in comfort
zone and safe territories but I'm like I just don't like to do it because you know we have
this exchange and something emerges that I haven't even thought about that's the most
interesting part of all of this for me yeah that's like really interesting like this kind
of palette of emotions like which of those are relevant and which of those are yeah we'll
be able to measure them but but maybe it's useless I mean one thing that I've been thinking
a lot about in this field because it's so new people are fixated on a small subset of
emotions right like joy surprise anger fear and I'm just interested in the less celebrated
states like the state of wonder like what do people look like when they are in awe of
each other right when they're in spite when you watch a TED talk and you're inspired what
does your face look like we don't know we probably can collect the data and so things
like that I think it is just so much to discover about human how humans communicate and I and
I find that just really fascinating and exciting yeah I should also ask you we are going through
a secondary psychedelic revolution after the 60s they are making a comeback they have a
significant amount of benefits for soldiers who are coming back with PTSD for depression
and also for individuals to expand their mind if they decide to experiment with you know
whether it's LSD or psychedelic mushrooms have you thought about studying that area
because emotions are a huge part of you know you're an individual who've never experienced
psychedelics you take two grams of magic mushrooms psychedelic mushrooms and you are
experiencing a world that you did not even know existed and you're experiencing it right
here and right now the short answer is nope we have not we have not us but there has been
a little bit of work done with PTSD patients but it's more around in the in the context
of psychiatry and the clinical kind of interviewing of PTSD patients where this particular study
at USC found that virtual these patients were more forthcoming and open with a virtual agent
than they were with a real human doctor because they judged the doctor to be more judgmental
of them so that's very different than what you're saying but that's the only kind of
example where I've seen emotion AI kind of studied in that context but that's also really
fascinating yeah I think it's coming because I haven't experienced it myself so I'm like
oh you haven't you haven't no okay I'm not well I tell you I started experimenting when
I was 25 because you know I grew up in Iran and the worst thing for my mom was you do
drugs and it was just you know by the way yeah blanket statement drugs and obviously
there are some of them that are really really bad but certain psychedelics literally saved
my life because I went through a period of depression you know guilt and shame hey why
did you leave your mom and all of that and I started going see a psychologist psychotherapist
whatever and after the second session I was like well how long would it take for me to
describe who I am to this person this is never going to work out for me all right and this
was like more than ten years ago but it's becoming legal right so they legalize it in
Denver there's a place maps a multi-disciplinary association of psychedelic studies they've
been pushing for legalizing MDMA for PTSD and depression and they're looking to 2022
for a FDA approval and all that and I think these two can go together unbelievably well
because there are a lot of unknown aspect of this experience that when quantified a
lot of interesting things a lot of interesting unknowns can emerge as a result of it yeah
new territory what a fascinating world it is we're living in very how do you see the
world change in the next 10 years just for fun oh goodness um well can I even like think
about what's gonna happen next week but there's a bigger general trend right yeah yeah I really
believe that the de facto human machine interface is gonna mirror the de facto human to human
interface so the way we interact with machines will just be the way we interact with one
another through conversation through perception and through empathy and I believe that that
will not only transform human machine interactions but it will fundamentally really connect us
better with you like it will fundamentally change human to human communication as well
so I'm excited about that yeah awesome well the book is called girl decoded a scientist
quest to reclaim our humanity by bringing emotional intelligence to technology what
is next for you and where can our audience follow your work and future endeavors so I
am very easy to find on social media I've been doing a lot of live streams on LinkedIn
and you know Facebook and other platforms so please follow me there for affective I'm
just really heads down trying to bring our technology to the world and especially in
automotive so in the next few years your cars might have emotion in emotion AI enabled capabilities
which is very exciting and then for me personally I've realized with this book it's the beginning
of a journey I don't know what the journey is but my gut and my instinct just by seeing
how people are reacting to the book is that it's the beginning of a new conversation and
new connections so you know I'm kind of embarking on this new journey not knowing where it's
going to lead me but I'm excited about it this is your first book right my first book
that's awesome that I mean you you obviously are very capable and reliable kind of a leader
because you have perspective right you didn't come out of just you know a comfortable kind
of a situation you know you struggled and you've you know thought a lot about this so
I'm very happy that we had this conversation I was excited I don't usually get excited
talking to new people but it's for the good reason great so much for having yeah absolutely
let me ask you the last question that I ask all my guests that if you come across an intelligent
alien from a different civilization what would you say the worst thing humanity has done
and what would you say is their greatest achievement the worst thing humanity has done is just
this dehumanizing of each other like likely we live in this empathy crisis where for some
reason we've just dehumanized each other we don't think of you know we've detached from
these people in this other country or this either you know these people who live in the
middle of the United States like we've just dehumanized and it's led to this very polarized
world I'm hoping this pandemic will fix some of that so I think that's kind of the worst
thing we've done maybe because it has a lot of implications on what we build and how we
use technology against each other so so that's that best thing we've done what is the best
thing we've done I don't know that's a tough question I think actually I'm a huge traveler
it's part of who we are as a family and the ability to visit other cultures and other
countries and and you know you know for me to grow up in the Middle East and then be
able to end up in this country and I think that's really powerful so this kind of cross
border ability to travel and explore the ability to travel and explore I think would be my
best thing we have figured out as humans.